Hello, this is John from
Caveofprogramming.com.
And welcome to the Cave of Programming
premium Java GUI Swing programming
tutorial series.
And in this series of at the moment 86
tutorials.
We gonna be covering [UNKNOWN] programing
in java swing, pretty much from scratch.
Well, absolutely from scratch all the way
to some really advance topics.
So, as long as you know some some java
you should be able to follow the series of
tutorials.
Now in the series we gonna look at
everything.
From creating database driven applications
like this one here, and
we're gonna take a look at JDBC connecting
to databases.
All the way to creating simple games.
So, we're gonna look at creating applets
as well that you can run
in a browser, and how you handle collision
detection and animation, and that kind.
Kind of thing and we're gonna look at
basically pretty much all the swing user
interface widgets
that you can use, convo boxes and trees
and top panes and dialog boxes, the whole
lot.
And this series of tutorials is structured
in such a way
that if you wanna know a particular topic
you can just look.
At that particular tutorial, and hopefully
will tell you what you want to know.
But if you also, on the other hand, want a
structured kind
of introduction to Swing programming, then
you can work through the tutorials
one-by-one.
Because they do follow one, one from the
other,
and we'll systematically build complete
programs, two complete programs.
In this series and we'll be talking about
how
to structure your code and we'll be
talking about
model view controller and all this all
these kinds
of topics that you'll need to successfully
build swing applications.
And I'll also touch on using visual
designer
incase you wanna design your applications
visually, but
with swing you really kind of need to know
what you're doing in terms of code.
And for that reason, most of the tutorials
are gonna be coding stuff by hand.
And we're gonna be really digging into
the underlying concepts and see how
something works.
In this introductory tutorial I'm just
gonna show you
a few useful resources that you might
wanna know.
I'm just gonna tell you before that very
quickly a bit about my background.
I've been a software developer and now a
trainer for I don't know around fifteen,
fourteen fifteen, years now and I've
worked for places like CSC.
Proquest, SBSS, AT and T, a whole bunch of
acronyms
and in this series of tutorials I'm gonna
share with you.
And pretty much everything I know about
swing programming.
So, hopefully you'll be able to
successfully create your own swing
programs, and even if you wanna go onto
other kinds of interface design using
different technologies then Knowing how to
swing will stand you in good stead.
Because a, a lot of the concepts that you
find in swing are kinda
general software development concepts that
are used
in other kind of visual [UNKNOWN] systems.
Everything that we're gonna be using in
this series of tutorials is free.
And, and that includes Eclipse, Eclipse ID
for Java developers.
Which is a free download.
It's completely free to use and it's
pretty much the industry standard.
But if you wanna use a different IDE like
NetBeans or IntelliJ IDEA,
then you will find the stuff that you
learn here very, very trans, transferable.
You'll have no problem doing this stuff in
a different IDE.
And we're gonna look at this window
builder pro GUI designer which
is a plug-in to Eclipse, you can also use
NetBeans for example.
Now, on to some useful resources for this
series of tutorials if
you go to Google and you search for window
window builder
pro, that's actually this is a product for
visually designing stuff that was.
Purchased by Google I think and released
as a
free designer, so you can find details on
that here
as an eclipse plug-in and that's, that's
very nice to
use, although you will, as I say, want to
learn.
How to create swing swing components,
swing applications by
hand as well to really successfully use
the visual designer.
And if you search for your clips ID for
Java developers, that will
give you a link to the IDE that we'll be
using throughout this series.
Of tutorials, IDEs, integrated development
environment, of course
and, some more useful resources are if you
search for visual guide swing components.
Then here you will get a link to all the
different visual swing components you
can use, and you get example code if you
click on any one of them.
And in the suitor tutorials we'll be
covering some
tips and tricks that you might not find
here,
but and this also really a hell of a lot
of stuff here in these in these examples.
That for reasons of time.
I haven't covered in the tutorials.
So, this is really good, resource to use
and you'll probably also want the visual
guide for to swing layouts because, to
arrange components in swing you use layout
managers.
And this shows you each one visually.
And again, you can click on the links to
get example code.
And finally, you will want to use the API
documents possibly
you may want to refer to particular API
documents in Java.
And swing is actual the user interface
toolkit that's built into Java.
So, if for example you type Jcombobox,
combo
box Java 7 and click on this link here.
You can find all the different methods and
all
the different things you can do with a
combo box.
And a lot of people are intimidated by
this documentation but.
It is released for once you have a basic
idea of knowing what you're doing.
It gives you all of the different methods
you can use.
Okay, so that's it for this introduction.
And in the next tutorial, we're going to
get on designing our first Hello World
swing program.
So join me again then and until next time,
happy coding.
[SOUND]