Hi, welcome back.
And in this tutorial we're going to look
at creating a basic Hello World Swing
application.
So, I've got clips running here.
I'm going to click on this workbench icon.
And if you're using a different IDE then
it's going
to work pretty much the same as it does
any clips.
Because they're all basically similar.
So I'm gonna go into File > New Project,
new job or project, here.
And I'll give this a name, I'll call it
swing1.
And I'm just gonna accept all the
defaults.
And so I'll click Finish.
And I'm gonna right-click my project
folder here or I
could optionally go to the, alternatively
go to the File Menu.
And I'm gonna do New > Class, and I'm
going to call this Class App, and
I'm going to tick this check box here to
generate a main method automatically.
So, this is just an ordinary kind of Hello
World Java program
without the Hello World, but I can already
run that by clicking the green Run button.
And it would just run and finish.
So, I want to run it as a Java
application.
There we go.
And now I wanna turn this into a basic
swing program.
So we're gonna be using classes from
the built-in Java swing window toolkit
package.
And they mostly begin with J.
And in this tutorial I'm going to be using
one called JFrame.
So, I'll create a variable, I've type
JFrame which I'll call frame.
And I'll set that equal to a new JFrame.
And in the constructor here I can pass in
a string which will be the title of my
window.
So I'm going to set that equal to hello
world, like that.
Now the the JFrame, is not visible, by
default.
And to make it visible, you have to call a
method called set visible.
But before I do that actually, I'm gonna
add the import.
Which I could do by clicking on this error
icon here and going to Import JFrame
or, in Eclipse, you can do Ctrl+Shift+O
which
stands for organize imports and that does
the trick.
So, I've imported Java.swing.JFrame.
And now to make the frame visible, I'm
gonna do frame.set visible,
brackets true, and that's all there is to
an absolutely minimal swing
program, but as you'll see in a second,
it's not very satisfactory,
so if I run this, it creates this tiny
window up here.
And I can expand it and it's got the title
Hello World there.
And if I click the cross in the corner
here, let's get rid of it.
The application doesn't actually quit.
And the way that you know that is usually
you'll see like a red button down
in the bottom right corner here in Eclipse
and I think it's pretty similar in,
NetBeans [UNKNOWN].
If you don't see it like I'm not seeing it
now, then, in Eclipse, go
to Window > Show View > Console and then
you'll see that button there.
And the fact that it's red tells me that
the
application is actually still running even
though the window is gone.
So let's click that to terminate it.
So now it's finished.
So to fix the two problems there,
I'm gonna do frame.set default, close
operation.
And I'm gonna pass to that a static member
of j frame which is exit on close.
And what that does is it tells the
application to
quit when you click that cross to close
the window.
So, when you close the window, your
application is now going
to terminate and you can see the red
button goes gray.
The other thing that's wrong with that is
its very small, so lets make the size
bigger.
I'll say, frame.setsize, frame.setsize and
let's make this maybe 600 by, I don't
know, 500.
And if I run this.
Now I've got a, quite nice Hello World
program.
Which quits when I click cross.
And there is still a little problem with
this.
Now in in previous versions of Swing, like
I
dunno, maybe Java four, possibly Java
five, I'm not sure.
It used to be the case that this was all
you need for a Hello World swing app.
But, at some point, some started saying
that you need
to run your swing app in a special thread
and I
think this is only of concern if you're
gonna be
doing, multithreading in your swing
application, but better safe than sorry.
What you need to do is, I'm gonna
use a static method of the swing utilities
class.
So, the swing utilities class has a method
called invoke later
and invoke later needs a class implements,
the runnable interface.
So I'm going to implement that interface
with just an anonymous object,
an anonymous class here by saying new
inside the, function brackets there.
Actually, I'll put the semicolon in
already and inside these brackets, I'll
say new runnable like this, new runnable
round brackets.
And then open a curly parenthesis and
Swing has
just put the closing one in automatically
for me.
And the runnable you may know has one
method, called public void run.
And if I click this warning icon here, I
can add this automatically in Eclipse.
Public void run, or I could just type it
on myself.
And let's get rid of this, this stuff
here, a few blank lines and things.
And you just need to put your code here in
this public void run method.
And now you've got a, hopefully more
robust
swing application than runs in the
approved manner.
So, if I run that, it just looks the same
as before.
And but presumably, it won't crash in some
circumstance where
otherwise it would if you hadn't done that
extra step.
But nobody really seems to know, to be
honest with you.
Okay, so in the next tutorial we're going
to start
looking at adding some components to this
basic Swing app.
So, join me again then.
And until then, happy coding.