Hello, this is John, from
caveofprogramming.com
and in this tutorial, we're gonna look
at the border layout, layout manager and
at text areas a little bit.
So, in the last tutorial I showed you how
to create, a
basic application, which looks like this,
such as the window and it's blank.
And in this tutorial, we're gonna start
adding some controls to this window.
Now, this is the point at which swing gets
a little bit complex,, but once you can
get
over this hump you can tackle all kinds of
projects because to actually add
components to a window.
You, need to know something about, layouts
managers and
there are several different layout
managers in, in Java swing.
And the task of layout managers, is to
decide where to put the components in the
window.
And also to kind of move those
components to appropriate locations and
resize them appropriately.
When you expand or contract the window and
that's where a lot of the complexity comes
from.
And we're gonna start with a very simple
layout manager here.
So at the moment if, if I look at this the
code that we've got so far we've just got
a really simple we're creating a frame,
setting the size
of it, setting what happens when you click
across any corner.
And setting it to visible and so that's
the operation when a frame's been set up.
And what I'm gonna do for a start in this
tutorial is something
that you'll probably want to do most of
the time, which is I'm gonna
create my own custom child class version
of JFrame so that I
can put codes in a constructor, that will
add components and we'll do this stuff.
So, let's just right click the Default
Package > New class.
And, I'm gonna create a new class called
Mainframe.
And, and that's gonna extend JFrame.
So a handy tip is to give your child
classes
names that reflect, reflect what kind of
thing they are.
So, if you're creating a customized
button,
call it something gorilla button and the
customize frame, something go to frame, so
on, to kind of help you keep track.
And I'm gonna give this a constructor, so
public name frame like this.
And the first thing I'm gonna do here,
let's take a look at this app again.
So, here, we're setting the title by
calling this constructor
of JFrame and I'm gonna move that code
into here.
I'm gonna say, super to call the super
class constructor and I'm gonna say in
there, hello world, so that's kind of
equivalent to whoops, didn't meant to do
that.
That's kind of equivalent to, this code
here and
now I'm gonna change this JFrame frame
equals new JFrame.
To just a simple command.
New name frame, to create a new class
of the mainframe type, which I'm defining
now.
And let's get rid of that, and let's take
this
code and move it into the constructor of
my new class.
So, my main method is just going to be
very simple.
It's just gonna run this main frame
object.
Save that and I'll go to main frame.
And then in construct I'll paste this in
and now we don't need
this, frame reference because we can call
the methods, of the parent class.
Directly, like this.
so, at the moment.
All I've done now, really, is divide the
existing code into two separate files.
And that will just run as before.
But now, it's kind of, neater to add, more
components to main frame.
Now, the first thing to do when you're
adding components is to set an appropriate
layout manager.
And as I mentioned in the inch dot tree
tutorial, if you go to Google.
Whoops, go to Google and search for visual
guides
layout swing, something like that, you get
this rather handy page.
And this shows you the different kind of
layout managers that you can use.
In a most flexible and complex form which
we will cover later on, this grid
backed layout that lets you put things in
a sort of very, very flexible grid format.
And, but there's several others you can
see,
most of which we'll be covering to some
extent.
And the one that I'm gonna show you here,
is this border layout.
And border layout is often used, to kind
of
sculpt the, the very basic outlines of an
application.
So you could use this type of tool bar at
the top,
let's say, and panels in, you know, in the
middle, left and right.
And maybe something in the bottom, like a
status bar or something.
What border layout does, is it just allows
you to add
components, in the center position or the,
the compass points, basically.
So, let's use that to add a couple of
components.
I'm gonna go here, to my main window and
say, set layout.
And I want to pass that, an object of the
type border layout.
So, I'll say new border layout here.
New border layout, and add the import with
CTRL+SHIFT+O in Eclipse.
And then, let's create a couple of
components that I want to add.
And you'll often want to, create
your components as private instance
variables so
that you can access them from
multiple methods, although, that's not
always necessary.
I'm gonna have here a, a JTextArea.
A text area is a region like this editor,
that I'm
working in here, which just contains a
whole bunch of text.
And if you just want one line of text
you'd use, JTextField and I'll call
that TextArea, and, and I'm also, I'm
gonna add the import.
And then I also have a private JButton.
Let's just call that btn.
And, at the import for JButton.
And you can either create your new
components directly here, in which case
they'll be
created, of course, when a class is
loaded,
or you can create them in your
constructor.
In which case it'll be created when the
object is created.
I, I don't see that it really makes a huge
amount of difference.
Well, I'm gonna say text area here equals
new JTextArea, like that.
And, I'm gonna say button equals new
JButton.
And let's just put some text on that
button, says, click, click me.
And now, I can add those components.
To my main frame, using this layout
manager.
Strictly speaking, I'm adding it to the
content pane of the JFrame.
The content pane is like a panel, that the
JFrame contains, which will contain the
components, but we don't need to worry
about that here, I can simply say add.
Passing the controller I want to add, so
let's say, text barrier and then pass
in a static constant of border layout, to
say where I want to add this control.
So, I'm gonna say border layout dot
center.
Like that, so I can add the text area
right in the middle.
And I'll add the button, in the south
position I'll say, add
button B-T-N, border layout dot south,
like this.
And, so these controls aren't gonna do
anything in a moment,
but now if I run that, I've got this
application here.
And I can click the button, it does
nothing.
And I can type, text in here and so on.
And in the next tutorial, we're gonna look
at
extending this application and starting to
make it do stuff.
So, that's all for this tutorial, join me
again next time, and until next time,
happy coding.