Hi, welcome back.
And in the last tutorial, I showed you how
to create this little application which
doesn't actually do anything.
And in this tutorial, I'm gonna fix it so
when you
click the button, it adds stuff to the
text area here.
So, I'm gonna navigate here to my main
frame and what I
wanna do, what I'm gonna do is, a kind of
common pattern for Swing Apps in general.
I'm gonna listen to one component and when
something happens
in that component, I'm gonna do something
to another component.
So I'm gonna listen to the button and when
the button
is clicked I'm going to add some text into
the text area.
Now the way to do that is firstly, I want
to add a thing called an action listener
to the button.
So, to do that my button is called btn,
and it's this private variable here.
And I'm gonna say btn.addActionListener.
Now action, the add action listener method
takes as its augment a an action listener,
a figure type action listener and action
listener is actually an interface.
So what I could do and perhaps will do in
future tutorials at
some point is I could make Main Frame
implement the Action Listener
interface, and then pass this into this
method.
But, what I'm gonna do instead here is use
an anonymous class.
I'm gonna say new here, inside the
argument brackets.
A new action listener and then, brown
buckets.
So this a bit looks exactly as though
I was creating an object of type action
listener,
which of course isn't legal by itself
because
actually this is not a class, it's an
interface.
But what I can do is, I can open a bracket
here.
And eclipse puts in a closing bracket
automatically, and if I click on this
arrow here, I can go to what I need to
import action listener first.
And then, click on it click on it again, I
can go to Add unimplemented methods.
And the ActionListerner interface just has
this one method action
performed and this method is run whenever
the button is clicked.
So, let's get rid of some of these extra
lines here.
I'm just doing Ctrl+D to delete them and,
in
here, what I want to do is append some
text.
Text to the text area.
And to do that, I'm gonna say
textarea.append
and that accepts a string and I'll pass
the string hello and I'll put, also
backslash end there to add a new line at
the end of each string and of each hello.
So, I'm listening to the button by setting
an
action listener on it, which is this
anonymous class.
And within the method, the action
performed method of the
anonymous class, I'm directly invoking a
method of the text area.
And I was gonna say, this is quite a
common
pattern, in swing, or in GUI applications
in general, I suppose.
So if I run that now, I need to select
the, main program here, and run that.
Now, if I click the bottom, you can see it
adds, a load, to the text area.
Okay, so that's it for this tutorial.
And in, in the next part of this tutorial
series, I'm gonna show you how to begin to
break up a Swing application into separate
classes, separate custom components.
And we're gonna add a toolbar to this.
And we're gonna add some scroll bars to
the text pane.
And we're gonna have the toolbar in the
text area as two separate kind of custom
components.
So until next time, happy coding.