Hello, this is John from
caveofprogramming.com again.
And in this tutorial we're gonna look at
how
to take this text area in our basic Swing
application
and turn it into a simple custom
component, and we're
also gonna add some scroll bars to this
text area.
So, at the moment the way this works is if
I look at main
out, I've just got a text area, which I'm
adding directly into the, main frame.
And, what I want to do is to begin to
break this application down, simple,
though, it is into separate components.
So, that we can work and each component
can kind of take care of itself, and that
the application as a whole, is basically
simplified as we add more stuff to it.
So what I'll do is I'll create a new class
here.
So new class and I'm gonna use something
called a jPanel
and I'm gonna call my custom component my,
my custom
class here, I'm gonna call it text panel
because it's a kind of panel.
And I'm gonna say that the Superclass of
text panel here is gonna be a jPanel.
So, I'll click Finish.
And, at the input there, and panels are,
basically, just kind of
depending on your operating system colors,
usually just sort of like gray flat areas.
Which you can add to your main frame.
But the great thing about them is that you
can add other components into them.
And that's what I'm gonna do here.
So to start with, I will just go back
here.
And, so currently I'm adding a text area
and instead of this text
area, I'm gonna get rid of it for the
moment and say private
text panel which is the class I just
created.
I'll call that text panel
and down here where I created the text
area previously, I'll say text
panel equals new text panel
and here I'll add the text panel instead
of the text area.
And for the moment, I'm just gonna comment
this out, comment out this bit where in
response
to the button click here, we pan text to
the panel, so I just comment this out.
And if I run that now, this is what our
panel looks like, doesn't
do anything, I can't add text to it or
click on it or anything.
I can click on it, but nothing happens and
so now I'm gonna add
a text area into this panel and turn it
into a kind of custom control.
And, so, the way to do that is I'll go to
this text panel class and I'll get an
constructor public text panel and in the
constructor, I'll create a text area
so in fact I'll put a private j text area
here, text area.
And in the constructor, I'll say that text
area equals a new j text area.
And let's add the import, and I'm
gonna actually, I could just, well, I
could set the layout on the text
panel, and I want this, I actually want
this text
area, for the moment, just to take up the
whole panel.
And I can use again border layout, so say
set
layout, new border layout, so this is
actually setting the layout.
Not on the mainframe but on the the jPanel
here, on the
text panel which is just a kind of jPanel
because it extends jPanel.
So I'll say, set layer, new border layer
and then I can just do
that bad text area and border
layout.center.
So it's very simple.
And I'm just gonna be adding in the
center, and
since I'm adding nothing to the north,
south, east or
west, this text panel is just gonna take
up the
entire area of the panel, which is what I
want.
Except that I'm gonna do something very
slightly different here because I want the
text
panel to have scrollbars, if the text
kinda goes off the edge or off the bottom.
So, to achieve that I just say here new
JScrollPane
and to the constructor of this scroll pane
I'll pass the textarea.
So, what I'm doing is just wrapping the
text area
in a j-scroll pane and now if I run this,
you
can see I've got, we've got this this is
the text
panel and it's got this nice text area in
it now.
And if I just put more text in than
there's
room for, I get this, this scroll, scroll
bar appears.
And the same if I hit return a bit,
like a vertical scroll bar here, which is
very nice.
And you can use scroll bars with.
All kinds of different swing components.
And, just wrap them in a j scroll pane.
Now I want our text into my custom my text
panel, my custom component, when the
button is clicked as before.
So what I'll do is I'll give this a public
method called let's make it public void.
And append, appendText maybe.
And that can accept a String, called text,
and
in this method I'll just call textarea, so
the instance variable text area up here.
Textarea.append again and I'll just add
the text in there like that.
So now to hook this on, get it working
just as it was before, all I
have to do is back in my main frame here I
can just call text panel.
So it was textarea.append, and now it's
textpanel.append, so I just call it append
text,
yeah, append text, and if I run that, and
click it, there you go.
Okay.
Now you see that the strategy I'm using
here, that I'm working towards is,
that the mainframe is creating lots of
different components, just two at the
moment actually.
And, and those components can each
be potentially quite sophisticated in
themselves.
And this is the beginning of a kind of
model for your
controller architecture, which we'll get
into a bit more as the tutorials progress.
Now in the next tutorial we're gonna look
at adding a toolbar.
So I'm gonna move that button to a
toolbar.
And we're gonna have a second custom
component instead of this button here.
So, join me again next time, and until
then, happy coding.
[SOUND]