Hello, this is John from Cave of
Programming and,
this is, a tutorial of creating two balls
and slim.
So, we're just gonna look at a
really, really very basic toolbar, in this
tutorial.
So, in the last tutorial we, we created
this little
app here, [SOUND] and if you click a
button [SOUND]
it just outputs a low there and what I
want
to is to have this button in a tool bar.
[SOUND] So, at the moment the structure of
this application now is,
I've got a very, very simple main
application that just does new MainFrame.
I've got a MainFrame class and the
MainFrame cr, creates two components,
a button and a text panel, and it adds
them to itself.
And it listens to the button, and, when
you click the button, it.
[SOUND] sends a command to the, text area,
the text panel.
And I've also got this text panel
component.
Basically it's a JPanel with a scroll pane
embedded in
it and a text area embedded in the scroll
pane.
[SOUND] Okay then, so let's take a look.
What I wanna do is, create a new class for
start, that's gonna be the tool bar.
So this is a, this is a new, custom
component.
So, I'll go to, I'll right click and go to
new, class
[SOUND] and, or I could go to file menu
and do new class.
And I'm gonna call this, [SOUND] toolbar,
and once again, as last time,
as in the last tutorial, [SOUND] I'm gonna
make this extend the JPanel
class, so click Finish, so public class
toolbar extends JPanel.
Let's add in the import.
And to get this a constructor, set public
[SOUND] toolbar like this.
Now if I go back to my MainFrame class,
I can already add a panel instead of the,
button.
And I wanna add it at the top, of course,
instead of the bottom.
So let's, here, create private [SOUND]
private variable of type toolbar.
[SOUND] And I'll call it toolbar.
And, here [SOUND] I can say toolbar in the
constructor, tool bar equals new tool bar.
[SOUND] And then down here,.
I can, just where I'm adding the
components, I could just, have a new add.
I can say add.
[SOUND] Now if I copy that first, Ctrl+C,
Ctrl+V.
[SOUND] I can say, add toolbar
atBorderLayout.north.
[SOUND] To add it at the top.
Now if I run this now I'm not gonna see a
whole, a whole lot.
Because, this panel's automatically sizing
to almost
nothing because there's nothing in it yet.
[SOUND] So, let's fix that I'll go into
the toolbar and let's
add two buttons to the tool bar to be
going on with.
[SOUND] So, let's have a private a private
J button and I'll call this.
Because I'm not quite sure what this
application's gonna do at the moment.
It's just demoing, the kind of theory of
it really.
I'll call this button one.
Well, let's call it anobutton.
How's that?
And then, [SOUND] I'll have a private
JButton, [SOUND] Goodbye button.
Goodbye button.
[SOUND] And of course, I wanna say in
the constructor, that the HelloButton =
new JButton.
[SOUND] Let's give it some text, or label,
Hello.
And the goodbyeButton = new
JButton(*GoodBye*).
[SOUND] Sounding a bit like a Paul
McCartney song, but nevermind.
Okay, and, and now I wanna add those
buttons.
To the, toolbar.
And, I'm gonna use something called flow
layout
because I don't wanna use boarder layout
here on
this panel, because I don't wanna add the
button at their North South center East to
West.
And you can only add one com, component.
Each position there.
What I wanna do is I wanna add them, kind
of from left to right.
And this say, layout manager does that.
And it's called, flow layout.
So we're gonna do set layout, [SOUND] new
flow layout.
And as I mentioned in their introductory,
tutorial.
If you, set your visual guide swing
layouts, you'll find
a guide to different layouts and you'll
find this, among it.
So if you set flow layout, all you have to
do is do add just add your components
without, like this.
And add, [SOUND] Goodbye button, like so.
And now if I run this now, I got two
buttons that are right in the middle.
[SOUND] And to get them over to the left,
I can pass
an argument to the constructor, the flow
lay out, lay out manager.
I can use flow lay out.left, like this
and that's gonna align my, components to
the left.
And by the way, you might wonder if you
can get
flow, flow layout to add components,
vertically and the answer is no.
I don't know why not, but there you go.
So if I run that, now I've got two
buttons on the toolbar that's beginning to
look, rather nice.
It doesn't do anything, yet my old button,
still works.
Now I wanna change these so that I wanna
get rid of this button down here and
I wanna make it so that if I, if I click
this button here, it outputs hello here.
And if I click this, it outputs, Goodbye,
in this text area.
And to do that we're gonna have to tackle,
one of the key, key things in, swing
development, which is creating a listener
and listening to a, a custom component.
I'm gonna show you a very simple
technique, to do that in the, next
tutorial.
So, join me again then, and until then,
happy coding.
[SOUND]