Hi, this is John from Cave on Programming
dot com and in the
last tutorial I showed you how to create
this little application here, and
at the moment, this button adds stuff to
this text area and these
button in this little toolbar don't do
anything but I want them to add.
Text to the text area instead of this
button.
Now the challenge here is, if I look at
the code and I go to the mainframe, so the
mainframe is adding a toolbar that I've
created, with
custom components that I showed you how to
create earlier.
it's adding this.
Custom text panel component.
But how do you get communication going
between the two?
And I'll show you what you could do and
then we'll look at the problems with that.
And we'll look at how to improve it.
So what you really want ideally, is
something like this.
Where you've got a listener kind of model
where you're listening to one component.
And when something happens in that
component, it invokes a
method and then you tell another component
what to do directly.
So the main frame class here is, it's
acting as what
we call a controller and if you are total
familiar controller architecture,
then you'll recognize it in the main
frame, is the
controller here is, hocking together the
components and telling them what to do.
And if you're not familiar with it, don't
worry,
because you will be by the end of this
course.
So, now what I want to do is the simplest
thing to do and, this is not the best
thing.
Will be to pass a reference to the text
panel to the tool bar
and then get the tool bar to cause a
method in the text panel.
So, let's look at how that would work.
And what I want to do really, is firstly I
gotta pass the text panel to the tool bar
somehow.
So I'll have to give the tool bar a method
called, let's say set text panel and then
I'll pass in.
And reference to the text panel.
The text panel of course is created here.
And here I am just passing this reference
to it.
So it's a walk in cabinet, you can get at
it.
And I'm going to implement this message,
set text panel, so let's do that.
And I'll go to tool bar, and I'll give it
a.
Public void set text panel.
Text panel accepts a text panel, like this
and
now when these buttons are clicked, I want
them to do something with this text
panel, so that I can pass this nest to
these buttons, and.
Cuz it were two very similar buttons here.
What I do is I need to add actions
listeners to these buttons so that I can.
So that basically the toolbar is listening
to the buttons on it
and it can respawn when they are click,
when they are clicked.
So I'm gonna make this toolbar implement
action listener like this.
And implement action listener.
I'll add the import there and Implements
Action Listener, there we go.
And then, if I click this arrow I can add
unimplemented
methods and I've added the Action Perform
Method
to, to the toolbar itself, and that means
I can
then do helloButton.addActionListener
this,
and goodByeButton.addActionListener this.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And just to see, if this works.
Here in the actionPerformMethod I could
just do a
sys out and, I'll put some text in here.
I'll put a button has been clicked, and if
I run this application now.
And it's always a good idea to run your
application frequently, and put
debugging messages here to check that it's
working as you expect at every stage.
If I just save that, and then.
Run it.
If I click these buttons, you can see that
down
in the, in the console I'm getting some
text output.
Now the first kinda defect here before I
mess about with this text
panel any further is that I want to know
which button has been clicked.
Clicked.
And I can do that.
Let's rename this Arg Naught.
So the actual perform method receives an
action event.
And let's call that E, for event.
And let's say
I can say.
J button clicked equals e dot get source.
And e, e dot get source.
Retrieves the actual source of the event.
Which in this case will be one of these
two buttons.
And it returns an object, but because I
know
that I've only added the action list here
to buttons.
I can just cast this to a J button.
So, now clicked will be the actual button
that
was clicked and the info this action
performed event.
File is action listener thing here.
I can then say if clicked, equals equals
hello
button, in other words, if the source is
just a reference here,
if this is a reference to this button, and
points,
and point to the same place as this, so if
clicked.
Click is equal to hello button, then sys
out hello.
Else, sys out goodbye.
Good bye.
And so if I run that, let's check that it
works, and I click hello, and it says
hello down here.
I click goodbye, and it says, goodbye,
which is perfect.
And now, I just wanna hook this up with
the, with the text panel.
So I can, I need to get this text panel
reference
somehow, into this method, and to do that,
of course, I just.
Let's use a private instance variable, so
private text panel,
text panel, and then in the set method, I
can just say
this dot text panel equals
text panel, so the private instance text
panel equals the one that's passed in.
And now finally.
Finally, in down here I can say
textPanel.append
text hello / and for a new line.
And if the goodbye button is clicked
then.
In fact no we'll say goodbye.
I thought maybe we'd be a bit clearer here
if I would say.
Else if clicked equals goodbye button.
Now if I run this, and I click,
and it says Hello in the text panel and
Goodbye, it says goodbye.
Get rid of this, this button here.
The button that I originally added in the
first place because
I don't want it anymore, so let's get rid
of all this.
Now, this basically gets your application
up and running.
And it works.
As you can see.
But, there's some major disadvantages
here.
To doing it like this because.
What you really want is you want your
swing application to be made up
of separate components that know as little
about each other as possible.
And the way I've written this in a moment.
The toolbar is inextricably linked to the
text panel.
The toolbar is tightly coupled with the
And we say in lingo it can call any method
of text panel
and you can't have a toolbar here without
there being a text panel.
It's not terribly reusable.
And if you look at your application and,
bear in mind, that
it could soon be much more complex than,
than it is now.
If you wanna debug the communication here
that's going
on that's causing these buttons to result
in this happening.
It's gonna be ultimately a bit of a
mystery.
Where to look for it.
What you really want is, you want to be
able to say okay, there's communication
happening to components.
That's happening in my controller.
My controller is the main frame, and the
communication should be hooked up here.
But instead what's happening is there's
communication going on.
Basically directly between the text panel,
between the toolbar and the text panel.
And if you carry on writing a whole
application
like this, it's gonna start resembling a
rat's nest.
And that's why in the next tutorial, we're
gonna look at.
A bit of a better way to do this.
And we're gonna look at how to separate
more cleanly your toolbar from your
toolbar custom component from your this J
Text Area custom component.
And the object is that will provide you
with a model for building up really
complex Swing applications, and keeping
them from getting into a rat's nest.
Okay, so.
And, join me again next time, and until
next time, happy coding.
[BLANK_AUDIO]