Hello again, this is John from
caveofprograming.com
and this is a tutorial on how to
separate your components in your swing
application
to maintain that kind of simple clear
architecture.
So in the last tutorial I showed you how
to.
Play this little app and the problem with
this is that I've got a tightly coupled
tool bar and text area and I've got my
main frame here, which is responsible.
It's more for creating the components I've
got
two components, the toolbar and a text
panel.
But the trouble is that the toolbar
is communicating, directly with the text
panel which
is not healthy, because we want all
communication
to go through our controller, the main
frame.
Now, to do that, I'm gonna just use, to
start with, a simple interface, because,
I wanna have the idea of a thing that can
receive messages, that
contain strings, so all the toolbar
already does in a moment, is,
It's, when you click, when you click one
of those two buttons, it sort of emits
a string that's either hello or goodbye.
And the first step here is I want to
codify the
idea of a thing that can receive that
hello or goodbye string.
So, what I'll do is, I'll go to New.
Interface.
And I'll call this interface let's call it
StringListener.
How's that?
It's not too important.
And I'm gonna give StringListener one
method header.
I'll make it public void.
and, let's call it I don't know actually.
Let's call it string or text.
Well, I'll tell you what.
Let's look at main frame.
In fact, let's look at the toolbar.
So when you listen to a event on a button,
you have an action list now.
So, the, Action list interact has this
action performed method in it.
And anything that wants to listen to a
button, has to have the action perform
method.
So in this interface, let's give this text
performed.
Or maybe a text emitted method.
I think that'll do.
Okay.
I made that a type string and so
so what's this saying is that anything
that implements.
This string this interface has to have
a method called textEmitted that accepts a
string,
and now, the beauty of this is that
I can in my toolbar I can make it fire an
event.
To a listener that implements this.
If someone clicks a button.
So let's see how that would work.
Basically instead of a text panel here,
I'm gonna give it a private variable of
type StringListener and I'll call that
textListener.
And, I need a method for setting this
string listener.
So, in the moment, I've got a method
called set text panel.
I'm gonna change that, get rid of that.
I'm gonna have a method.
Public void set and I'll call it
setStringListener like this and the
setStringListener method
accepts any object that implements the
StringListener interface.
Let's call up listener.
And what it does with it, is it saves a
reference to this up here.
So let's say this .textlistener, this
.textlistener equals listener.
So, what I want, what I'm doing now is and
let's just get
rid of this comment out the references to
text pannel for the moment.
So in my toolbar I've given it a variable
of type stringListener.
The stringList interface just says that an
object should have one method called
textOmitted which accepts a string and
I've supplied the toolbar with a method.
To set this textlitner here.
Now in my main frame, the beauty of this
is I can say toolbar.settext.
Listener sets string listener, sorry, sets
string listener.
And then I can use an anonymous clip.
Class, just as I do with the buttons here.
So with the button you can do, actually
this isn't an anonymous class, but in
an earlier tutorial I showed you how to
use an anonymous class for the button.
And the action listener.
We're going to do the same thing here.
So I'll say, set string is snap.
A new string listener as the old string
listener was class and open a bracket and
so Eclipse put in a closing bracket here
and I just need to.
To add the missing methods, I don't add
unimplemented methods, and at
the moment I just output this text here so
let's get rid of some of this extra space.
So my stringListener class just has this
text emitted
method and at the moment it's just gonna
print.
Print out the text here.
And now.
in the tool bar, when a button is
clicked, if the hello button's clicked,
I'm gonna say
if, if the text listener.
Has been set.
So if it's not, not equal to null.
Not equal to null.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Then, I can say text listener.
And call the um,text omitted method of
text listener and pass in hello.
Because the hello button's been clicked at
this point.
I can do the same, if the goodbye button's
been clicked.
And here we go.
Goodbye.
And now finally, the final step here, is
the, in the main frame.
If this text emitter thing happens first.
We'll let's first run it and see if it
works.
So let's minimize the editor here, go to
my swinger,
and click hello and goodbye, and you can
see that that's working.
There's a little more space than I.
I expected.
That's because I've got a print and our
language also adds on a new line, but now
all I've got to do is get the textPanel
and call textPanel.appendtext text.
So if I run that and I've got the same
results as before.
Now don't worry if this seems pretty
complex because it
is a little bit complicated, but when you
get your head
around this you've understood Basically
the most important facts about getting
the communication work working, getting
your components wired together, in swing.
And the whole trick to it is is that you
have one component
where you set some kind of listener or add
some kind of listener.
And a controller and some kind of central
communication.
Switch board listens listens to that those
messages and
tells for the components what to do when
the
messages occur and so, I got this method
here
this all is interface enables me basically
to separate.
The toolbar and the text area.
And, so the toolbar now doesn't know
anything about the text area.
There's no reference to text areas in this
button.
All there is, is a reference to a string
listener which could
be any kind of class, because all the
toolbar cares about is that.
So the string listener should have some
methical text
emitted so that the tool bar can call that
method when a button is clicked, and
that's all
the tool bar has to know about or care
about.
And in the main frame, the main frame
intercepts these method calls.
So the tool bar is basically when a
button's clicked, it's calling
the text emitted method which is actually
the method of this synonymous
class here, so it's calling this and that,
and then, in here,
in the controller, the main frame, with an
append.text to the text panel.
By calling a method that we added to text
panel.
And that is, that is pretty tricky.
But if you just kind of have a look at the
code
and type this out yourself, you will get
the hang of it.
And if, if it seems.
Particularly complex.
It's almost not worth worrying about it
too much.
If you just type it out then maybe, I
don't know, type it out again like a day
later.
You know, with variations, of course, to
make it interesting.
Then.
It will start to sink into your synapses,
and you will understand how it works.
And when you've understood this, you've
basically got the swing.
And, using this technique, you can build
up very complex swing gaps.
And you can keep the communications simple
between components
and they won't turn into, hopefully, a
rat's nest.
I'm just gonna mention very quickly here
that if you, this is
called set stringlistener, but you often
see methods called add actionlistener for
example.
And that's because you can add multiple
listeners to swing.
Components.
And what I do with it is, instead of
having
the single reference they have like an
array list of references.
And in fact, and they just iterate through
our
array list and notify any listener that's
been added anywhere.
And we might look at that in a future
tutorial if it comes up.
But this.
Simple technique, relatively simple, will
get you through most cases.
Okay, so join me again for the next
tutorial,
when I'm not quite sure what we're gonna
do.
But we're gonna further work on this swing
application.
And make it a bit more interesting.
So until then, happy coding.