[SOUND] Hello again, this is John
from caveofprogramming.com, and in this
tutorial we're
gonna look at sizing components, so in our
last tutorial I created this.
And what I'm gonna do with this
application is,
I'm gonna let a panel on the left, which
is
gonna be a form, so it's gonna contain
some text
fields for entering data and a button to
submit data.
So an, in the context of that, I'm gonna
show
you, I'm gonna explain a bit about sizing
things in swing.
So, to start with I'm gonna add a new
class in here, which I will, which once
again, is gonna expand JPanel, and I'm
gonna, I'm gonna call it form panel.
And it's gonna, actually I'll just click
finish that.
And by hand I'll type extends j panel just
for variation.
So this is a kind of j panel and I'm gonna
give it a constructor.
So form panel, [SOUND] and I'm gonna add
this to the main frame.
So it goes to the main frame.
Okay, let private [SOUND] form, form, if I
can
get it cut to left there, form panel, form
panel.
And let's say form panel equals, equals
new form panel.
And I'm gonna add that on the left-hand
side, so, in the west location, so add
form panel borderlayout.west.
Now if I run this
so I need to select this App here it's
added the panel
but it's it's very narrow, and I want that
panel to be wider.
Now with some components under some
circumstances, for example main frame
you can just do set size but usually what
happens is, you're adding a component.
Using a layout manager.
And it's actually the layout manager that
determines the size of the component.
And in order to tell the layout managers
what size and the components want
to be, the components have anything called
a preferred size.
So to show you if I go to this form panel.
Now, preferred size is actually there's
actually a method called get preferred
size.
And that returns a object called
dimension.
So I'll call it dimension dim.
And I'll say equals
get preferred size, get preferred size.
And if I do [UNKNOWN] on dim I'm not too
sure if dimension has a two stream method.
Yeah, it does.
Okay, so we can see that the preferred
size of
this panel is ten units wide and ten units
high.
Nevertheless, it's actually spanning the
entire vertical height here.
And the reason for that is, although the
component can have a preferred size.
The layout manager will not necessarily
respect
it and some layout managers ignore it
completely.
But for border layout here it's gonna use
it judiciously.
So what I can do here to resize the panel
is I can say dim.set in fact, I
can say dim.width and change the width to
let's say 250 pixels.
And I can call setPreferredSize,
setPreferredSize, dim.
Like this.
So I've got the preferred size.
And I set the width to 50.
And then I've called setPreferredSize.
And here I could've just done, new
dimension, and, and given it some dummy,
height.
Because, as we can see, the border layout
manager is
not respect the height anyway but it will
respect the width.
So if I run this we've got now a wider
panel that's easier to add controls into.
And, and I think if I remember rightly,
that preferred size will also work with
buttons.
In the Gridbag layout manager because
shortly
in a couple of tutorials, we're gonna look
at how you use a layout manager called
Gridbag layout to add controls onto the
form.
But that's coming shortly.
So in the next tutorial we're gonna give
the form a nice looking border.
So join me again then.
And until then, happy coding.
[SOUND]