Hello there, this is John from
Caveofprogramming.com.
And in the last tutorial I created this,
so there's a panel here, which I'm gonna
write the controls into, but in this
tutorial
I wanna give this panel a suitable border.
Now to give a component the border.
You can say set border, so I'm in a
constructor
of the form panel class here, which extend
straight panel.
And I could pass in there, I'm going to
use a static method of border factory
called create and
let's pick one of these methods and the
one
that I use is, all of these create
different borders.
But I use Create Titled Border and I'll
pass in a title at Person.
This is gonna be a form for adding people
into some kind of database.
And if I run that it looks like this.
It's quite nice, except that because the
borders are so close to
the edges of the panel you can almost not
see the border.
So what I could do about that, is I could
add a second border around this border.
Which is just an invisible border that
just creates some space.
So I'm gonna start by taking this out of
the set
border called, and I'll say border inner
border,
equals, borderfactory.create, title
border, and
then I'll say border, outer border, equals
border factory,
border factory.create.
And I want empty border here.
And I want to be able to specify the
margin all the way around.
Set our margin of five pixels for left,
right, top, and bottom.
And now to combine these two borders
together, and set
border, I can pass border factory, top
create compound border
and I can pass that an outer border and a
inner border.
Inner border, which are the ones operating
already.
So if I run that you can see that now it's
indented a little bit.
It might be interesting to add a border to
my tool bar.
As well, let's just try that and see what
it looks like.
I might remove this again, though.
So, if I go to my tool bar, here in the
constructor of my tool bar.
I can say let's maybe put it here.
Set border, border factory.create, maybe
just edged border.
Let's try that, let's see what it looks
like.
And there's also bevel, bevel borders and
things like that.
So now I got a border around my tool bar
which I may or may not get rid of later.
So that's borders for you and you
can experiment with different kinds of
borders.
Raised borders, lowered board, lowered
borders and so on.
And, and in the next tutorial we're gonna
have a look at text fields and labels.
So join me again, and join me again then,
and until then, happy coding.