Hello there.
In this tutorial we're gonna look at text
fields and labels, in Swing.
So in the last tutorial I created this
little application and I
wanna add here a couple of little text
fields for entering information.
And also a couple of, labels to say what
the
text fields are and underneath I want to
have a button.
So, that you can click the button to
submit the information.
and, to do that I'm gonna start by going
to Font panel, and I'm gonna
give it some number variables which will
be
the controls, I'm gonna use in the panel.
So I'll have two labels, JLabel, [SOUND]
and
I'm gonna call one of them, Name Label.
New send new, actually I'll do the new in
the constructor so I'll call it, [SOUND]
NameLabel here.
And private JLabel, occupation level,
because this is gonna
be a form for adding some information
about people.
And it's sort of private JTextField.
Now, a JTextField is, a single line field
of text like this kinda thing here.
As opposed to a text area which is a
whole, area like the editor I'm in here.
So I want a JTextField named field,
[SOUND] and a
private JTextField, occupationField.
And I'm also gonna have a button to submit
the information, so I'll say
private JButton, [SOUND] and I'll just
call that okBtn, OK button.
So now in the constructor I'm gonna,
actually create, create those objects.
So I'll say, nameLabel equals new JLabel.
And I'll give this some text here in the,
in
the constructor parameter which is gonna
be, [SOUND] name colon.
And the.
Occupation label is gonna be, [SOUND]
occupation
label is gonna be new JLabel [SOUND]
occupation.
Occupation.
And, the the name field, name field.
Is going to be a new JLabel, it's going to
be sorry, a new JTextField.
And now the important thing here is when
you create, create your
text field, you have to specify how many
characters wide it should be.
And the strange thing is that the text
fields
always appear wider than the number of
characters would suggest.
As far as I know, this is supposed to
represent, [SOUND] characters it's just
that it's a bit off.
Okay so, and I'm also gonna have
occupationField equals new JTextField,
I'll make that ten as well, we can always
change the size later.
And finally the button, so.
OkayBtn, and notice I'm spacing out my
code here,
[SOUND] into distinct sections using blank
lines, which helps legibility.
So equals new, [SOUND] JButton, and I'll
just give that the label here.
Okay.
And now I'm gonna leave it there, for this
tutorial.
Because in the next tutorial, we're gonna
get to something that's,
probably the second most complex thing
after the whole event listener business.
And that's the grid back layout.
Which is an extremely flexible way but a
bit tricky, of laying out your components
in Swing.
So, join me again for that tutorial and
until then, happy coding.
[BLANK_AUDIO]