[SOUND] Hello this is John from
Kevolveprogramming.com and in this
tutorial, we'll gonna log cuts, grid back
layout, which is layout manager.
So in the last tutorial, I created this
little,.
Program.
And in this panel here, I've actually
given
it, it's called form panel and I've
actually
given it some, some text fields and
labels,
which I now want to add to the panel.
And to do that I'm gonna use the most
powerful but also perhaps the trickiest of
the layout managers and you're probably
gonna wonder, as I show you this, if
it isn't easier to use a visual designer,
such as the Window Builder Pro, which
is free, a free Eclipse plugin I showed
you in the first tutorial in the series.
And the answer is that it could be perhaps
quicker but the
window the visual designers for Java at
the moment don't seem to be very good,
to be honest and you kind of, it's gonna
help a lot if
you know this stuff anyway and all the
Java Developers that I've actually worked.
Out with, or moan.
And, personally have pretty much shunned
visual
designers in favor of doing this by hand.
This seems to be a real culture of it in
Java.
And you'll probably see why if you start
using the Visual
Designers and you see how rubbish they
are, to be honest.
But, nevertheless, Window Builder Pro is
probably the best of the bunch.
So let's get on with it, having said that
and the
first thing I'm gonna do is I'm gonna say
setLayout
of course setLayout new grid,
GridBagLayout and
GridBagLayout is so flexible that The
developers I've
knows including myself, tend to just stick
with this one layout and we don't really
use for example boxLayout or gridLayout
much.
Because this is so flexible once you've
learned the quirks of this.
You you can pretty much just use this for
most purposes.
So I'm gonna start by, now GridBagLayout.
you, you have a GridBagConstraints object
that you use
with grid back there, so I'll call that GC
and set that equal to a new
grid bag constraints, and
GridBagConstraints has a whole
bunch of fields, and you've got to
initialize those fields, before you use
it in any serious way.
So, I'm gonna to start by doing that, I'll
say GC.,
and perhaps the most important is the grid
X and grid Y,
and grid X and grid Y so the idea is that
you're laying
out your components in a grid, but the
cells in the grid
can be very flexibly sized and they can
also span columns or rows.
And the cell at position zero zero is in
the top left hand corner here.
So we.
As we increase X we go from left to right,
and as we increase Y, we go
from top down to bottom, but if you just
have one grid cell, then its gonna
be in the middle, so you see how this
works as I go along here, nd I'm gonna say
DC.grid Y equals null.
Now another very important thing to set
here is the weight.
I'm gonna say 2C.weight x equals one, one
and
GC.weight Y equals one as well.
And the weight controls for a given cell,
the weight will control
how much space it takes up relative to, to
the other cells.
So this number here it doesn't have to
it's not important what the number is in
itself.
What is important is how this number
compares to
the other weights that you assign to the
other cells.
And finally, you might want to set
GC.fill.
That can be set to horizontal, vertical,
none, or both,
and that tells your components, whether to
take up all the
space in the cell, or not, and I probably
don't want
mine to, so I'm going to say grid back /u
constraints.none.
And it's pretty important to set this lot
at the start, because if you leave any of
it out you tend to get problems later
which can really have you tearing your
hair out.
So, first I'm going to add the, the top
leftmost component which is going to be
name labels.
We'll say addNameLabel.
These are the components I created in the
last tutorial in this series.
And I pass addGC there.
Now if I run this, name is also appearing
in the
center of the panel, because there's only
one cell at the moment.
So, whether you call it top left or top
right, or what you like,
makes no difference because if it's only
one it's gonna be in the middle.
But let's now, say, GC.gridX equals one.
So I'm going from left to right, and
GC.gridY still equals zero, and
soGC.gridY is not changing and I'm gonna
reuse this grid back constraints, but
the reason that I'm a typing this again is
just to make it
clearer the code, what's that link, and
that is a big problem with
GridBagConstraints.
You tend to lose track of what's
happening.
So you really need to divide up your form
into kind of logical parts, you
know, and la, maybe put comments in in the
code and that kind of thing.
Or use tricks like this as well
of redefining variables that you don't
need to.
Okay, so let's do add name field.
Co, comma GC.
And if I add that it's gonna be one along
an X.
It's gonna be here.
If your text field appears extremely tiny,
you've probably forgotten to
set the text field width here, so don't
forget that.
And, so let's go ahead and say DC.gridY
now equals one
and DC.gridX, I'm going to set that to
zero and to add
occupation label, occupation label
comma DC, so this is adding a new row, so
I've gone down one in Y and it's down
here, and, then I'll say GC.gridY
still equals 1 and GC.gridX equals 1 as
well and add occupationField.
OccupationField, GC.
And so now, I've got my field in here.
And finally, I'm going to add a button
down here.
So, i'm going to say GC.gridY equals 2 and
GC.
GridX equals 1.
So I'm adding it in the second column.
The first column is number zero of course,
and add Okay button, [UNKNOWN] see this?
Now if I run that, that button's going to
appear down here.
Okay.
So that's great except that it looks like
a donkey's
ass because of the alignment and
everything's completely spread out.
So the first thing I'm going to do is I'm
gonna
to move these labels over to the right,
set it there flush
with the text fields and I'm gonna make
sure that the
text fields are moved over to the left,
rather than being centered.
And the way I do that is before I add the
labels, I have to say GC.anchor.
And this specifies the side of the cell
that the control sticks to if you like.
So I'm gonna say GC.anchor equals grid.
And let's try
GridBagConstraints.LINE_STAR_LINE_START.
So LINE_STAR means, it's like the start of
a line.
It's like, basically East is down here.
There's also first line start, which would
be up
here top left or last line start down
here.
Last line end is bottom left and first
line end top, sorry bottom right.
First line end top right, you, you
probably get the idea.
So me, I'm gonna use lines start here.
And I'll copy that because I want to also
make the
second label go to the, actually I don't
want a line start.
I, I actually want it to be line end
because I want it to
stick to the right hand side of the cell,
which is in the first column.
And, and I also want my my button and my
label,
my text fields to the LINE_START, to the
left hand side of the second column.
So here if I go to the field and I, change
this to LINE_START
and before I add the occupation field,
I'll have LINE_START as well.
And I don't actually need to repeat it,
but just for clarity here.
I'll set this to line stop as well,
although it's still LINE_STOP because I
used it here.
Okay, so there we go.
The alignment is just a little bit better
and know I would like I'd like these
the, the, controls to be up here somewhere
rather than spreading out vertically like
this and the
way I'm gonna do that is I'm gonna make
the first and second row is very small.
And I'm gonna make the last row take up
all the space, just to start with.
So, I'm gonna go to the weight Y, and this
is the weight Y for first row here, and,
let's take this out because I have to set
this out, I have to set this every time.
I'm gonna.
Move this to here.
And let's let's maybe, rearrange this a
bit.
I know, it's as good as it is because this
is all the
first row so let's put some comments in
here which will help a lot.
First.
First row.
And let's have a comment here so in the
next section I've got gridY equal to one.
So then it's going to be second row.
And finally.
I've got the button which is in the third
row down here and these are the kind
of lengths you' have to go to keep things
clearly with GridBagLayouts this is the
third row and for the first row I'm gonna
set the the weight text
and weight wanna set the weight Y I can
leave the weight text as it is I think.
I can set the weight Y, to a very small
value like 0.1.
And, I can have, that set to 0.1 for the
second row as well.
And then for the third row, I'm gonna set
the weight Y, to a much
bigger value, like 1.9, so the third row
takes up the most to the space.
And if I run that it looks like this,
which is an improvement.
If I, let's make this last row even bigger
and see how that looks.
So yeah now these are more bunched
together.
And I want the button here to be not
[UNKNOWN] which is here on the left.
The first LINE_START which is here.
Because conceptually it's like this is the
first line here.
Then the, the line.
And then the last line.
And then we've got lines start and end.
So let's make that first LINE_START for
bottom, the anchor.
So here I can say, instead of lines.
Start first.
LINE_START and if I run that, the buttons
now can
appear, which I think you'll agree looks a
lot better.
And there's one last little change that
I'd like to make here, because I
want my labels to have a little bit of
space up to the end.
And I could do that actually by by just
putting some some space actually in the
label text
itself, but because I want to show you
something
quite important, I'm gonna do it a
slightly different way.
I'm gonna use a indent.
So I'm gonna look for where the labels are
now.
So here's the occupation label and up here
is the name label.
And before writing those, I'm gonna say
GC.indent, I think it's called indent.
GC.inset.
Sorry.
Equals new insets and if you look at the
insets class, so
you Ctrl+ Shift+O type the import and put
the cursors there and let's have a look.
It's got the arguments or.
Top left, bottom right.
Although, to be honest with you, sometimes
I try inserting values
for insets and they seem to be in the
wrong order.
So let's try this today and see what
happens anyway.
I want to have an inset on the right
there.
So what I'm gonna try doing is, this is
top left bottom
right, like that, and I'm gonna have the
same insects before the, occupation label
and.
For the other controls I'm going to have
the inserts.
If I remember right I can just set set
these to null.
But if that doesn't work, I'm going to set
it to like a blank inset object.
So after I've set the insets there, I've
then done away with that.
And I've set the inserts here so I'll do
away with that again here.
And let's also do away with it before I
add the button here.
And let's see if that works.
So if I run that.
And I've got an error because my memory
[UNKNOWN] part here.
And I actually need to do just a need
blank insets instead of null.
Accept that, there's no there's no
construct with no parameters, so
let's set it to naught, and I'm confident
this will work.
So wherever I've got insets equal to null,
I'm gonna set it equal to naught.
So that there's no cutting.
And of course if I was worried about
efficiency here, I could create
just one insets subject or two in this
case, and I could reuse them.
Where I need them, if I run that.
Now we've got a little bit of space.
It should be five pixels, but who knows if
it really
is exactly five pixels, right on the side
of the labels here.
That's it for this tutorial, in the next
tutorial, I'm.
Hooking this little panel up to that so it
does something.
And we're gonna use [UNKNOWN] listener
model that I've already explained.
But then if you didn't fully understand it
last time cuz we're gonna go over it
again.
And I'm actually gonna use an event object
to carry
information from here up to the
controller, the main frame.
And I'm gonna output it.
In this text area here.
So until next time, happy coding.