Hello, this is John from Cave of
Programming dot com.
And in this tutorial, we're gonna look at,
the event object class in Java Swing.
And we're also gonna, take a look at,
getting the text from text fields in
swing.
So, and form handling in general.
So in the last tutorial, I created this
little application and at
the moment, actually these buttons still
work but this form doesn't do anything.
And I wanna make this form work.
And in future tutorials, we're gonna look
at the model part
of the model view controller architecture,
which we're gonna get into.
But and that part handles data, sorting
data, and dealing with data in your
application.
But for the moment, I just wanna fix this,
so that if you fill something in here.
And you click okay.
Then it adds the text to this panel on the
right here.
So I need to transmit data basically from
this form,
to this panel control on the right, but I
don't want
to send the data there directly and to
keep the communication
streamlined and to keep it from getting
tangled in my application.
I want all communication to be rooted
through this
main frame here which is acting as my
controller.
The main frame creates all the main
components, my
toolbar, text bar and form panel and I
want my.
The information from my form to reach main
frame.
And then main frame decides what to do
with it.
Processes it anyway it wants to.
And in this case, it's gonna tell the text
panel to display it.
And that's one of the keys to keeping
your application from turning into a rat's
nest.
So, to do that, I need to respond to
clicks on this button.
And, beginners often make the mistake of
trying
to detect when the user is entering text
here.
And most of the time you don't need to do
that, because.
Cuz you only want to submit your form
information when the button is clicked.
So it's the button you have to listen to,
and when the button's clicked,
you're gonna get a text from these text
fields, and do something with it.
So let's first go into the form panel.
And I'm going to add a Listener, an Action
Listener.
To the okay button.
So, I'll say, okay btn.add.actionlistener
and I
could make my form class, my form panel
class implement that.
Listener and passing this here.
But what I'm going to do instead is use
an anonymous class and put a semicolon
right there.
I'm going to say new action listener,
which is the interface name, round
brackets
and open the curly parenthesis hit return
eclipse puts the closing parenthesis in
parenthesis.
And if I click on this here I can, if I
got the input there already which I have,
then I can add
unimplemented methods here and that works
the same in Net beans
I think, and probably an intelligent idea
if you're using that IDE.
And then it adds this public void action
before method which receives a action
event notice.
Now I'll get rid of these lines that I
don't really need.
By the way this is a.
attribute that ensures, so it's an
annotation that this really is an
override.
But I'm going to trust that it is the
correct override.
Just delete that.
And now, so this is going to be called
whenever the button is clicked.
So when the button is clicked, I can say
string name equals.
In fields dot get text.
And string occupation equals occupation
fields dot get text.
Like this, it's pretty simple.
And I'm just referring here, name field of
course.
An occupation field, or kinda private
instance variables in my containing class.
The form panel, which contains the form.
Now at this point, I somehow need to pass
this information to
my main frame and, I'm not gonna try to
call main frame directly.
I'm gonna do what I've done before and
raise
an event, which the main frame is gonna
listen to.
Now I'm gonna introduce a new little.
Kinda twist here, because I wanna kinda
move
towards showing you how swing handles
events natively.
So we see that swing's got this mechanism,
where you
say things like add Action Listener, and
then your Action Listener,
your class switch implements your switch
action interface, in this case,
as a method got action perform, which
receives an action event.
And the action event is used to.
To pass information from the control that
raises the event, which is a button in
this case, to the listening class, which
is this synonymous class here, in this
case.
So, I'm going to actually defined an event
and my
event is gonna be used to temporary
install name and occupation.
And also information I'm going to add to
my form later on.
And it's gonna transmit, it's gonna be
used to take that information up
to the main frame which is my controller
class because the main frame
creates the toolbar, text panel and form
panel, and it decides what to
do with the information that they generate
and it hooks them all together.
So, I'll start here by creating a new
class,
and I'm gonna call it form event.
This is a kind of event class and I'm, I
don't have to, but I'm gonna make it
extend, Different objects which is a
standard Java class and if I had the
import there that's
actually, this event object is the class,
which.
All the kind of swing events like, for
example, actually vent, derive from.
So if I, if I just extend this event
object it's gonna help
us, kind of move towards More like the
swing native architecture later on.
Although this native kind of swing event
handling is a, kind of a bit overkill for
most purposes, which is why I haven't kind
of immediately shown you how it works.
So so I've got a Form Event Object, which
extends Event Object.
And I'm gonna start.
By, well I'll have to import that.
so, import, event, object.
And
I'm gonna add a construct here.
Because event object ask.
A constructor.
Which accepts an object, which is the
source of the event.
And the source means the object that
raises the event.
And in this case source is gonna be the
form panel.
But for example, within the form panel, I
listen to a.
Button, a J button and the source in that
case, is going to be the button itself
that
actually, so this actually, then will have
a source,
which will be the actual button that
raises the event.
So now, once I've done that, so, I've,
I've just extended the event object, added
a constructor.
Accepts the source of the event.
And, I'm just, this is really simple, I'm
just gonna add a couple of fields now, so
private, string, name, and private,
string,
occupation, because I just want this class
to, to store that information temporarily.
It's just gonna take that information.
And relay it to my main frame and let's
add getters and setters for that.
So, I'll use an Eclipse shortcut.
I'll right click and go to source and.
Generate getters and setters and every
good IDE, as this facility, of course.
And click ok and there we go, I've got my
getters and setters, get occupation, set
occupation, and so on.
and, I.
Will also, let's also alter their
construct a bit here.
Because I might want to just bonk in the
name and occupation here.
Actually, I'm not really sure about that.
Let's just have another construct so I can
use it if I want to.
So let's say here.
String name.
String occupation.
And this dot name equals name.
And this dot occupation equals occupation.
And if you've been programming in Java for
any length of time,
this kind of panel will be burnt into your
brain by now
where you just have, you pass in some
parameters and set the
instance variable parameters to the, to
the arguments that are passed in.
Okay, so, so now I 've got a
event object that can store that
information temporarily.
And back in my form panel, when the button
is clicked, I can
say, I could create one of those events,
such as a form event,
event, I'll just call it f actually equals
new form event,
and I can pass in the source, which is
this, and the name, and the occupation.
And now, the question is, how am I gonna
get that back to my.
Main frame and I want the main frame to
kind
of have some stuff that looks like this in
it.
So if I go to the main frame you see that
I've, I've got my, I already
set a listener on the tool bar and I want
the main frame to do the same kind of.
Thing with the form panel, so I can say
form panel dot,
and I want something that looks like this,
set form
listener, and that method is not
implemented yet, but this is what
it's gonna look like when it's finished,
And in there, I want
to be able to say something like new form
listener.
Which again, doesn't exist yet.
And form listener interface, which I'm
going to create, should have a method.
Something like, public void form event.
For the, form event occurred, let's say.
And the form event occur method should
accept a form event,
event, which I'll just call E, and then it
should do something with it.
In fact, what it should do, is it should
get the.
String name because e dot get name.
Because form events is just this event
class that I've just created right here.
Which has the get name and the set name,
and all that kind of stuff.
And string.
Occupation equals E dot get occupation,
and
once it's got them, it can tell the text
panel
what to do, it can say text panel dot
append.
[SOUND] I think the text panel here, the
text panel has the append text method.
So I can say append text and something
like main and let's add in a plus.
And some punctuation.
And then occupation and plus and maybe a
backslash and new line.
Now if you're kinda losing the thread a
bit at this point
don't worry too much.
I'd, I'd say like, take a look at the
example we went through earlier with the
tool box.
This is very similar.
It's just that I've introduced this event
object, this form event thing.
And try typing it out for yourself,
because once you've typed this out
once or twice you, I think you will get
the hang of it.
And the, the main points here are that I
created this.
Form event object, which can store the
name and occupation.
Actually, that should be called
occupation, spelling mistake there, let's
just
fix that, so the form event stores the
name and the occupation.
There we go, and it derives from
swing the swing Event, object, class.
And, and that has a constructor, that
accepts
the source of the event, and the source of
the event is whichever component fired the
event, which
is gonna be my form panel in this case.
And, the next step is, like, if you get
used to adding action business to buttons
like here,
I've added an action list to this okay
button,
you can then do the same thing with your
own.
Controls, so instead of action listener, I
just made up the names here, I've said set
form listener instead of add action
listener and
instead of action listener, I've got form
listener here.
Instead of action perform, I've got
perform event occurred, so I'm just making
these up and now I'm gonna implement the
relevant stuff to make that work.
And the way I'll do that is.
So I've got my form event, but I need to
create the form listener interface.
So let's just oh I've still got one error
in
here, yeah, I've just got one A missing
there, okay.
So I'm gonna go right click here, and I'm
gonna go to New, Interface, Form Listener.
And I want my FullListener interface to
have a method called FormEvent occurred,
so that's all I want to have in it, which
accepts FormEvent, so I'm copying that,
and I just paste it
in here, and just to make this more like
the kind of.
Native swing way of doing this.
I can also make it implement, and event
listener.
Listener and sorry not implement but
extend.
The event listener class which is the
drive utility event listener.
And that's the basis for all the listeners
in swing like the action listener for
example.
And now, I just need to create this set,
form this new method in the form panel.
So if I go to my form panel, then I can
say here, let's have a private variable.
Private.
Form, form listener, form listener.
and, I want the method called set form
listener, so let's go down
here, let's get rid of those blunt lines
and say public for your set.
Form listener, and that accepts a form
listener, in
other words, any class that implements a
form listener interface.
So I'll call that listener, and I can just
set the this dot form listener equal to
the listener.
And then the final step here, is.
At this point here, in my action list on
the button,
I've created a form event that has the
relevant information in it.
And now I just have to say that if the
form listener
which I added as an instance variable, is
not equal to null,
not equal to null, then I can call the one
method.
That all form listeners have, which is the
form event occurred.
I can say here,
in, where is it, in my form panel, so I'd
say form listener,
if it's not equal to null, dot form event
occurred and pass in the event there.
And
the whole kind of point of this is full
panel doesn't contain any references.
It says to mainframe.
But nevertheless, mainframe has set
itself, or it's set actually
in anonymous class as the form listener
using this method.
So, it used to set form listener.
And that anonymous class here that
implements form
listener interface can receive the form
even occurred.
And it can, it has a method that will be
called.
By the form panel when a form event
occurs,
so the form kinda caused that form event
occur method.
So this, here, is calling this method
here, and
then this has been the mainframe and then
mainframe tells the text panel what to do.
So if I run that.
I thought I'm feeling something here, like
lets
try it with nothing in for the moment.
So I just get a colon being output.
And you might want to put some validation
on this form of course.
So lets fill in the edge on Software
Trainer.
Click ok, and every time I click.
Click on it fills it in.
So let's have another one.
Bob.
Lion Tamer.
There you go.
So this, I appreciate that this is pretty
complex and a lot of people
are puzzled by this, but as I say, don't
rack your brains over it.
Just type it out.
Just look at the example I've given you,
and try to implement the same thing, and
if
you can spend that time doing it, you know
just like a hour or two doing that.
It will really help you get your head
around and understanding this stuff will
massively help you and create nicely
structured swing applications.
And alternatively.
If you just want to bang out swing
applications that just work, then yeah,
you could, you could pass in a reference,
to the mainframe directly into your,
directly into your form panel.
And, or, even pass in a reference to the.
You could pass a reference to the text
area panel here, to the form panel here.
But if you do that a lot.
And if your ambition is to create complex
Swing applications.
Then that will get, unmanageably complex
pretty quickly.
So, if you wanna create quite complex
swing applications.
It's really worth just spending a little
bit of
time looking at this code and getting used
to it.
Okay, so that's more than enough for this
tutorial and you'll be
pleased to know that after this, we're
looked at kind of swing events,
and we've looked at we've looked at grid
back layout, and after these
two immensely complicated things, it's
Almost plain sailing from here on in.
So in the next tutorial, we're going to
look at something nice and simple.
We're going to look at the J list control.
So join me again then and until next time,
happy coding.
[SOUND]