Hi.
Welcome back.
This is John from caveofprogramming.com.
I hope you survived the last tutorial on
events, which was pretty complex.
In this tutorial we're gonna look at
something a lot simpler.
We're gonna look at, list boxes.
So, I've created so far.
This application with this form here.
[SOUND] That just fills stuff in, here.
And what I'm gonna do now is add a new
control to this form, which is gonna be a
ListBox.
So, I'm gonna start by going to the class,
that represents the form here.
and, I'm gonna add a new private instance
variable type, [SOUND] JList, which is the
Swing ListBox.
And, [SOUND] I'm gonna make this ListBox
hold.
Different age categories like under 18, 18
to 65, and over 65.
And so I'll call this ageList.
[SOUND] And, let's go down to where I'll
add the input there.
[SOUND] And let's go down to where if.
Created the other components and say
AgeList equals New DayList.
[SOUND] Now the Swing components in Java
they pretty
much follow the, Model View Controller
architecture.
So in the MVC architecture the view is The
literal, the actual GUI stuff like buttons
and everything.
Everything you see draw, drawn on the
screen.
The controller, in the case of our
application here, is, well a controller
is,
the part of the application that contains
all the logic, and that hooks everything
together.
And at the moment, this is really, [SOUND]
our main frame.
Because that's.
Getting information from the different
components
and telling other components what to do.
And in this application here we haven't
got a model at all.
The model is the bit that stores data and
deals with data, deals with databases, and
so on.
But the upshot of this is, that if you
wanna add,
items to a JList, you gotta add stuff to
the JList's model.
And, [SOUND] what I will do here is I
will,
create a default list model, [SOUND] which
I'll call AgeModel.
And I'll set that equal to New
DefaultListModel like that and
at the import, and I can add items to this
AgeModel and to start
with I'm gonna just add simple string
items, and in the
next tutorial we're gonna look at how
that, how you can make
that, kinda hook that up with a database
and use ids.
These to represent your items instead of,
strings.
But, we'll keep it simple here.
I'll say AgeModel.addElement.
And the first elements gonna be a string
it says, let's say 18 or under.
[SOUND] And actually, maybe that's not
exactly, typical.
Let's just say, actually under 18.
And I'll copy that.
And, I'll make a, [SOUND] two more items
here, and I'll
have the middle category to be, 18 to
[SOUND] 65.
And the last category here, I'll have 65
or over,
[SOUND] and now I need to tell this
ListBox to use this model.
So I say ageList.setModel.
[SOUND] AgeModel.
[SOUND] So now let's add that ListBox to
the form and then
we can have a look and make it look a bit
nicer.
So at the moment I've got, if I run this
application I've got, three rows here
starting numbering at 0.
That's first row, second row, and last row
has a button in.
So I want the, ListBox to be before the
button on the third
row, and I want the button to be moved to
the fourth row.
So I changed this here grid y for the
button to be three, using
my, [SOUND] create [UNKNOWN] let's make
this comment, fourth row.
[SOUND] Then let's just copy this, and
paste that in there.
[SOUND] Say third row, [SOUND] and this is
gonna be, so grid wise gonna be two, and
here instead of adding a button, I'm gonna
add the, AgeList and everything else.
May be same ,now lets run this and see how
it looks.
And so this my ListBox oh yeah, actually
made the last
row take up all the space and don't want
this third row
take up lots of space and am gonna change
that width
by here to something that's more than the
final point 2 and.
Run that.
And that looks a, a lot better I think.
Now the this box here it doesn't look too
pretty.
So, I'm gonna, make it look prettier.
And the first thing I'm gonna do is set,
the preferred size to make it a bit
bigger.
[SOUND] So let's go up to where I can
create the, AgeList.
And so it's actually I'll go after here,
after I've set the data.
I don't think it really matters.
And I'll say
AgeList.setPreferredSizeNewDimension.
[SOUND] And let's have it at, I don't
know, 110 and 66.
[SOUND] You're probably gonna have to play
around with
those figures, to get it to look, [SOUND]
really good.
But I think that looks acceptable and.
Let's give it a border.
Because it looks a bit strange without a
border.
So I'll say,
AgeList.setBorder(BorderFactor.create).
[SOUND] Maybe etched border will.
But good, I've missed a lot there though.
For the factory.create edged order.
[SOUND] So, see how that looks.
There we go, that's, quite a lot better I
would say.
And, Maybe just slightly, wider and now
I wanna get information from this ListBox
when the OK
button is clicked and the way to do that.
Is, so in my action list on my button
here I'm already getting information, name
and
occupation from the text fields and what I
can do
is I can say string, [SOUND] hcut let's
call it
equals, hlist.getSelectValue, like that.
And that returns a, object.
So I need to put in a type cast here, from
object to string.
Because I know that the items in my
ListBox are actually strings.
Therefore, I can, definitely custom to
strings.
And, if I do [UNKNOWN] out here to check.
And it's always got to check as you're
going along, that things are behaving as
you expect.
Then, if I select one of those and click
OK that's gonna come out down here, in the
console.
I'm gonna, also select a default item when
the, this
box is created, cuz I think that would
look nicer too.
So let's say here, [SOUND]
ageless.setSelectedIndex, and set it to 1.
So, the first item is 0.
So, by setting it to 1, I set it to the
middle item like that.
Yeah, I think it looks, better.
And now the next logical step here, will
be
to change the where is it, in my form
panel.
I've got this form event, class that
carries information to the main frame.
And the next logical information will be
to add in, the age category here.
But I'm actually gonna do that in the next
tutorial because.
Usually when you create a, ListBox, you
probably
don't want to get a string from it.
You probably want to get an ID that
represents that string,
because it's that ID that you will store
in your, database.
usually.
That's not necessarily the case, and I
could of course
here, I could, just use this AgeCategory
directly, and I could
maybe have an if statement that looks at
the AgeCategory
and does different things, but as a
general principle, it's not.
Good
to have your the kind of, control that
aspect,
of your, application, the actual business
logic of it.
It's not good to have the logic, depending
on, things that are directly connected to
the view.
So if I change the wording.
Of my, age category, [SOUND] and if I were
to change this, you know, to say something
like,
I don't know, over 65 instead of 65 or
over, I don't want that to break my
application.
And really, I wanna work with IDs here,
not direct with the
strings, [SOUND] and so we're gonna look
at how to do that, in
the next tutorial and we're gonna look at
how to get information,
[SOUND] from this ListBox back, to
somewhere where it can actually be used.
So join me again next time, and until
then, Happy Coding.
[SOUND]