Hello, this is John from
caveofprogramming.com and in this
tutorial, we're gonna look at how you can
use
IDs in your list boxes, rather than
relying on,
the strings that you output in the user
interface.
And that we're also gonna hook up a little
bit more of the
code in this little application that we've
been working on here, and here.
And I'm gonna make it output some stuff
here in this panel.
When I click, Ok on this form.
So At the moment, what's happening is if I
click, Ok on the form after I've selected
something in this list my code is in this,
in the, in the class that represents the
panel.
It's just retrieving the string.
From the list box.
And a problem with that is usually the
kind of string
is a thing that might change if you decide
to reword it.
Or something.
What you, you really want usually is you
want some ID that corresponds to that
string.
So, if this was a table in a database, and
we're
gonna get into databases later on in this
series of tutorials.
Then each age category would probably have
an ID,
and it's that ID that you usually really
want.
So to make this work.
What I will do is I'm gonna write a new
little
clasp, and because it just quite small on
the utility class.
I'm gonna just write it here in the file
along with form panel.
And things that I'm writing to my list box
are age categories.
And I'm gonna call this.
Class age category and let's
give this a constructor, and each age
category I'm gonna say category
has a id int id, and it has a string.
Text that is a descriptive string that
appears in the user interface.
So let's give this a private string text
and
also a, I'll put it up here actually, a
private int ID.
And in the constructor.
I'm just gonna set that text and ID.
So, this dot ID equals ID and this dot
text equals text.
So, it's just a little utility class for
matching up ID's.
And string for the should be this, for the
age categories, and
what I can do, is I can add that class to
my list box instead of strings.
So let's look at where I'm adding the
elements to my list box, and it's here,
it's I'm adding it to the model, remember,
of the of the J list.
So instead of having under 65 I'm saying
new age category.
It's a little class I just created and
have I can have an id here
and then a string and I wanna do the same
thing
down here and here and I'm gonna change
the ids.
So, each one has a unique id, and let's
make that one and make that two.
And now if I run this what's gonna happen
is I'm gonna see this.
This is the result of doing toString on my
AgeCategory objects and to actually make
it look like nice.
All I've gotta do is give this AgeCategory
class,
a two string method, so public String
toString, and.
Return text, cuz I, this is the text that
I actually want to display, which is the
text that
I'm passing in here and now if I run that
it looks just the same as it did before.
But the advantage is that when I click the
button
instead of saying
ageList.getSelectedValue, Well
actually, I still wanna do that.
But it's or do I?
Actually, I think what I want is get
selected
yeah.
Get selected value should do the trick.
But instead of casting it to a string, I'm
gonna.
Cast it to a AgeCategory like that, and
then call this AgeCategory.
So, if I run that when I oh yeah, need a
semicolon there.
When I click, Ok, it's gonna get my age
category object from the list.
So I'm just doing, I'm still doing
ageList.getSelectedValue.
I can't actually remember if that was the
right method, but it is getSelectedValue.
But it's just that the values in my list
now are not strings.
They are age category objects.
And the advantage of doing this is that
here,
I've now got access to the string, and the
ID.
Which is probably what I really want.
So, let's go down here.
And let's give it a public
public int getID.
And I'll just return the ID there.
And here when the button is clicked, I can
now say hcup dot let's just.
I'll put the ID for the moment.
And it I run that, so when I click, Ok
down here in the console,
I get the ID [UNKNOWN] string, which is
what you want most of the time.
Because usually this information is gonna
be stored in a
database, and having the string text is
not usually any use.
Okay, and now I'm gonna at this point so
like
what I'm gonna do now is just make that
text appear on the right hand side here.
And if you're a fairly advanced java
programmer you might wanna skip that bit.
Because all I'm gonna do, is I'm gonna
modify the
event model that carries the information,
sorry, the event object.
It carries information from this panel, up
to the
main frame, and then down again to this
text panel.
I'm gonna modify that to accept my id,
which is one of the advantages of using
events.
So when I get, when I collect all this
information.
I'm saying, form listener.
Form event occurred, and passing it this
event.
And a form listener.
The thing that's listening, actually, in
this case, is the main frame.
So, let's go to form event here.
And it's already got a get name, and a get
occupation.
But I'm gonna give it a private.
Int ageCategory.
And I'm gonna let's put this here.
Let's say int age, ageCat.
And let's say, this.ageCategory equals
ageCat.
And let's give it a get age category.
So public.
Void getAgeCategory and all that has to
do is just return ageCat of course,
ageCategory.
So yeah, it's not public void actually
it's int and so
all I've done here is just make this event
object capable
of storing a bit more information and then
here in the
form panel, I can pass in not only the
name and.
Patient, also the age cut dot, dot get ID.
And now finally in my main
frame here I can add to the text panel
some more stuff here.
I can say So, I've got name and occupation
and, and I could also output,
Let's see, I could say int age cut equals
e dot get h cut.
So, I'm just using the method I've just
declared on the form we found.
And here, I can output.
The age category, so let's do plus age
cap,
age capped, and I'll still have the new
line there.
So, eclipse itself hopefully putting in a
double quote I don't want.
And if I run that.
So [COUGH] so now excuse me if I fill this
in John software say software, and I'm
believe I'm 1865.
So, if I run that it's it's gonna output
here John software one, h category one.
So you see this, this using an event model
is
very flexible because you can transfer a
lot of information.
From this form, just using your object.
You don't have to keep you don't have to
make this
form event occurred have more and more
arguments all the time.
In the next tutorial, we're gonna look at
another wonderful form widget that you can
use.
We're gonna look at the combo box.
So, join me again then.
And until next time, happy coding.
[SOUND]