Hi, this is John from
caveofprogramming.com and in
this tutorial we're gonna look at combo
boxes.
Combo boxes are sort of like combination
of a text field and a list box.
Where you have like a kind of drop down
thing at the side of the box.
And they work pretty much like, list
boxes, Excel, that you can
make them editable which allows users to
enter their own values in them.
So if you want to go in and try that for
yourself then be my guest.
And if you want to see a worked example of
this then stick around.
So, if I run this, this is the application
I created in the last tutorial unto now.
And I'm gonna add a combo box in here
under the list box.
So I'm gonna go to my form panel class
here,
and I'm gonna start by creating a private
variable JComboBox.
And I'm gonna make this a list of
Employment
types, so I'll call that emp, emp combo
maybe empCombo, employment combo that
should do the trick.
And I'll just add the input there and
where I'm creating my components here.
I'll say empCombo equals JCombobox.
And then in the same way that here I
created a default list model
for my combo box, so let's just put a
comment, Set up list box.
Now I want to.
Set up my combo box in SMOA so, Set up
combo
box, so I'm going to create a default
combo box model,
call that emp model equals
new default combo box model and I'm gonna
add some items to that.
And model.addElement and
@model.addElement, this is just
the same as the list case really.
I'm gonna have some strings in here, lets
say employed
and I'm just gonna Copy that.
And Paste in a couple more.
And let's have self-employed and
unemployed.
And then, I'm gonna set that model on
the combo box, so empCombo.setModel, set
model, empModel.
Now I can already add that combo box to my
layout but this layout is actually getting
a bit complex, if
we look at the class here, it's getting
quite big and
there's a hell of a lot of stuff in one
method.
So, just to make it a little bit more
readable.
What I'm gonna do is, I am gonna add to
the method here, public void
layoutComponents.
And I'm gonna take this layout code here,
that
uses a grid like layout, right up to here.
Here do Ctrl+X and I'm gonna paste it in
there, so at
least we got the grid bug layout stuff in
a different method.
And here, I can call layoutComponents.
So, it's always good to hit the green run
button after you've made any kind
of major change, so in a moment, still, it
looks the same it appears to work.
So that's good.
And what I'm gonna do now is I want to
make just a little
adjustment to this, this layout to make it
a bit easier to add new components.
I've broken it down into rows.
And if I want to add a new component now,
I've got
to move this button down a row and then
set one here.
So just to make it a little bit easier,
I'm gonna go to the top here and I'll set
grid y right at the beginning here and
then when I get to the next row
I'm going to take grid y out and put it
here.
And just do ++ and this means that I've
got to always do this row by row.
Otherwise it would get horribly tangled.
But and you have to kinda do this thing
very judiciously
because you could really mess up your
layout if you're not careful.
But I think at this point it's gonna
simplify things a bit if I use-
if I increment the row each time instead
of setting the row to an actual number.
So.
That's still the finer want here and let's
check that it still looks okay.
I haven't messed anything up and another
thing I
want to do actually is add a label on the
left hand side here but I'm gonna do that
in
just a second after I add in my combo box.
So let's change this from the comment from
fourth row to
just next row because these are just gonna
be more rows
and then, to add in a new row now, I can
copy this, which is my list box and just
paste it in.
And if I've got this right, if I add in
now
empCombo and I run that I'm gonna get my
combo box here.
It's very nice.
That said in a label as well.
So, my, some of my controls have labels
like, like here.
And, and I think, if I copy that.
And I go down here.
So here's my ageList.
And let's go after I've set the weights.
I should be able to just create a new
label here
because I don't really have to have the
labels as instanced variables.
I can just use them here because the
labels are probably not gonna change.
So I can just create a label on the fly
here and say new JLabel and this should
say age, semi, sorry, colon.
I forgot what this was called for a
minute.
Okay, and if I run that let's take a look
at it and see if it works.
So, we've got age there but I want to
align the age.
I want to put it the FIRST_LINE_END so,
rather than line end
so the first line int is kinda top, is
kinda top right.
So there we go, that looks pretty good.
And I'm gonna use that again for my combo
box so let's
paste this in here and this time it's
gonna be new JLabel
Employment.
And run that and that looks terrible cuz
it's aligned to the bottom there.
So let's try putting that as well, first.
First line in, see how that looks.
And that's not so bad, I would say.
And now, to get the values from this combo
box,
it's pretty much the same as with the list
box.
This is very similar, I can do here, let's
say string empCut equals new,
actually equals, sorry, String, so a
typecast here and empCombo.
And instead of being get selected value,
it's getSelected,
getSelectedItem and also like, if you want
to have multiple
selection in there, you can and you can
return the rate of selected objects.
So.
And actually come to think of it, with
JList you can allow multiple selection, by
doing, age in this case, for example,
ageList.set.
Selection mode and you can, if you look
up the documentation for that you can
allow it
multiple items to be selected but I think
in
a combo box you can't actually select
multiple items.
I think I'm wrong to say that.
But anyway, so we'll get now the, item.
So we're, we're getting the item from the
combo box here.
And I'm just gonna output that here.
So I'm just gonna output empCat.
And if I run that, and now click OK
on my console here, I'm gonna see the
combo box, kind of selection.
And of course if I wanted, I could then,
when I set it by combo.
I could say and empCombo.setSelectedIndex,
let's set that to zero.
So, it has a default selection.
There we go.
Now you can make your combo box editable.
So, I can say empCombo.setEditable, True.
And if you do that, it means that so if I
run it now, you can see now it's
appearing in white and I can select all
the values that
are in it as before, set this to
unemployed, as befits the times.
And if I type something in here like I can
say other for example.
Then, it will retrieve that value when I
do
get selected item, the thing to watch with
this though,
is that with ageList I used an ageCategory
object
that I created, and I put that into the
list.
And so that I could pair up ID's with,
with the
actual items rather than just cut the
string that represents the item.
And you can use the same trick with combo
boxes
but the problem is that if the user edits
the
box you won't retrieve your, a object of
the type
that you put into it, you're retrieve a
string instead.
So you have to think about how to deal
with that,.
You could use instance of to check what
you're returning from the combo box, for
example.
And, or you could just do getSelectedIndex
and just
get the index of the things, thing that's
selected.
It doesn't matter too much.
Lots of ways to do it.
And but for the moment, for this tutorial,
just to keep things a little bit simpler.
I'm just gonna use this string straight
from the combo box and I'm gonna go to my
event of course and, and let's add in here
a string empCat
and I'll give this also a private string,
empCat and I
just set that, implement category here, so
empCat equals empCat.
This is my event object that kinda relays
the information to the main, the main
frame.
Let's have a public String
getEmploymentCategory
and just return empCat like that.
And then so all I have to do now is in
here I
can pass in, when I create the event I can
pass in my empCat.
And if I save that, the arrow should go
away.
And in mainframe now, so when I
receive the form event occurred, I could
say string empCat equals
event.getEmploymentCategory.
And I can add it in here, so empCat
and plus and let's have some punctuation
as well.
And let's run that and let's fill
something in here John
Software.
1865 self-employed okay and here we got
all the information.
So that's it for this tutorial.
And in the next tutorial, we're gonna look
at checkboxes so join me again then.
And until next time, happy coding.