[NOISE] Hi, welcome back.
This is John from Cave of Programming dot
com
and this is a tutorial on check boxes in
swing.
So, I'm going to start here by declaring a
check box so.
J Check Box, and actually
I'm gonna make this a check box that, you
tick to say that you
are a US Citizen, so I'll call it Citizen
Check and I could.
To just get the get whether this check box
is selected
by calling the E selecting method and I
could just pass that back
to my main frame but to make this a little
bit more interesting I'm gonna
actually have this check box enable or
disable a text field
which is gonna be J text field and
its gonna be called tax field.
So if you tick the check box to say your a
US citizen.
You have to enter a tax ID.
So let's go down here and I'll, I'll set
Citizen
Check equal to a new J Check box here, new
J Check box.
And I will set tax field equal to a new J
Text field with a width of ten characters.
And now in in the constructive to your
check box
you can actually supply some text so
several different constructors.
You can supply text and you can say
whether
it's initially selected or deselected, but
I'm not going
to use those parameters here because I'm
just going
to put a label by the side of it.
And, and I'm also going to put a label by
the side of my tax field, and I want
my label to also appear grayed out if the
citizen chat box is not ticked along with
tax field.
So I'm going to add my label for tax field
up here, so J label
and tax label, so let's call that, and
here I'll set
tax label equals new J label, and now I'm
going to do a little
bit of init setup, well actually apply the
tax as well so say.
here, tax ID.
And
let's set up, set up, tax ID.
So, I'm gonna start by making the tax
label disabled.
So I'll say set enabled.
False.
And I'm also gonna make the tax field, not
enabled either.
So it's gonna appear grayed out and you're
not gonna be able to enter stuff in it.
And then, to the citizen check here, which
is
gonna be initially deselected, I'm gonna
add an action listener.
So add action listener just like a button.
So, I'll say new Action Listener.
Listener.
And.
Add a semicolon there and add an
implemented method here,
and just get rid of some, some of this
extra stuff here that I don't need.
And what I do is, so this will be invoked
whenever the citizen check box is.
Ticked or unticked.
And I wanna firstly get whether
that text field is selected or not, so I
can say
boolean is ticked, let's say,
equals and it's gonna be citizen check.is
selected.
There we go.
So that will get me true or false,
depending on whether this is ticked or
not.
And if it has just been ticked I will
enable the tax label in the tax field.
And otherwise I'll disable them.
So I'm gonna say tax label dot set enabled
is ticked like this.
And tax field.
Dot set enabled.
[SOUND]
Is tacked.
Okay.
Now let's add those controls to the form.
So I'm gonna go down, I'm gonna go down
here to where I do the layout.
And so the last row's the button.
I'm just gonna copy the row before the
button here.
And here I'm gonna add in my my check box.
So let's add in here citizen check.
And let's add.
A label here which I'm gonna just make it
say, US,
US citizen.
So if I run that let's see what it looks
like.
You see it says US citizen, I can take
this.
Looks rather nice.
Let's copy this again.
And, it's the row underneath it.
So now, I'll add in the text field.
And,
so I'm gonna use here, for the label.
I'm gonna use the tax label control that
I've just set up.
And.
Here I'm gonna add the text field.
So, if I run that, you can see it's
disabled.
But if I tick this, I can't enter stuff in
it.
If I tick this, then it is enabled, like
that.
I can disable it again.
It's rather nice.
And of course I can, so that's basically.
If move check boxes, I'm just gonna add,
gonna modify my form
event to store some further information,
and you're probably pretty familiar
with this by now, so if you get a picture
with
the form events, then feel free to skip to
the next tutorial.
I'm gonna add here a Boolean US citizen,
US citizen,
and I'm gonna work this rather long
constructor.
Let's just do control shift F to format
that
bit and then I'm gonna say here string tax
ID.
And Boolean US citizen.
US citizen.
Like that.
And let's just do this dot tax ID equals
tax D.
And this dot US citizen.
Equals US Citizen.
And I can add a get methods for those.
So let's just add to use the eclipse short
cut.
Right click here, go to source and...
Generate getters and setters.
And I wanna generate getters and setters
for
these in fact, probably don't really need
the setters.
That's just expand that, and get rid of
that.
And if you have a Boolean variable, then
you can see Eclipse is
generating a is US citizen, rather than
get US citizen, which is quite common.
A reasonable thing to do.
So that's that.
If I wanted, of course I have, to modify
the events here.
Let's do a format on that as well.
And then I can add, here.
So, to actually get the value from the
check box I need to use selected method.
So I'll add in here, the this should be
string tax ID.
D equals tax field dot get, that's
pretty simple and Boolean US citizen,
citizen equals and that's just gonna be.
The name of the check box.
Which I've forgotten.
I think it's, citizen check right?
citizen check dot is selected.
There we go.
And so I'm just gonna write these in here.
So tax Id and US Citizen.
And I can do something with that
information later.
But for now, I'm not gonna worry too much
about it.
So I could add it in her, for example.
and, ok so that's it for this tutorial.
And in the next tutorial, we're gonna look
at radio buttons.
So check boxes are great if you have a
bunch of options and you can
tick any combination of the options or you
just have one, as in this case
but sometimes you have a bunch of options
and you can only select one of
them, they're mutually exclusive and for
that
situation you use radio buttons not check
boxes.
So we're going to look at that in the.
Next tutorial.
And until then, happy coding.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
[NOISE]