Hello, this is John from
caveofprogramming.com and in this
tutorial we're gonna look at radial
buttons in Java Swing.
So, in a moment I've got this nice little
form here and.
In the last tutorial we added this check
box here.
And in this tutorial I'm gonna add some
radio buttons down here.
Now, radio buttons are a little bit more
complex than check boxes, but, nothing you
can't handle.
So, I'm going to have check boxes here.
That represent gender, so, to keep
things nice and simple, simple, I just
have two alternatives, male and female.
And I'm gonna start by creating my radio
buttons here, so I'll say private jradial
button.
And just to repeat what I said in the last
tutorial right here buttons allow you to
choose mutually exclusive options.
So if you have options you can select
together you want check boxes.
But if you got to pick one option from
a bunch of several you want radial buttons
so let's.
And call this male radial and then I'll
and then I'll create another
one called, start the import there, J
radial button female radial.
So I'm just gonna have two of them.
And you also need a button group.
To use with radio buttons.
So I'll say private button group and
gender group.
And button groups are what allow you to
group
the buttons together, so that you can say
that
if one of them is selected, then the other
should be deselected automatically, which
is the usual behavior.
Off radial buttons.
So now, lets go down here and say
maleRadial = new
JRadialButton and I'll give that some text
by the side of it.
Put it there.
It says male, and female radial = new
JRadialButton.
Female, of course, female.
[SOUND] And I'm gonna add those to the
button group, so I'll say here.
Gender group.
Equals new button group.
And notice it's button group and not j
button group, which I think it's because
this.
I think this comes from the AWT, the
previous Window toolkit that used to exist
in Java.
I'm not sure.
So let's settle the gender radials here.
Set up gender radials.
[SOUND] And I'm gonna start by adding
those two radial buttons.
To the button group.
So I'll say genderGroup.add maleRadial.
And genderGroup.add, femaleRadial.
And now let's go ahead now and add those
to the form.
And we'll see a couple of little problems
come up, which we can then fix.
So, I'm gonna add the radial buttons on to
rows here.
So let's copy one of these rows.
And here are the male radial.
And I'm gonna put a label by the side of
that.
On the left there that says gender.
And then, on the next row, that should be
new JLabel, new JLabel.
On the next row, I'm gonna add the next
radial button, so let's go down here,
paste this.
And don't need a label for that, so I'll
get
rid of that and I'll say, female add the
female radial.
There we go.
So, if I look at that now one
obvious problem is that these are really
widely spaced.
And that's just the, spacing on my, my
grid layout,
so let's go to where that, where I have
that
mail radial and reduce the weight y for
this particular
row, so let's set it to something really
small like 0.5.
0.05.
So that looks quite a lot better.
And this label looks a bit misalighned.
I'm not paying too much attention to these
labels as I go through.
Cuz fiddling with the labels takes a huge
amount of time.
And it's a matter of taste.
But I will just fix this gender control
because it looks really ugly.
Let's go to, Here, I just change it from
first line end to line
end so it aligns in the middle of the row,
so that looks a little bit better I think.
Now neither of them are selected at the
moment, so let's go up here
and, I'm gonna go to the male radial here.
And I'm gonna set it to selected by
default.
So maleRadial.set, selected true.
And if I run that, then I got male
selected and if I select female, because
they belong to a button group, selecting
one de-selects the other as I want.
Now the next interesting challenge here is
how to find out which one is selected.
And by the way, it's worth mentioning, you
absolutely
can not add action list on to radial
buttons.
But I won't do that here, I want
to actually get information about which is
selected.
At the, at the end so to do that the first
thing I'm going to do
is, I'm going to do, male.
Radial dot add action, actually not add
but set action command and set action
command.
Let's do set a string that you can
then retrieve from the button with get
action command.
So I'm going to set this equal to male
and this is, this is separate to the label
here.
This is some text for kind of internal
purposes.
And let's do the same thing with the
female radial here so female
radial.set action command female and now
what I can do is.
If I go to that, the action listener on
the button.
So down here, this is where I'm collecting
all my data.
I can say
I can say string gender command equals.
And, I can use the button group, so gender
group dot.
Get selection.
And that's gonna return the button, the
radio button that's well
it's gonna return actually the button
model of the radio button.
And on that I can do get action command.
Like this, so that's gonna return male
female.
And of course I could do a dot equals on
that string here
and change it to a boolean, if I wanted,
or something like that.
Let's just put gender in here, and let's
go to, if I click on form event and go to,
and hit F3, in eclipse, so I
can go to the declaration of it and here I
can say String
gender and just do the usual stuff like
here, so private, private string.
Gender and this.gender equals
gender, and I could supply it with a get
gender of course so if I go to source
and generate get this inserters, and I can
have a just a getter for.
Gender.
Okay, so there we go.
And just to show you that working, let's
maybe
oh yerah, I've got, let's change
genderCommand to gender actually.
That makes more sense.
And in the main frame, of course, I could.
Where I receive the event I could make use
of gender some how, if I wanted.
So, I don't know, let's just do a sys out
for the moment.
So, if I.
I've got this form event being seeped
here.
So I could say e.getgender now' cause I've
just added that method get, e.getgender.
And if I run that you're gonna see the,
when I select one of these buttons
and click okay then it's gonna say, female
or male just according to what I select.
So, if I don't touch it, then it's gonna
be male and there's
my string, of that app, to previously
which I'm just gonna remove, actually.
Okay, so, Yeah, that's that.
So like in the next tutorial, I'm gonna
take a break from looking at all these
different form controls, you'll be pleased
to know, and I'm gonna look at menus.
So we can look at the j menu control.
So join me again then, until next time,
happy coding.
[BLANK_AUDIO].