Hello, this is John from
CaveArtProgramming.com and this is
a tutorial on adding menus to your swing
application.
So in a moment I've got this swing
application, and there's no menu here.
And in this tutorial I'm going to show you
how to add a really basic menu
and I'm going to tell you the kind of
minimum you need to work with menus.
And then we'll look at some more advanced
stuff in the next tutorial.
So I'm going to start by going to my main
frame .Java here where I
just create the main frame and I'm going
to give that a new method called, it's
going to be private create menu bar create
menu
bar.
Now if you look at an application like
Eclipse, for example, this.
The thing across the top is called a menu
bar.
We have file, edit, source, refactor, and
so on.
And the, each of the separate things here
are called menus.
And the items in a menu are menu items.
So, I'm going to start by creating a new
JMenu bar, which I'll call menu bar.
And I'll set that equal to a new JMenu
bar.
And I'll just return that from this
function.
So return menu bar.
And let's set return type of this
function.
To jmenubar like so at the import there.
And now, in my mainframe constructor here,
I can just do set jmenubar.
Now don't call set menubar by mistake,
because,
there's a kinda historic method here
called set menubar.
And set menu bar is not compatible with
JMenu bars, so
you need to set J menu bar, not set menu
bar.
So if I run that, it's not gonna look any
different at the moment,
although this may be a faint, so the line
there, where there, many will appear.
And now let's get this a couple of menus,
so I'll have a JMenu.
File menu equals new JMenu and that's
called a file as is traditional and
oh, at the file menu, to the menu bar, so
I'll say menu
bar.@ and I will push in the file menu
like so,.
And let's also have a JMenu window menu
equals new JMenu, so I just add two for
the moment, just to kind of demonstrate
the principles involved and I'll say
menubar.add
window menu, and if I run this.
So now we've got two menus but they've got
no items.
So let's add some menu items to them.
So in the file menu let's have.
A I'll create a JMenu item here.
And I'll call this let's call it export
data.
And I'll set that equal to I'll call it
export data item.
And I'll set it equal to a new JMenu.
An item and I put a text in there.
So, if you look at a file menu usually the
text begins with capital letters and if
you have two words
usually they're capitalized and if you
bring up some other dialogue
you put an ellipses on them, so and that's
worth noting.
For consistency with other applications.
So, the same UJ menu item and export
data...
And that's gonna bring up a dialogue that
allows me to export my data.
So, I'll add the JMenu item import there.
And let's have a importDataItem as well.
So, let's say JMenuItem
ImportDataItem and that's going to say
import data.
And these are going to allow me to
import and export data from my
application, ultimately.
And let's add both of these menu items to.
To the file menu.
So in fact, I'll just, I'll put this
down here so that we're grouping
everything together.
And I'll also jMenuItem.
And as is traditional, let's have a
exitItem.
So an exit item on the menu.
So if you look at this file it's got Exit
down there.
Let's add one here as well.
So exit.
There we go.
That quits the application.
Oh, I could put the equals new JMenu,
menuItem accept.
Okay so let's add those to the File menu.
I'll say, fileMenu.add exportDataItem.
So exportDataItem.
And fileMenu.addi mport, data item.
And, then its other fileMenu,add
separator, like that
to make a nice, so if you look
at menus often they've got like these
Nearly
invisible horizontal lines in them to
separate logical groups.
So we're gonna add one of those separator.
And file menu.add exit item, like this.
Now for the, For the window menu I'm gonna
have a
JMenu I'm gonna actually have a sub menu
here.
And I'm gonna call the sub menu.
So I go to window here.
Here's I've got a show view kind of item.
So, I'm gonna say here.
I'm gonna have a sub menu called show.
So I'll call this, show menu equals new
JMenu, show.
And, show menu is gonna show sub menu,
it's gonna have, At the moment just one
item.
And that item is gonna be, Is gonna be
JMenuItem.
And it's gonna be called showFormItem
= new JMenuItem.
And it's gonna say.
Lets call it, person form maybe, I don't
really know what to call it at the
moment, but that will do, and so I'm gonna
add the show menu.
To the window menu, so I'll say window
menu.add
show menu and I mustn't forget to add the
show form item
to the show submenu, cuz this is slanting
more complex than it really is.
But, you'll see in a minute how this looks
[INAUDIBLE] show menu don't have to show.
PerformItem.
And now, I think I'm good.
So, I've got the, I've got fileMenu and
I'm adding items to the fileMenu here.
While I'm creating items there and putting
them here, without setting up the file
and then I add the file menu to the menu
bar, and the window menu.
So I create the window menu here, and that
[UNKNOWN]
you move that down to organize this a bit
more logically.
So I create a [UNKNOWN] menu.
And I add a show form item to the show
menu, and
I add the show menu to the window menu,
and the window menu I add to the menu box.
Let's have a look and see how that looks.
So I've got a file menu here.
It's got export data, import data and
exit, and the windows.
It's got show.
If I go to that, this submenu opens up,
which just has one item in it at the
moment.
Now I, there's lots of things you can do
with menus, and one useful thing
to do here is that this, you can actually
have check boxes in menus.
And I'm gonna, in the next tutorial, I'm
actually going to show
you how to change this menu item here, so
it uses a chatbox.
And we're going to use that to show and
hide this form here.
And there, there are very similar things
you do in menus.
And we're going to look later on at
mnemonics
and accelerators and pop up menus and
things like that.
So join me agin next time.
Time when we'll be making this menu
actually work.
And it's worth just mentioning here, if
you haven't got the patience to look
through more tutorials on menus, then you
can just add action listeners to your
menu items, and you can respond to them
just like you would with a
normal button, and that will be enough to
get you working with menus already.
But, as I say, in the next tutorial we're
looking at check boxes and menu.
So join me again then.
And until then, happy coding.
[BLANK_AUDIO]