Hello, this is John from
caveofprogramming.com and in
this tutorial we're gonna look at checkbox
menu items.
So if I run this App here, at the moment
I've got this there's this rather nice
menu up here.
[UNKNOWN] doesn't actually do anything yet
and I've got this sub menu here and in
this tutorial, we're gonna change this
person form submenu into a check box
menu item and that's gonna show and hide
this person form here.
So I'll go to the main frame class here,
where I create my menu
and in addition to being able to add menu
items and menus
to to menus you can also add JCheckBox
menu items.
And there's also a JRadio menu item.
And here we're just gonna look at the
JCheckBox menu item.
The J Radio menu item works basically like
radio buttons and
you happen to [INAUDIBLE] and it's pretty
much all the same.
But I'll leave that as an exercise for you
in the interest of keeping these tutorials
reasonably short.
So here I've got my, in fact, I've got my
window menu here.
And I'm, here, adding the show menu to the
window menu.
And the show menu I'm creating here.
And the show menu, I'm just adding a show
form menu item to it.
Which is actually just a menu item.
So if I go up to where I've declared that.
That, which is, yeah it's actually here.
And I'm gonna change this jmenu item to a
jcheck box menu item.
Let's add the import there.
And I'll change this variable declaration
although I'm not sure that actually
matters.
And now if I, yeah if I run that, you'll
see what it looks like already, I'm just
go to
window show and it's got that nice check
box there
which I can check, and I can uncheck it,
such magic.
And I can, I wanna set this initially to
checked so.
If I wanna actually use the methods of it,
so,
then I probably do need to change the
variable as well.
Variable name.
So, I'm gonna you set, select it and I'm
gonna set that equal to true, initially.
And now, in the last tutorial I mentioned
that you can now action
listeners to your J menu items and I'm
gonna add a action listener.
I'm about to add my listeners here.
And I'm start with this this show form
item here.
So I'll say,
showformitem.addactionlistener.
And let's make that new ActionListener,
and, just the same as for button,
and implement the unimplemented
ActionPerformer
[UNKNOWN] with CTRL+N and I'll get rid of
some lines here.
And now I can actually just
if I want to reference the show form item
here, in here, I could do,
I could just make that final, or I could
also just get it from this event here.
So I could say event.get.
source, like this.
And I know the source in this case is
gonna be
a JCheckBox menu item, because that's what
I've added the listener to.
So I can pass that to that and, and I
could create a variable here.
menu, let's just call it menu item.
Equals and then I can say I wanna
show or hide the the person form.
So this mainframe has a bunch of instants,
variables, and one of them says form
panel that contains the form that I've
been working on in the last tutorials.
So I'm gonna just say, form panel.set
visible.
And this also works with dialogues.
By the way.
You can show an enlight dialogues.
Which we'll look at later using set
visible.
And I'll just say that is eq, that is
visible or invisible depending on menu
item dot dot.
Is selected.
There we go.
[SOUND] So just in case that was a bit
confusing here,
I've chosen just to show you an alternate
way of doing this.
I've got the menu item from the source of
the event here.
But I could just have used, this is
basically
pointing to the same place as this
variable here.
And if I declare this variable final here,
in other
words constant, I could have just
referenced that directly here.
But oh sorry not there.
Of course, that's where I'm using it.
But where I declare it, so here, I could
declare that final, and that would enable
me to.
Let's reference it in here.
Just mention it in case you're not too
familiar with, a
kind of referencing stuff from methods of
anonymous classes like this.
So, anyway let's run that, and now
[INAUDIBLE] window menu, and then go to
show.
That's ticked because I set it to selected
to start
with, but if I untick then my forum is
gone there.
It's rather nice, and if I tick it again
then it's back.
There you go.
So and that's the first tutorial.
You can also add icons to a menu.
But in the next tutorial we're gonna take
a look
at mnemonics and accelerators, which is
not completely menu specific.
But it's very useful stuff to know.
So join me again, then.
And until then happy coding.