Hello.
Welcome back.
This is John from caveofprogramming.com.
And in this tutorial, we're gonna look at
Mnemonics and Accelerators.
So I've got this application here and I
have a menu here.
And we're gonna add some Mnemonics and
Accelerators to this menu for a start.
So Mnemonics is actually it's a key that
you press together
with the Alt key that invokes a component
that's already visible.
So if I want to get to the Exit menu here,
the exit, Exit menu item.
Via Mnemonic.
I first got to invoke the File menu, cuz
the File menu is visible.
So I can use the mnemonic on that.
Then I can use the mnemonic on the Exist
menu, when that's visible.
And mnemonics is kind of an accessibility
feature.
And they're also used by many of us just
as a keyboard shortcut.
For expert users, there are also
accelerators and accelerators
work certainly at least on menus even if
they're not
visible and you can set mnemonics on other
controls
besides menus but accelerators I think are
just for menus.
So we're gonna take a look at examples of
both here and
I'm gonna start by making this File > Exit
menu actually do something.
So here I am in my main frame where I
create the menu.
I've got this create menu bar method here
in.
In the main frame.
And I'm gonna add an x, a mnemonics to the
File menu.
So we'll say filemenu.
setmneumonic, setmneumonic.
And there is a version that takes a char
but that's considered obsolete.
So you should use the int fashion.
And the int that you passed to it is
static
constant from the key event class and, and
there are static
const, constants representing all the keys
on your keyboard, so
I'll do Ctrl+Shift+O and I will to add the
import there.
Doesn't seem to have worked.
I want to add VK F, which is stands for
virtual key F.
I'm not sure why I can't add my key event.
Oh, there we go.
Now it's working.
So if I now run my application, you can
see that the
F of File menu is underlined, telling me
that the mnemonic is Alt+F.
So if I hold down Alt now, and press F.
It opens the File menu and I can actually
scroll through that with the arrow keys.
Let's also add a mnemonic on the Exit menu
item.
So I can say exitItem.setMnemonic and for
exit
the most traditional mnemonic is probably
the
the X key, so let's add in
KeyEvent.virtual key X.
And so if I run that now I can do, if I do
Alt+X now I'm hitting Alt+X does nothing.
If I do Alt+F, and then we see the X of
Exit is underlined.
And if I hit now Alt+X, then it invokes my
Exit menu item.
And let's actually make that work, to make
this more interesting.
So exitItem.addActionListener
addActionListener new ActionListener.
Put the brackets in there, and then add
the
actionPerformed method and let's get rid
of some of
these extra lines that I don't need and
put semicolon
in, and then here I would just do System
system.
I accept.
So I always, I always feel that there
should
be some more adequate way of exiting from
Swing programs.
But as far as I know, this is the right
way to do it.
And later on where we are probably gonna
look at well
we are gonna look at adding a confirmation
for the exit here.
So if I run that.
Now if I do Alt+F+X then the application
exits.
You can also add mnemonics to to like form
items so you can add for example
let's take the OK button as an example
search for J button here.
So underneath where I create the OK button
I could do in
fact, what I'll do here, cuz this is a bit
mixed up,
I will delete the OK button, mind creation
from here, and I'll
put it up here, where I'm creating the
other controls just for consistency.
And I can have a comment here saying Set
up op mnemonics, mnemonics.
I think that's spelled right.
And I'm gonna say OK button dot set set
mnemonic, I think it is set mnemonic.
And, KeyEvent.VK
and let's make it, I don't know, vko for
OK.
So that's inside the import there and if I
run
that now, you see the o is underlined of
OK.
And if I do Alt+O, then it clicks OK for
me, which is rather nice.
I can now fall text fields and these other
controls here,
like for example, if I look at let's look
at and combo.
So, end combo, endCombo has no set
mneumonic and the
reason for that is, for these other kinds
of control.
You don't set a mnemonic on a Control
itself.
You set it on an associated label, and you
see here that otherwise you might want
to line the mnemonic if it's in a text
field, there's no text in here.
The text is on this label.
And in fact you set the mnemonic on the
label, so the way that works
is I can say, for example, name
nameLabel.setmneumonic.
SetDisplayed mneumonic, actually.
Displayed Displayed mneumonic.
There we go.
And key events.
And this is a name [INAUDIBLE].
If I run that, you can see let's underline
the.
And in the name as you might expect.
And now what I need to do is I need to say
nameLabel, nameLabel.
And because we need to tell the label what
what
to set the label for so you say
setLabelFor and.
Pass in the nameField there and if I now
run this and I do Alt+N then
it sets the focus in my name field and I
can do Alt+O to submit that information.
So, one last thing for this tutorial,
Which is
we're gonna look at, accelerators which
just apply to menus.
So, as far as I know.
So let's go back to the main frame again
and an accelerator
is a key like I don't have any examples
here in eclipse.
yeah, so like Ctrl+W here is an
accelerator.
And you can invoke accelerators without
the menu actually displaying
so, let's add A accelerator Ctrl+X rather
than Alt+X to the Exit menu item.
And the way to do that is, is say
exitItem.setAccelerator
and then that accepts the Keystroke object
and I actually use the static method to
the keystroke class called.
Get key 'kay, looks like the input there.
And getKeyStroke.
And the, the method I want takes two
parameters, and the
first parameter is a key event, it's a
Virtual key code.
VK_X, is what I'll use in this case for
the X key.
And then you need.
A a method of, sorry a static constant of
the ActionEventClass,
rather strangely, and I want to use in
this case, a CTRL_MASK
constant, so you can see the accelerator,
unlike the mnemonic, the mnemonic
is made for one key, the accelerator's
made for two keys because.
The mnemonic is always Alt, but
accelerated you can choose
your key so I'm choosing CTRL_MASK with
the X key.
And if I now run that, if I look at the
menu I'll use my, my, mnemonic actually.
You can see that it's not only is it
outlining the x
of x out, which's the mnemonic, but it's
put Ctrl+X in here.
Which is the accelerator.
Let's get rid of the menu and if I do
Ctrl+X, it now quits my application.
Ctrl+X, there we go.
So accelerators are for expert uses and
you can gradually learn tha, the
accelerators of an application, and invoke
them without actually opening the menu.
So that's enough for this tutorial.
And in the next tutorial, we're gonna look
at option panes and I'm gonna
show you how to add a confirmation here to
this Exit menu item.
So, join me again then and until next
time, happy programming.