[BLANK_AUDIO]
Hello, this is John from Cave of
Programming dot com and this is a tutorial
on J Option panes which are, a quick way
of producing those handy
little dialogues that pop up to ask you if
you wanna do things or not.
Basically, and we're just gonna show you
two simple types here, although that's
a plethora of possibilities, so in the
last tutorial,
I cre, created this application, and I, in
particular, we added some stuff to this.
Menu to make it work.
So if I go to exit here, it quits, or I
can also do control x, for example.
Now I want, the application to ask me if
I'm really sure that I want to quit.
Because although that's, quite annoying,
at the same time, it.
It can be quite useful.
It can stop you losing data that you
haven't saved and that sort of thing.
So let's assume that you think it's a good
idea to do that.
And here I'm gonna put, I'm gonna create a
little dialogue box that will
pop up and just ask the user if he or she
really wants to quit.
Now to do that I'm gonna use the.
J Option Pane.
So if you go to Google and search for J
Option Pane
job seven or something like that then
you'll come up with this page.
And it looks pretty ferocious but there's
only really four main possibilities.
You can create confirm dialogues, which is
what I want to create.
Here, a dialogue that asks you if you want
to really do something or not, and you
might have a no button on there, or a
cancel button, and a yes or an okay
button.
An input dialogue, which I'll show you
also in this tutorial, gets just a little
bit of input, just a little bit of text
from the user, which is sometimes useful.
Message dialogues, just display a message.
And option dialogue is the most flexible
kind of type that allows
you to kind of roll your own using a
variety of constants.
And of course check out this page to get
the, full details on this.
But here, so I want to use the static
option of J Option Pane and I'm gonna use.
Show confirm dialogue.
So, let's just add the import and then the
auto complete will the work.
So, I'll use show confirm dialogue and you
can see that they are.
And various possibilities of constructor,
sorry not constructor.
Of overloaded method just for this show
confirm dialogue.
And the one I want to use, the simplest
one, just takes a handle to.
component which I believe can be null, as
far as I
remember, and a message that you wanna
output in a dialog.
But I actually wanna customize this a bit
more, so I'm gonna use this version here.
So the first document to the show confirm
dialog,
is gonna be, I'm gonna use the mainframe
window handle,
and because I'm in a.
Kind of anonymous, sort of inner class
here.
If I type this I'm gonna get, a handle to
the, anonymous class rather than the main
frame, so I need to cite the main frame,
do this, to get this for the main frame.
The message I'm gonna make, Do you really
want to exit the application?
That should do the trick.
Question mark there.
And, let's, maximize the editor here, to
get some more space.
And the title, let's.
Put confirm, I don't know, confirm exit
should do the trick.
And then the interesting bit here is the
option type.
And I want say J Option Pane, and I want
a, let's have a.
A, okay button, and a cancel button.
So I'm gonna say here J Option pane, okay,
cancel option, like that.
And, put semicolon in, control shift F to
format a bit.
Now if I run that, Okay.
It's not actually gonna work at the
moment.
But if I do, control X, I get this here.
So it's got an okay and a cancel.
And it's, nice little question mark there.
And it doesn't matter what I do now.
It's gonna exit.
So to actually make it do something, I
need to retrieve the value here.
So I'm gonna say, int.
Action lets call it equals the return
value of show Confine Dialog.
And I can check the action.
And I can say if action equals, equals J
Option Pane.
Okay, option.
So it will return okay option, if the user
clicks okay.
If the user clicks okay.
I'm gonna just do the system dot accept.
And otherwise, just ignore it.
So, I'll use the.
The accelerator and control X to bring up
the file.
X the option again, so control X.
And if I click cancel now, nothing
happens.
And if I click okay, then it quits.
So that's that.
And that's all I got use for.
For this application right now.
But I just want to show you the message
dialogue as well.
Which might be used shortly.
Let's just copy this bit because it looks
pretty similar.
And I'll just make it come up here.
Just for a minute and I'll delete it
later.
So, let's say show.
Sorry not message but input dialog.
And let's get rid of that so again, I'm
passing the handle to my parent window.
That's the first argument.
And then some kind of, message.
Let's say enter your
username.
And a title there.
Enter username and let's
just have the okay option there and if I
run that,
and I'll just invoke it by doing control X
and you see that I've got
a little thingy where I can enter some
text here, Now this icon looks a
bit funny and so there are two things i
want to fix about it now.
I wanna retrieve this text and I wanna
change
that icon and this is a an arrow icon.
So lets do that by here so called J Option
Pane or Okay Option.
I kind of use a binary.
Bit wise kind of,
I can actually put another integer value
in there and just do a
bit wise or in it like this with a like
vertical pipe there.
And I can say J Option Pane dot, and I
want.
I think it's information message.
And that's, that's just an icon
that's gonna look, appropriate for some
information.
So if I do that, then it would look like
this.
It's got an I there.
And other possibilities, because this
probably isn't actually what I want.
You could have for example a warning
message icon.
So, if I run that and it looks like that
it's a question mark is a tri, sorry, an
exclamation mark in a triangle and, but
the one I probably want here is.
Just the question, question message.
And i'm going get the return body from
that so I'm going to say string text
equals.
And that's just equals and let's do this
out here, and
I'm going to delete the suffix, we don't
actually need this.
I just wanted to show you it working.
So if I run that then do control X to
invoke it.
Enter username.
You've got a nice question there.
And if I enter like, cancel then it's
gonna return null.
And if I run it.
And I enter okay, but don't actually type
anything in.
It's just going to return empty space.
And if I actually bump into something.
I'm going to click okay here.
Then I'm going to get text retrieved so
I'm retrieving my text now.
And, so I just want to show you that just
to demo it, but as you can
see the thing is that show input dialogue
is almost the same as show input dialogue.
And the only extra trick that I've really
added
there is, well for one thing, instead of
retrieving
the action which tells you which button is
clicked,
you can retrieve text with a show input
dialogue call.
And the other thing is just using this or
[INAUDIBLE] and then doing
this J Option Pane dot question, message
to change the icon there.
But apart from that it's the same as this
confirm dialogue.
So let's remove that because I've done
what I
wanted to do, and before I leave this
tutorial,
I just want to show you one other thing
that I noticed was quite funny about this
application.
Which is at the moment if I resize it like
this, the form can go
a bit mental like that, so I want to stop
it getting too small 'cause I
want there to be enough space for this
form to fit on there without it getting
warped or distorted or anything and I'm
gonna fix that just by going to my main.
Frame.
In my main frame I've already set, set
size, but what
I'm gonna do is just set a minimum size as
well.
So, set minimum size, and let's, let's try
that at 500, 400 and see how that looks.
And I thought this has to be not two,
integers.
But it has to be a new dimension and we've
seen, the dimension,
before, I think we have anyway, because,
yeah, I used it on the jpanel.
So, let's run that.
And if I resize that now, it will only go
to a certain minimum
size, which is what I wanted, that
protects my form from getting screwed up.
Okay, so that's it for this tutorial, and
in
the next tutorial we're gonna look at the
very exciting.
A file chooser dialog and we're going to
get a lot of functionality for free.
So I'm make use of this file menu allows
me to bring up
a file chooser dialog, where I can choose
to import or export data.
So join me again then and until next time
happy coding.