Hello, this is John from
Caveofprogramming.com, and this is
a tutorial on file chooser dialogs in Java
swing.
So at the moment, I've got this
application, and I've got this File menu.
And I can go to Export Data and Import
Data.
And I wanna make that.
Bring up File, choose a dialogue.
So I can choose to Open a file, or to Save
it.
And we're gonna look at that in this
tutorial.
So the first step is I wanna reuse the
same file chooser dialogue
every time because I wanna customize that
dialogue, and I wanna use it for both.
To my open and save files operations, file
operations.
And I also, wanted to remember where I
browsed
to the last time I opened it and for that
reason I'm gonna just use one file to use
the dialogue rather than create a new one
every time.
So here in my main frame I'm gonna
create a private JFileChooser and I'm
gonna call that.
FileChooser and add the import there.
And let's maximize [UNKNOWN] control them.
And now here in the constructor mainframe
I'll
create a new FileChooser object equals new
JFileChooser.
And I'll go down here.
Scroll down to our create the menu, and I
want to add a couple of action listeners
on my menu items so I'll say
ImportDataItem.addActionListener.
And this ImportDataItem is just the j menu
item,
you might remember from previous episodes
in this tutorial series.
So, I'm gonna add the ActionListener here.
And let's add the action perform method at
the
ActionListener as we have done so many
times before now.
And in here, to start with I'm just gonna
say FileChooser.showOpen,Open Dialog.
And for the parent window I'll parse in
mainframe.this, so that it knows
where its parent window is and it knows
where to appear and that sort of thing.
So now if I run that, that's already gonna
work.
File Import Data like this.
I can select.
I can Cancel it.
Or I can select files.
But to actually get the file that's
chosen.
One thing you wanna check whether this
Open Dialog returns an a value that
means that the user's clicked the confirm
button, the Open button rather than
clicking Cancel.
So let's say if, let's wrap this in an if
and say if the return value of that is
JFileChooser.APPROVE_OPTION, then, we're
gonna really open the file.
Otherwise we'll just ignore it.
And for the moment, I'll just do a sys out
cuz
I just wanna print the name of the file
for the moment.
And I'll say FileChooser.getSelectedFile.
And so I'm relying on the two string
method of, this
actually returns a file object, but if I
do sys out on
there, it's just gonna do a, I'm just
gonna see the
path, cuz it will just invoke the two
string method of file.
So now let's run that and see how it
looks.
So I do File Import Data.
And let's pick a file here.
well, you can see that I can browse
between different directories.
Now let's pick this file and go to Open
and here I've got the name of the
file and it's returning the file object
that actually
represents the file so I could open this
now.
And in future tutorials so, we haven't
actually got a data model
for this application at the moment, what
I'm doing really is all kind of view.
So in a future tutorial soon we're gonna
look at creating a simple data model.
And when we've got the data model, we can
then look at saving that data.
But for the moment we're just gonna
concentrate on getting the app.
The actual files to save to or open And
for my
Export Data item I'll add a very similar
listener, so let's just change this
to Export, since this is the export data
item, instead of show open
dialog, quite simply I'm gonna change this
to show Save Dialog, like that.
And if I run this now and do Export Data.
This brings up the Save Dialog that says
Save.
And, if I choose file, and then it's gonna
output the
name of the file that I chose here because
it's doing this.
So that's, that's enough for this
tutorial, I think.
And in the next tutorial, we're gonna
refine this.
File dialog a little bit because we're
gonna actually, if you, you see
in the moment you can choose any file, but
in the next tutorial
we're gonna look at how you add filters to
the file so that
you can, narrow this down to particular
kinds of files with particular extensions.
And in closing I just wanna point out a
really useful resource here, if you
go to Google, and I've mentioned this Also
in the first tutorial.
And you search for swing visual guides
components.
This is re, a really really useful page.
So click on the first entry there, and if
you search in there
for FileChooser, you can see extensive
examples on how to use a FileChooser.
And one thing that it talks about here
that
I'm not gonna show you in these tutorials
is you
can actually create little custom panels,
which show like
a custom view of the files that you're
looking at.
And there's also some really useful code I
think if you search for Utils.Java in
there.
Then there's actually a they actually give
you a little
utils class here that gets the extension
from a file name.
But we're gonna, I'm gonna implement my
own for these tutorials.
But that's, and you can easily figure that
out.
It's just kind of string handling stuff.
But this is, this is quite handy.
So that's it for this tutorial.
In the next tutorial, as I say we'll look
at filtering this file.
So join me again then.
And until next time, happy coding.