Hello, this is John from
caveofprogramming.com.
Welcome back and this is a tutorial
on adding filters to your file chooser
dialogs.
So in a moment if I run my application and
I go to File, Export Data.
It allows me to select any file.
But I wanna narrow this down so that I can
only export
or save, save or import, certain kinds of
files with certain, particular extensions.
So to do that let's go to where I create
my file chooser in Main Frame here.
And that's where I'm creating the file
chooser.
And I'm gonna say, fileChooser.add.
And it's add I think it's add actually, I
always forget this.
But let's take a look here, at choosable
file filter.
There we go.
And add choosable file filter accepts a,
it accepts
objects of type file filter, which is an
abstract class.
So I have to implement my own, file filter
there.
And I'm gonna do that now.
So let's go to new class and I'll say,
I'll call this, person file filter
because this application kinda allows you
to enter personal details.
So, I'll call this person file filter and
I'm gonna make
that, a superclass of that file filter,
the abstract file filter class.
And it's at the import.
And now if I click on this Error message
here in Eclipse, I can add and implement
methods.
And there are only two methods that you
need to implement.
There's the accept, which determines, it
returns true if you wanna accept the
file and allow the user to select it, or
false if you don't.
And the description, returns a description
of the
kind of file that this file filter filters
on.
So in my description here, I'm gonna say
return and I'll return this string
that says person file, person files.
Person database files, how's that?
And in brackets I'm just gonna put the
filter and let's say that this application
uses files with an extension of PER,
completely arbitrary.
PER standing for person, of course.
And now here so I've got my file as the
argument
here to accept and I need to do something
with that.
And what I'll do is I'll get their file
name.
So I'll say string, name equals
file.getName.
And I wanna check the extension of this
file name here.
And you could write some just string
handling stuff here.
But I've actually already written a little
utils class here as a static method.
And well it still says you can find it.
And by the way, you can find a very
similar
thing in the, if you search for official
guides, Java, components.
Official guides, swing components in
Google.
Then go to the go to the file chooser.
Page that, you can see that they have
actually
created a tools class that's actually
similar to this.
But what I've done is, I've got the last
index of the dot for start and the file
name.
And I've said if that's equal to minus 1
return null, because if last in text
solved returns minus 1 it means it doesn't
find the dot anywhere in the given string.
And then I say if the point index is equal
to name.length
minus 1, it means the dots right at the
end of the string.
It means the file has no extension
basically,
so I return null, otherwise I return
name.substring and
I return the first character of the
substring is,
just after where the full stop period is
found.
And the last character is gonna be right
at the end of the string.
So you pass in name.length, because
substring
doesn't actually include the character at
this index.
This includes characters up to this index
here.
So in my personal file filter, now I can
say string
extension equals, and I can just use my
utils
class method there, get file extension
from the string.
So return me all the stuff after the last
dot in the file name,
and if the extension is equal to null, of
course then that's no use to
me, so return false, it means it doesn't
have an extension.
else, I can say, if extension dot equals.
And let's just say I only want it if I
only
want to accept the file if the, if the
extension's PER.
Then I can say return true.
And now, where I create the file chooser
here, I can say, new person file filter.
Just passing an object of that class
there.
And if I run this now, I do either export
or import, can say such percentage
page files start appear so this is the
string that I added to my file filter.
And its gonna filter and it gonna let me
select files with the PER extension.
If you want more than one filter codes,
then
you need to add choose file filter
multiple time.
Kinds of different filters that you've
designed.
But here I just want to filter purely on
PER.
So I've actually created a file with a PER
extension at the moment.
And one problem you can see here is that I
can't actually select direct to it, which
is completely useless.
Because how can I browse the files that I
want, and to get around that, you need say
here in your file filter, if
file.isdirectory, then
you always wanna return true like this.
So, now if I run this and I do file and
export data, let's say and
I can browse to see and in my docs folder
here, so it's not showing the directories.
I created a test up PER and I can select
that and
at the moment it's just outputting the
thing I've selected down here.
So that's it for this tutorial one thing
that,
I, I'm not gonna go through in this series
of
tutorials that you can find on the
Jfilechooser page
of the swing, of the visual guide swing
components page.
Is you can actually out custom panels to
your
file choosers to show like a display of
your file.
But I'm not gonna make use of that here.
I'll leave you to look into that for
yourself.
And in the next tutorial we're gonna
look at something that's not really swing
specific.
But it's extremely useful if you're
designing swing applications.
And that's we're gonna talk a bit
more about the model view controller
architecture.
And in particular we're gonna implement a
data model here, so
that I've got somewhere to actually store
my database of people, details.
So join me again next time, and until next
time, happy coding.