Hello, this is John from
caveofprogramming.com.
Welcome back.
In this tutorial we're gonna look at
creating
a very simple data model for our
application here.
So the stuff we've been working on so far,
is all the, the gooey part of the
application.
It's the view.
And now I wanna create some way of
storing the people the whose details are
entered here,
So we're gonna be looking at kind of the
back end whereas this is the front end.
And I'm gonna start by creating a new
package.
So I'm gonna go to new package and I'm
going to call that
gooey and I'm gonna take all the code that
I've got at the moment.
So I'll just Shift+Select these files.
And I'm gonna drag and drop them into GUI.
And that's gonna re-factor my codes a
little bit so
that it puts package GUI at the top of my
files.
If I run that, it should still run just
fine.
And I'm gonna create a new, another new
package.
So, New Package, which I'll call I'll call
it Model.
And Model is gonna contain classes that
deal.
With my database and in fact just to start
with I'm just gonna store the data
in Java code here where my application
runs.
And later will occur connecting this to a
database.
But for the moment I'm just gonna
create some very, very simple data
handling classes.
And now the golden rule here is that stuff
in your
model should absolutely never reference
stuff in your, in your view.
The stuff in the back end should never
reference stuff
in the front end to say in, in another
way.
So in the classes end model I should never
ever have.
A statement that says import GUI whereas
the
GUI may well reference the the model
although often
the GUI communicates through the model
exclusively through
controller classes, which we'll look at in
the future.
But right now I'm gonna start by creating
a class in my model and I'm gonna
call this person, and person is gonna be a
class
that stores people while the application
is running.
So it's gonna be a lot like.
This form event class.
Except that whereas the form event just
takes whatever data
comes back form the form and transmits it
to the mainframe.
My person class should be much more tight
in terms of the way it stores data.
The person class we'll see in a minute,
but it's gonna store
data in a kind of clearest form possible,
and it's gonna you know, we're gonna have
some notion of really trying to ensure
data integrity here, so here, so
I've got, my person's gonna have a name,
but I'm also gonna give it a private.
ID, and the ID is gonna be the unique key
of my persons,
my people in the database, which I'm gonna
connect up in future.
Now string name is fine.
Let's take a look at this form actually.
So occupation again is just a string.
But each category here, there's only three
choices.
So it shouldn't really be a string.
It should be something which is limited to
three values when we
store it in the actual kind of data model
or in a database.
And in your.
If you have a sequel database you'd
probably use
some kind of a non type and we can
do the same thing in Java, so let's create
a let's create a new class here in the
model.
And you, I'll make it actually a new
enumeration,
a new non, and I'm gonna call that anon.
Age category, age category and the age
category's only gonna have
three possible values under 18, 18 65, and
65 or over.
So let's call those, let's call those
categories child.
Adult senior.
So it goes this is a anon and then in my
person here
I can change the age category from an int
which could be anything to a AgeCategory
Okay, and the employment category is gonna
be similar because employment
here is well, actually, it's probably not
gonna be sim, similar,
similar, because the thing is that people
can type what they want in here.
Yeah.
So let's probably, leave that as a string.
I'm just kind of thinking on my feet here.
I think actually I'm gonna create a
employment category as well.
So, I'll right click the model again.
And I go to new
class and I'll call that employment
category.
And let's, let's just say here that we can
have
employed in here.
Self employed.
So
maybe capitalize this, employed.
Some people put these enumeration
constants in all capital
letters but I'm not gonna worry too much
here.
unemployed.
And we could have a category buffer, for
if they type something in themselves and
you could go to the trouble of storing of
exactly or actually I meant not to
make that a class, but, in so you,
whatever they type in over there you
might wanna store it separately, but I
think
for this little application here I'm just
gonna.
Store other if someone types something
into this combo box.
And then the other stuff we need, we need
to boolean for US citizen probably int for
tax ID, I don't know, or string and we've
got male or female as well, so I
think since, again, male or female has two
values, or it may
have,um, three cuz apparently, These days
after you can put author
on the agenda form, then let's give this
a, let's create a
new anon here, so not a new class, but a
new anom.
And let's make this let's call this
gender, and let's get this.
Values of male and female.
So that'll do.
And now, in my person
class here, I can say that the gender has
type gender.
So I'm just using anoms.
For the situations where I've got like,
you
know, three strings or two strings, but
they can
only actually have two or, you know, they
can only take one of two or three values.
They're not actually free text.
It makes sense to have an enom to store
them.
So I think that's all okay now, so
employment category.
Yeah, that's gonna be type employment
category.
Like this.
Tax ID property string really.
Looks okay.
So now that's let's go ahead and.
Create the getters and setters.
So, I'll right click, go to source,
generate getter and setters and I wanna
generate getters and setters for all of
them here, like this.
And for the moment, I'll just give it I
don't know if I really.
Want to construct it, because to create a
constructor
with all these values is going to be quite
long.
I mean to actually let's say, public
person and let's, yeah, why not?
So let's, let's say int ID.
In fact, I miss our ID.
For the moment, so I got set ID, I'll just
give it a string name, string
occupation, occupation
age category, agecat, let's say, well
let's make it agecategory, why not?
Employment category employmentCategory
String taxID, boolean US
citizen, and Gender gender.
And this of course will have.
To this.name equals name.
This is a
bit boring.
So this.occupation equals occupation.
I don't know if there are any shortcuts
in Eclipse, for dealing with this kind of
thing.
I suspect not.
And this.employmentCategory.
Oh yeah, I've called it m category, mcat
there.
So let's call it mcat here as well then.
Mcat equals mcat, and this.taxId equals
taxId.
This.USCitizen, we're almost there.
Equals US citizen and this.gender equals
gender.
Now I will make the ID increment itself.
I'll put a private static count.
Let's just.
Explicitly set it to null although it will
be initialized
to null anyway and that should be a type
int.
And then in here I can say this.id equals
count and count plus plus.
So every time I create a new person,
it'll increment the count which will be
semicolon and
if I then set the idea explicitly
afterwards
it will override this value here, which is
good.
So, I'm just using This static variable,
classic use of static variable, just
to count how many people there are, and to
create an ID there.
So now I've got a person class that can
store people
in some kind of database, and I'm just
gonna do something.
Really simple here.
I'm just gonna right click and create a
new class and I'm gonna call that
let's call it database for the moment and
database
I'm gonna give it a private array.
ListofPeople, so let's put person, in this
array list
and set that equal to well, let's give it
constructor.
So public database, Database.
And let's s, say that, people
equals new ArrayListOfPerson.
And this is, this is gonna be the class,
I'm just
gonna use for the moment to store people
in my database.
And then we can have a method, for
example, I'll
add to this as we go along, but like
public void.
Add person which just accepts a person,
and just says people.addperson.
And we could have a method that gets the
array list, so public let's say list of.
Person, so use the list interface and say
get people like this and just return
people.
You have to be careful because you can
modify this using your
return value like this, but I won't worry
about it too much.
It's I just have to input that.
Java util list.
So now I've got a little data base
thing that can store people while the
application's running.
I'm gonna work on this and later on we're
gonna connect it to an actual data base.
And in the next tutorial I'm gonna create
some controller codes.
That's gonna kind of interface between the
view here and
the model here and it's gonna allow me to
add people to this
sort of database and then [INAUDIBLE]
wecan look at.
Representing those people visually.
So that's it for this tutorial and the
next
tutorial, as I say, we'll extend this a
bit
further and we'll actually start storing
people, so join
me again then, and until next time, happy
coding.