Hello, this is John from caveof
programming.com, and, in this tutorial
we're going
to look at implementing the controller bit
of the model view controller architecture.
Now I don't intend this to be a
a two, a series of tutorials on software
architecture.
But I wanna implement the kind of minimal
architecture that
I need here to give to make my Swing app
work, even if it's not the most efficient
app in
the world or anything, and it doesn't do
anything very interesting.
I wanna at least make it make sense, so
that
you can see what the difference between
components doing something.
A vaguely useful.
So, if you don't wanna go into software
architecture at all, then feel free to
skip ahead and we'll get back to swing
components in the next lesson.
So, I'm gonna create, I've got my GUI
package here that's got GUI code in it.
I've got my data model here.
and, and the way a lot of software
developers think of this is
that the model's gotta be water tight, and
it's gotta really preserve your data.
Whereas the GUI could be this thing that
it may even crash all the time.
You know, as GUIs tend to do, who knows?
But hopefully it won't do that.
But the point is that the model must be
very reliable and highly tested.
And whereas the GUI, you just want it to
look nice and hopefully work most of the
time.
So if you've got logic, so called business
logic that doesn't isn't obviously to do
with,
you know, text boxes and text areas and,
you know, check boxes and things like
that.
So it's not part of the view, the GUI.
And it's not part of the data handling, we
call it \Data Handling Code.
Then that logic is considered part of the
controller, and we may as well create a
special
package for it here, so I'll say new, I'll
right click on source actually, and I'll
say new
new package, and I'll just call that
controller.
[SOUND] There's nothing cast iron about
this.
You wouldn't necessarily do this in a
real application, although you would, at
the very
least have a rigid demarcation between
back
end model code and front end GUI code.
So in the controller, I'm actually gonna
create
a class here, which I'll just call
Controller.
Controller and I'm gonna
give so the main frame, is gonna call
controller, when
it wants to add stuff to the database, and
I'm gonna go to the mainframe here.
And we're gonna give it a private
controller, control box and the main frame
calls the controller and the main frame
actually is
a sort of controller in itself really,
because it hooks.
Some of the components and tells them what
to do [NOISE] but I'm going to have like
an actual controller that interfaces
between the database, and
sort of more, more sort of gooey specific
code.
So that's yeah, added the input there and
that's create.
A controller here equals new controller.
Like this and now the, the test that I
want to handle in this
tutorial is that the the the kind of,where
is it?
When.
When stuff is added to the form.
Someone clicks the Okay button.
Basically raises its form event.
Which carries information about people.
And at the moment it's just sort of
outputting some of it in the text area.
Which we're gonna change to a J table
shortly.
And, what I want to do here is I want.
This to actually add the data to a
database, even if for the moment it's only
gonna be basically an array list, and to
do that, I
need to transform this data to stuff that
could go in this.
Person object here.
So to do that.
If I go to yeah.
If I go back to my main frame.
I could.
One thing I could do is I could have
control, a
method on controller that accepts all
these different pieces of data.
And then turn and then creates a person
object, and adds it to the database.
Or I could just pass this event to the
controller really.
And I think I'll do that.
Because although I feel that possibly
having a method
here that accepts all the different pieces
of information.
It might be more elegant because it avoids
referring to the form event in the
controller class.
Just to save time actually I'm just gonna
give it a method here that, called public
void.
addPerson.
And it's just gonna accept the form event
and call it
ev.
And so now in my main frame.
Start the import for that.
And, and here as I'm importing GUI stuff
into my controller.
And that's not so bad.
But what most.
Never happen, is you must never import GUI
stuff into your data model,
so let's go to the mainframe here, and I'm
gonna say here,
controller.addPerson and just pass at
this.
Event here, and let's get rid of all that
stuff.
I search the E, not the EV okay?
Now, in this method the first thing to do
is get all the information I need from the
events.
Let's say string name equals
event.getName.
And string occupation, occupation, equals
event.getOccupation.
And, let's run the application and see
what else it's got in, it's got age.
[UNKNOWN] Age, category.
So
we've got an event.getAgeCategory which
return an int, so int
age cat and calls and we've got an
employment category then.
GetEmploymentCategory, which returns the
string, so string empCat equals.
And we've also got a US citizen Boolean.
So, Boolean is US equals ev.get.
Actually it is US citizen and you may have
a tax ID, or that may be set to nothing.
It may be null or empty.
So string tax ID equals event.getTaxId.
and.
And this looks for gender.
So event.getGender.
And that returns a string.
So string gender equals.
Now my person takes, it has kind
of different requirement for how it's
constructed.
And so let's say Person person equals new
Person.
I'm gonna, after I supply a bunch of
things to the constructor here, and
when I've constructed the person, then I
can add it to the database with this.
So, let's have the, let's make the
controller have a reference to the
database.
So let's say database.
Db equals new Database.
There we go.
And then, I can port, and then I can say
db.add
person and then I can add the person that
I created there.
So now I just need to.
To take these, and transform them to the
appropriate type to supply to the person
constructor.
So if I put my cursor between these two
round brackets in the person
constructor, and hit Ctrl+Space in
eclipse, it
shows me all the arguments I need.
So, I need a name, occupation,
now I need age category, so, yup, so that
should be.
I should've known.
Just paste it.
Hcutler.
And I've lost my auto complete.
So let's take a look at this.
So age category.
Oh, it's actually I just got it wrong.
It's actually an age category.
enumeration.
So let's say AgeCategory, ageCategory.
And let's say switch page cut
and in fact let's call this.
Age catId to make it more explicit, what
it is.
And I can say switch age cat, age catId,
and case 0
I can set ageCategory to ageCategory
.child, and if you remember, age category
is.
Is this enumeration that I've got here.
So I'm transforming from the integer which
the form returns to the enumeration.
And that may or may not be a necessary, or
a good
thing to do, depending on your database
and, you know, kinda preferences.
But I'll do it here just to do something.
So and case 1.
Set it to adult, and case 2, we'll set it
to
senior, and ten I can supply a age
category there,
and my autocomplete's helped me come back,
so that's.
Invoke auto complete, press F2 to get this
focus.
I can scroll.
Now I need employment category.
So I need the same thing again basically.
Employment category, you're call on the
phone.
People can select from one of three
categories, or they can type stuff
themselves.
So let's have a variable of type
employment
category, and category, and let's do, I
can't
do switch on a string, I don't think, so
let's
say, if if empcatdoc equals employed then,
I'm gonna say, empCategory equals.
Employment category.employed.
else, and then let's copy and paste this.
So we're gonna say else if it equals
selfEmployed then we have selfEmployed.
If it equals unemployed then this equals
unemployed.
And finally, we've got another which is
where
the, the user types something his or
herself.
So let's say else there it equals other.
And in the case of it equalling other, I'm
just gonna,
in lieu of doing actual testing, which of
course you should do.
Let's get this working.
I'm just gonna say system.add.printLn.
I'm gonna print out the empCat just to
remind me and just so I can see that if
it is equal to other that it's not
self-employed, unemployed, or employed.
Just as a debugging aid there.
So, system.airPrints kind of red text down
here in the console.
And now I can add empCategory to to this
constructor.
And, let's take a look at what else.
I need in here, so I've got employment
category tax ID, US citizen, gender.
So let's have here tax ID US see what I
called it up here, let's
maximize the editor with Ctrl+N, and.
And I called it is US, so that's put in
here and it's US, true or false
and then I need a gender, which again, is
a category thing.
So, that's our gender gender except that I
think I've already used gender up here.
So, let's call that gender count.
And I can say if gender.equals
male then genderCut
equals gender.male.
Let's add the import there.
Yeah, okay.
And else.
And I shall presume that gender Cat equals
gender.female, if not male.
And then let's add this here.
So genderCat.
Okay.
If I save that I still got an error
age category may not have been initialized
and that's because
I haven't gotten a default case here.
So let's say well let's just
say [INAUDIBLE] equals to mean
[INAUDIBLE].
So now when I fill in the person details
then
hopefully it's just gotten in to my data
base or if
you haven't seen it happen and what we're
going to do.
Tutorial is, I'm gonna change this text
area to a J table, and
we're gonna look at viewing the data in
the database, in that J table.
So join me again next time, where we'll
get back to looking at actual swing
components.
And until then, happy coding