Hello this is John from
caveartprogramming.com and in
this tutorial we're gonna look at tables
in Java.
So what I'm gonna do, is I'm gonna replace
this text area here with a J table.
So to start off with, I'm gonna create a
panel to hold the table.
So let's create a new class and I'll call
it Table Panel,
and I'll make it an extend JPanel, and,
at the import, [UNKNOWN] skip that
constructor, so public table on our
and now I'm gonna give this a private
instance of JTable, so JTable table.
And in the constructor, I can say table
equals new JTable at the import.
And lets set the border, the, the layout
to
Border Layout and so set out new border
layouts.
I just wanna add the table in the middle
here and [INAUDIBLE] will do the trick.
So I can say
addtableandborderlayout.center, there we
go.
And now, back in my main frame, I can add
that, into
the main frame, I can say here, Private
Table Panel, Table Panel.
So I've added an instance for able to the
main frame of my new class and down here,
where I create the different panels, I can
say Table Panel equals New Table Panel.
And of course, down here I need to add it
to the main frame.
And for the moment I'm just gonna replace
text panel and [UNKNOWN] will bring text
panel
back and I wanna show you how to use tabs,
but for the moment that will do.
So if I just run that, it doesn't look
like anything at the moment.
And that's 'cuz we've gotta get the data
into it somehow.
And there are various ways of doing that.
You could use a default table model.
But, I'm gonna do it a slightly different
way.
In my Table Panel, well, actually, first
things first.
I'm gonna actually create a new class in
this GUI package here.
New Class and I'm gonna make this New
Class and
we're gonna call it table, let's call it
Table Model.
Maybe I should call it Person Table Model.
And I'm gonna make it extend, Abstract
Table Model.
Abstract Table Model and I'll click
Finished at the imports there.
And if I click on this error message here,
it's
gonna say I've got to implement a bunch of
methods.
So let's implement those.
And now the rest of the tutorial is
basically
largely gonna consist of implementing
these methods, so I've got
one for getting the column count, getting
the row
count, and getting the value a particular
row and column.
And so this is actually not too complex,
really.
And, but [INAUDIBLE] in table panel here,
what I'm gonna have to do, is
I'm gonna somehow gonna have to create one
of these person table models for starts.
So let's do that.
Let's say private person table model,
table model.
And down here I can say table model equals
new person
table model, and then I can pass that to
the
constructor of the JTable, passing the
table model there.
And now, so, if I run that it still
made them crash but it's still not gonna
do anything.
So now I need to get my data into
the Abstract Table model, 'cuz this
abstract, this Person Table
Model is really just a wrap up for my data
that presents it in the right way for my
table.
So first of all I, if I take a look
at my controller here, so I've got, so
there's my model.
I've also got this controller package with
a controller class in it.
And I could, I'm gonna in this tutorial,
this series of tutorials, let's just
say it's not intended to be a set
tutorials on Software Architecture.
But, I'm gonna have the policy that my GUI
stop
is gonna communicate with the data model
only through this controller.
So, I'm gonna give this controller a
public
method that returns a list of person
objects.
And I'm gonna call that getpeople.
And that's just gonna wrap my
db.getpeople.
And so if I say that, I then input the job
utility list.
And, and now, I need to get this somehow,
let's just have a look at this.
Yeah.
I've gotta actually have a return.
Now I need to somehow pass this list of
people here, to my table model.
So to do that I'm gonna have to get it
into this, table panel, which is where the
table model is.
So I've got a table panel, with a table in
it, and a table
model and the table model's created a main
frame, and I wanna route my
kind of data and my communications through
main frame here, so that our main
frame is acting a little bit like sort of
local controller for my GUI.
and, and to do that, I'm gonna give this
table panel a method.
I'm gonna give it a method called setData
which
accepts a list of person objects.
So let's call that let's call that DB cuz
it's basically the database
and I give it a private variable here,
let's say private
in fact I probably don't really need a
private variable at all
because what I can do is I can say on my
table model.
If I go the person table model, I can give
this the constructor.
So I can say public person table model,
and I can make the constructor
accept a list of person objects, so-called
DB.
And I can create a local a private
variable here, an instanced variable of
the same type.
And I can send a constructor this.bdb
equals db.
So all I'm doing here is I'm passing a
reference to the data into
the table model, which is acting as a sort
of wrapper for the data.
And now in my table panel, if I can pass
in a list of person
objects to my table panel, then I can say,
table model.
In fact I'm creating my table model here.
So, let's, actually let's change this
slightly.
Let's let's not have a constructor.
Let's say.
Let's give it a public set data method.
And that's gonna just look like this, so
let's add this in here.
So I, let's, let's see that I construct it
without actually passing in any data, if
that makes sense.
So I'll have this set data method and now,
if I've got this right, which
I think I have, in table panel I can say
tablemodel.setdata.
I pass in the list of people.
So there's a lot of passing around of data
here, and
then in a minute, I'm just gonna recap on
what we've done.
But first, let's just make this work.
So now another missing piece is, I need to
go into
the mainframe here and at some point, I'm
gonna have to get the data and pass it to
the table panel.
So the, the table panel now has a set data
method.
So, let's say after I've created a
controller, I call TablePanel.set
set what do I call that, setdata,
tablePanel setData.
And I can pass in controller.getpeople
like this.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And so let's follow the sooner.
So I've got a data model already, and my
data model is this
states base class which contains [UNKNOWN]
of people and if I add a
person, we've seen in previous tutorials
that by clicking okay on my
form, it's gonna call the out person
method at this database to, to do that.
And so in the main frame, if I click okay
on that
form, it's gonna get this form event, and
it's gonna add a person,
fire the controller and the controller's
got this Add Person method, which
turns the person event object into the
right form for the data model.
And adds it to the data model.
Now also, in the mainframe, I can use
the controller getpeople method, to, to
get my list of people.
And I can then add it to the table panel,
and set table panel to set data controller
[UNKNOWN] people in the table panel.
And then get the [INAUDIBLE] to people,
which I set in the table model, and in the
table model that just happily receives
that list of person objects.
So it seems complex, and of course if
you're, if you're
really implementing a real application, it
could get more complex than this.
And the, the point of this tutorial rather
is I just wanna show you table working.
And the bottom line is here.
You've gotta have, for your table, you've
gotta have a table model and that table
model is gonna have to be able to return
the the
number of columns, the number of rows and
the the values in each cell.
So, now I can actually do that.
Cuz now I've got actually a reference here
to the list of people.
I can then get con account.
Well, actually we'll talk about that in a
second but, and get row column that's
pretty easy.
'Cuz I can say return DB.size, cuz the,
the DB
here is just a list which has a size
method.
And the size is the number of person
objects in that
list and that's gonna be the number of
rows in my table.
Now to get get the value, at a particular,
this is actually a particular
row and column, the way that I need to do
that is so I get this,
this get value out will receive the, the
row and the column and have to
return the data that's supposed to be in
that row, and the column, and that column.
So to do that, I can just do a switch on,
well let's first of all get the person,
relevant person object.
And that's gonna be very simple, it's just
db.getrow, and I see the row number there.
sorry, not get row, but db.get.
Actually, and then, I can do a switch on
the column, and I can return
a field from the Person object, and, as
appropriate, depending upon the column.
So I can say, case, let's say case zero,
let's return person.get id.
And case one,
I'll return person.getname, and case two,
let's
return person.get occupation case three.
I can return person.
getage category, case four
returnperson.get.
Employment category, case five return
person.isUScitizen,
and case six, let's return person.tax.
GetTaxID, I'm, I think I saw [UNKNOWN]
that's
seven different cases here, from zero to
six.
So, we've got the seven columns, so for
the column count, let's return seven here.
And now, you know, after, you return null
down here if not if
those all matched, and I've got they
should be, if I got everything right.
So I've, I've said there're, if I say
there are seven columns,
then call here should never be more than
six, cuz it's starting zero.
So the last value should be six.
So this, this should never happen, this
return null.
Okay, so let's, let's run that, and at
the moment, I'm not actually gonna,
nothing's gonna appear
to happen, 'cuz if I click, if I
type [INAUDIBLE] information there and
click OK, nothing happens.
And if that, yeah, I've got a I'm not sure
if that's a big deal or not.
Let's just clear that.
But in my main frame, what I need to do.
So in the main frame I've I've got this
thing that responds to form clicked.
So when a form event occurs, it
says controller.addperson, and what I need
to do,
is I need to tell my table to refresh
every time something's added to the data.
So it then knows to recheck the data.
So I'm gonna add a, a method to table
panel, which I'm gonna call Refresh.
And it's not there yet, so I'm typing
tablePanel.refresh, and I've got to
implement that now.
So I'll say public void refresh, and what
this is gonna do, is it's just gonna
go to the table model and call one of
these fire methods,
which you've got different like fire
methods
for firing different events to tell the
table that's looking at the model, that
different aspects of the model have
changed, and
the one I'm gonna use here, is I'm just
gonna say file data table changed.
So let's run this now, and if I add my
name in here and click OK, we've
got a row added and the row is not exactly
beautiful, but it'll do for just a minute.
Occupation software [UNKNOWN] like that
again.
So, it's it's gonna keep adding the same,
basically the
same value, different i.d.'s here, and I
won't worry about that.
Now one last thing, for this tutorial,
isn't
gonna add a column header to this table
and
the way to do that is in my table panel,
usually tables should be in a scroll pane.
So where I add it to the table panel, I'll
say, I'll say new Jscroll pane.
Tables are really designed to be in scroll
panes, in jScroll
panes, and then I'm gonna go to the table
model here, and I'm gonna
right click here, and I'm gonna just go to
override implement
methods, so source, override implement
methods, and I wanna
override a method here, called
getcolumnsnames let's
take that, and click OK.
And this precedes the index of the column,
and returns the name of the column.
So, now, I can have like, I up here, and
this stuff, column names.
So let's say private, private string.
Column names.
And that could be a array of strings like
this.
Like this.
There we go.
And I'm gonna set that equal to a bunch of
appropriate column names.
So let's say equals and let's open a
[INAUDIBLE] parenthesis, close it there.
And in here, I can type ID name, let's see
what else we've got down here.
We've got occupation.
Occupation, age, category,
we got employment category.
Employment category.
US citizen and tax ID.
Tax, Tax ID.
Let's try that.
And then here, I'm gonna just return and
call names
and open up Array Reference bracket and
put in a colon
there and again, this, this is never got
off the
end here, 'cuz there're one, two, three,
four, five, six, seven.
There's seven column names and I've said
that there're seven columns.
So when it asks for the column name, it
shouldn't direct exceed six, cuz it's
starting from zero.
Now if I run that, we've got the column
names here.
Let's just expand that and if I add to
some data in there, John,
Software, Trainer, and click OK.
Then it hunts me in there, now that'll do
for the moment.
And, and in the next tutorial, and because
I want to build
up a little bit of data to work with,
we're gonna look at
how you can save this data despite
exporting it to a file, so
we're gonna implement, this stuff
basically,
that we have from the File menu.
We're gonna look at serialization that
allows you
to save objects like really easily with
minimal effort.
and, we're gonna basically make these menu
items
work, so that you can export and import
data.
And each one will connect to a database,
but that will do for the moment.
And once we've got that working, we can do
a bit more stuff with this table.
So that's it for this tutorial, I
appreciate that this was pretty complex.
But the essence of it isn't too
complicated, and it's basically just if
you got
a table, you need a table model, and my
table model extends Abstract Table model.
And then you just fill in all the columns
or the, sorry
methods that you need to implement, and
they're, they're pretty simple really.
You get [INAUDIBLE] and get value out is
the
one that gets the data for the row and
column.
And the only little complication really,
was that if you
actually update the data in your table,
you've gotta cause some
kind of fire event method on the table
model, to actually
tell the table that's looking at our model
to refresh itself.
Okay, I think that's quite enough for this
tutorial.
so, in the next tutorial as I said, we're
looking at serialization, which isn't
strictly speaking a part of swing, but
it's gonna be very useful for this
application.
So join me again then, and until next
time, happy coding.
[BLANK_AUDIO]