Hello, this is John from Cave of
Programming dot com.
And we're gonna take a kinda temporary
detour from looking at
swing in this tutorial just to look at the
serialization in Java.
And the reason I'm gonna do that is.
Just because, by building this,
application, which does quite a lot
already, but I want to have a way of
making these import and export data
items work so that I can store some test
data here that we can work with.
So that's why in this tutorial, I'm gonna
go over Saving objects to files
in Java and restoring them, even at that
small, strictly speaking, part of swing.
So, I'm going to start with the database
class
and which is part of my model here and I'm
gonna give this database
class, a couple of methods for, saving and
loading.
This array list of people.
So, I'll give it a method called save to,
to file.
Save to file will accept if I object if
it's in the argument.
That's the file that we actually want to
save to.
Let's have the import there, Java IO file,
and I'll make the import type void.
Now to actually do the saving, firstly
I'll create a file output
the stream, which I'll call FOS, and I'll
set that
equal to a new file, file output stream.
Which we're at the file.
And then, after I do the import, I'll have
an object output
stream OOS equals new object output
stream.
And this is going to route the final
output stream off.
We got this kind of, rushed and dull thing
going on.
That's the [UNKNOWN] you always seem to
have
and Java when it comes time things file.
And I'm going to use to object out of the
the
string to write my array list of people to
a file.
And after I've done that, I'll just call
OS dot close.
And I'm gonna throw from this method, IO
exception
because i want to handle it further up the
chain.
Now to actually write this array list of
people to this file,
there are various ways that I can do that.
And the way that I prefer, because it
avoids
warnings about, kind of, unchecked types,
and this sort of
thing, is to convert this arrays to people
to
an array list, and then write it to the
file.
So, I'm gonna say, person array, and I'll
just call that, I dunno, persons,
equals, and let's use people.
People dot two array.
And I'll use this version that returns a
array of the correct type.
So here I have to pass in a new, let's
copy that,
a new person array, of the correct length,
which is gonna be people
dot size, like this.
yeah, and if I've got this right, which I
have, that's gonna return a.
List of person, so you kinda create the
actual array there and
basically it's to array filter and then
returns a reference to it.
And then it's pretty simple to write that
to a file.
So all we have to do is say OS
dot Write Object, Write Object, and pass
in the arrayness.
Because an array sorry an array in Java
strange
though it may seem, is actually just an
object.
And if I, the advantage of, of doing it
like this is that if I've used the array
list.
Here, people, and an array list, although
it
has the template type person, suffers from
erasia,
which is when you, not the eighties center
band, but actually if I had actually
written this.
This array list to to the file then it's
type, would've been erased.
And then when I restored it, I
would events property getting a unchecked
conversion warning.
Which I, I don't mind, so I prefer to do
it this way.
Anyway that's, that's not too important.
That's my, my [INAUDIBLE] here and let's
run.
Rightly loads from file method.
So public void loads from File File, File,
here.
And that's also gonna throw IO Exception.
And this time I'm gonna use a File Input
Stream FIS equals new file input stream.
Now that's gonna route the file here, and
then I'm gonna have a, Oh.
Get Input Stream dot OIS equals new Object
Input Stream.
And that's gonna interrupt the File Input
Stream.
And after I've noted objects.
From that.
I'm gonna do the OIS dot close.
That side, the imports are Control Shift
O.
And now I wanna restore from this object,
the stream by
array of that [UNKNOWN] cuz you see an
actual array in Java.
Does not suffer from erasure.
It remembers what type it actually is.
So let's say
OIS dot read object and I'm just gonna
read the one object.
And it's gonna be a personary of persons.
So let's just copy that, like this,
inputs.
And then, I can cast that to type.
That's an array.
And if I save that.
It's got a little arrow here.
Oh yeah, I've gotta also handle this.
Class not found exception, so if I do
surround a try catch there, and I'll
just do that in a moment, and once I've
got my array, I, I wanna
then set this people array, I wanna fill
it with the items from the array, and why
I'm importing thing, just for this little
application, is that I don't wanna change.
The array list that this is pointing at.
So I don't want to create a new array
list.
Because then I don't think about how to
get that array list back.
Of the chain to my table model.
So I just want to rather create a new one.
I want to just add to this one, put items
into it.
So i'm going to say here equal.
Dot clear like this and then let's say
people dot
add all, and I want to add all the items
from this array but add all
doesn't take an array directly but there
is an arrays
dot, I think it's called, to list method.
Maybe it's called at, as, as list.
Let's see.
so, I'll have to pass in there the persons
array.
Let's add the important and in fact I
think it's called add list.
So what I've done is I've converted this,
persons array to
a list here and I've, added that list to
the array list.
List, of people, after clearing it.
So that's a little bit involved, but that
should basically take care of, saving, and
loading, the,
array of person objects, using
serialization in Java.
And if I wanted to save more data and load
more
data, of course I can, I could, then,
further go on.
To write more stuff after this.
And I could then load, more stuff after
this as well.
So you're not limited to just reading and
writing one object with serialization.
And, there's one important thing that I
must remember to
do otherwise I'll get an exception which
is that I must.
Make Person implement Serializable.
So if I go to public class person, I have
to say implements serializable.
Otherwise I'll get a I'll get an exception
being thrown.
When I try to serialize it, so.
So I'll add Java IO serializable and I
don't actually have
to add any new methods there, although
eclipse is gonna give
me a warning here about a generated serial
about a serial
version ID, I just, I'll just get it to
add that.
Just to shut it up.
Okay, I don't think we actually need that
there.
So let's save that, okay, the warning's
gone, so now I'm gonna just make the save.
To file a note from file methods work.
So firstly, I'll go to the controller,
which is here,
and because I've decided that in this
application, I want
more communication from the GUI package to
go through the
controller, I'm gonna just add rougher
methods in the controller here.
So public, Void save to file, and that
accepts file file,
and all it does is it calls the db dot
saved file method.
And of course I also have to add the
throws IO exception
that it's at import file, and at throws
declaration.
Okay, and Sent in again for load so public
void load From
file, file, file, let's type here throws
IO Exception.
And that's going to do db dot load.
From file, file.
There we go.
And now finally, the, the last bit in this
chain here, chain
of method calls is if I go up to the,
where are you?
If I go up to the GUI here, the view, part
of the MVC architecture, model view
controller, and I go to
main frame here, then if I look down here,
I've actually
got a I've got a input data item and
export data item.
Item, menu item, which at the moment
aren't doing anything.
So let's make those work, let's say
controller, for import dot load,
controller, spell it right, that will
help.
Controller dot load from file and that's
going
to make set file chooser dot get select.
File which will return the kind of file
object that that user has chosen to load.
Let's delete that and let's handle the
exception there and surround with try
couch and what I'll do is if it can't load
the file, I'll say J.
Option pain dot show message dialogue.
And then let's pass for the parents named
mainframe dot dis.
And actually don't want this.
Form of the constructor.
I want a more advanced one.
I have some more Humph.
This one I think.
So that's the message in here.
So load data from file or maybe let's say
failed.
Yeah, how about that.
Could, could not load the data from file.
How's that?
And that's the title error.
That'll do actually, error.
And finally, message type, J Option
Pane dot [INAUDIBLE] error, error message
there.
And I just do Control Shift F to format
that a bit.
Now the the save is gonna look pretty damn
similar.
So.
So let's copy that and put it in here.
And except for, it's going to be load it's
going be save
not save from but save to file and let's
say could not save data to file.
And, apart from that it's all going to be
pretty much the same.
I'll just show you what that error message
[INAUDIBLE]
looks like here, so let's run this and go
to file, export data, and I'll export to
test
doc there and so that's what the message
looks like.
Could not save data to file, so it's
rather nice.
But I'll get rid of that for the moment
and let's see if this thing.
It works, I don't think I've gotten
anything, although
it is easy to make mistakes with
serialization, I find.
So let's run this here, now I've got
something which
is, when I actually load the data so we I
do.
For all we, so,
let's go up with it here and when I do
load from file, I've got to remember
to call table panel dot refresh,
otherwise, the
table panel won't know that there's more
data there.
And refresh method if you recall, in table
panel
just basically, let's take a quick look at
it.
We've got this, thin gui I've got a person
where are we table panel, there
we go, and that's just doing it's got the
refresh method it's called table model.
fire table dates changed and that tells it
table to
query the model again and get the latest
data from it.
So let's run this and see how it, how it
looks.
I'm gonna add, I'll add myself in there,
John.
Let's just say software for occupation,
I am self employed and not a US citizen.
So let's click okay.
And let's add another.
Person in there, let's say Sue, and let's
make Sue a
manager, and let's say that she's employed
and she's a US citizen
with tax ID 1111, and she's female, let's
add her.
And actually I should really make it that
when
I click the okay button it clears the
form.
Could do very easily by saying the text on
these values next to
nothing, and resetting the selection, but
I'll leave that an exercise for you.
Let's go to file, export data, and I can
type the file name here.
I'll just use this test dot pair that I've
been using.
Click save, and now, if I go to.
To import data from test dot per,
hopefully there'll be no errors, and
just to prove that it works, let's quit
the application, run it again, and go to
file import data, test dot per and there
we are, we've got my data
back okay, so that's it for this tutorial,
as I say, not swing specific but.
But pretty damn useful so I thought it was
worth going over because it fits very much
into the
context of this application, and I wanted
to leave
you with an application that sort of, sort
of works.
And in the next tutorial, I'm gonna show
you
how to use pop up menus and we're gonna.
Create a pop up menu that let's you just
delete
a row from this table, cuz at the moment
if I
do import data and right click on the
table, nothing happens
and we're gonna fix that, with a little
pop up menu.
So join me again next time, and until next
time, happy coding.