Hello, this is John from
caveofprogramming.com and in
this tutorial we're gonna look at pop-up
menus.
So, if I run my application here, what I'm
gonna do
is, I've got I've got some data that I
saved earlier.
And I'm gonna add a pop-up menu to this
table
so I can right-click and delete rows from
this table.
Now actually, the first thing I'll do is,
let's just add a accelerator to
to the input, of action in the menu,
because it's gonna
otherwise, drive me a bit crazy
continually selecting that menu item.
So, I'm gonna go to import item, keystroke
get keystroke.
And I'm gonna set accelerator to I, with
the control mast.
So, Ctrl+I cuz it's now gonna import data.
So if I run this and do Ctrl+I, I can
select my file here.
And there we go.
So pop-up menus are pretty similar to
ordinary menus,
and let's have a look at the table panel
here.
I'm gonna give the table panel an instance
of private
and instead of JMenu, or MenuBar, it's
gonna be JPopupMenu.
And this is something called a Pop up.
And this is gonna be pretty similar to the
stuff we looked at in a tutorial on menus.
So in the constructorate table panel here,
I am gonna say
pop-up equals newjpopupmenu,
and I'm gonna give that just one menu
item.
I'll say JMenuItem and then I'll call this
removeItem equals new JMenuItem.
And let's say that I will say delete row,
cuz it's gonna a delete
a row from my table, and I'll add that to
the pop up menu.
So I'll say popup.add removeItem.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Now to to show this menu item, all I've
got to do is call popup.show basically.
But there are a few complications here
because I want this
pop up to pop up when I right click the
table.
So I'll go to the table, and
I'll say table top, at MouseListener, at
MouseListener.
And MouseListener, you can actually, use
like the, MouseListener interface, and
do for example, new MouseListener, or make
a panel here, implement MouseListener.
But MouseListener has a lot of different
methods in
temperament and we only really want the
mass clipped.
So instead, I'll use a class called
MouseAdapter.
And here I'll say, New Mouse Adapter.
And MouseAdapter is like a default
implementation of MouseListener,
except that you can just override the
methods that you just need,
rather than having to implement all of the
MouseListener methods.
So, if I right click here and go to
Source, Overwrite implement methods.
I can overwrite the mouse clicked pressed
events.
That should do the trick.
Mouse press and then here, let's delete
some of this slightly superfluous stuff.
I only want to bring up the menu, the
pop-up menu if someone clicks the right
mouse button.
So I'm gonna say if e.
getbutton equals mouseevent.button3.
Because the right button is button three,
even if you've only got
two buttons on your mouse, cuz there could
be a middle button.
And I'll say, popup.show, and now I want
to show my, you'll notice here there's
actually two
deprecated methods that we don't use
anymore, and
this is show, one that we do use here.
And the first argument to that, is a
reference to the
component that the pop up belongs to,
which is gonna be myTable.
And then, after that, we wanna pass on the
x and y half, we're
to actually show the menu, and that's
gonna be e.getx and so
that's, e is the Mouse event, and x is
gonna be the location.
Where I right click, and that's the e.get,
Y, getY, like this,
and now if I run this, and let's do
control I, that's the accelerator I
added, and import some data, and right
click, then I get this Delete Row
pop up menu, and of course you can add
sub-menus or whatever you like.
More, more data writing style menu, just
as you can with a normal menu.
Now, in the next tutorial, we're gonna
look at
selecting rows in this table, and we're
gonna make
it so that if you right-click on a row, it
gets selected and you can then delete it.
And join me again then.
And there's just one thing that I, I
wanna, very quickly
mention here, that I sort of omitted from
the last tutorial
on Serialization, which is that in case
you wonder, what Eclipse
often asks you if you wanna add this
serial version ID.
And you only really need that, on well you
don't really need it anywhere,
but it's good if you have it to, for
example, my password here is serializable.
And, so in the last tutorial we looked at
saving that to a file, and then restoring
it using Serialization, and this serial
version UID, what happen is, if you save
a class, an object to a file, and
then restore it using serialization, Java
will check
that the serial version UID matches, and
will
throw an exception if if it doesn't match.
And if you don't implement it here, and
you serialized an object, it
could be apparently theoretically on
different Java
platforms, on different platforms I should
say.
The generated serial version UID behind
the scenes, will match so
you could have an exception when you
restore your serialized object.
Because Java will think it's a different,
kind of, object, even if it isn't.
So basically, the long and short of it is
that,
if you've, if you're implementing
serializable, probably best get this a
serial version UID and it doesn't have to
be a huge
number, it could be like ten or a tab you
like.
But, that's not crucial.
I just thought I'd mention it.
Okay, so as I said in the last, in the
next tutorial we're gonna look at
selecting rows in tables.
So join me again then, and until next
time, happy coding.
[BLANK_AUDIO]