Hello this is John from
caveofprogramming.com, and this is a
tutorial on selecting rows in tables and
getting selected rows.
So it's actually possible to select
multiple rows in J
tables, but we're not gonna look at that
in this tutorial.
We're just, in this tutorial, we're just
gonna look at selecting one table row.
And the idea is so I've got this
application here.
And I can import data into it.
And I've got this pop-up menu which
appears if I right click on the table.
And when I right click the table, I want
to
select the table row that's directly
underneath the mouse here.
So to do that I, in the last tutorial, I
added a mouse listener to my table.
And when I click the right mouse button.
Actually, when I select the relevant table
row.
In fact we can make so that the table row
selected if the mouse is clicked at all.
And to do that I'm gonna use a method, a
table, that returns the row, that's at a
certain point.
So in mouse pressed.
Actually, in here i'm gonna say.
[UNKNOWN] row equals table.row.
At point.
And row point, gives me the table row
that's a particular point.
And to get the point where the mouse is
at, I'm
just gonna use the method of this mouse
and enter here
and say, E.getpoint, like that and now to
show that works,
I can just assist that out here [SOUND] on
my row.
And if I run this, Sync later.
And, right click, you can see down here in
the console pane, that I'm getting a
number that
represents the row of the the row
underneath where
I clicked the mouse which is exactly what
I want.
Now to select that row I need to use these
selection model at the table.
Because if I say table tops, I'll get
selection model, where are we, get
selection model.
That returns me a object that deals with
the selections on the table,
And I want to say getselectionmodel.select
dot add set selection.
So, set selection interval, that's one.
So with set selection interval, you can
select rows in
your table starting at this row, finishing
at this row
and I'm just gonna select one row here, so
I
just wanna start it, the row that's under
my mouse.
So I'm finishing that row as well.
So, if I run that now.
And import some data, then we select the
row under the mouse which is very nice.
Now, the next step here, is when I select
this menu item, delete row, I wanna get
the selected row from the table so that
I can delete it, and to do that, I'm gonna
first add an
action listener, to write to my remove
item in my pop up menu.
So I'll say remove item but add action
listener.
Listener and, and new action listener.
I'll use then anonymous class in here
again.
And put the brackets in the, and it's at
the import.
And if I click on this error, I can go to
at unimplementing methods.
Just maximize the editor here, and get rid
of some extra lines.
And now, I can say Int row equals
table.getselectionmodel again, get
selection model and if I actually I could
just use get a
selected row in this case which will be
some place, and then to check as you just.
Sys out here, row and, now, so I got rid
of the other sys out, so now if I run
this-
in fact, let's minimize the editor and
show the console-
so if I run this, do control I, import
some data then I right click and go
to delete row, and presto in the console
down there, you can see that it's output.
Putting the selected row with the table.
Now in the next tutorial we're gonna look
at
deleting rows from this table, so join me
again then.
And, and until next time happy coding.