Hello, this is John from
caveofprogramming.com, and in the last
tutorial we created I set up this kind of
pop-up menu here.
So I can, so that one to delete rows or
tables and then this
tutorial which is gonna implement our
functionality
and delete the row from the table.
Now the strategy that I'm gonna use here
is I'm gonna actually delete the row
from the from the data model and then I'm
gonna tell the table,
that the row has been deleted to make it
refresh itself.
And I'm also gonna instead of the table
panel
deleting stuff from the model itself, I'm
gonna make the table panel raise an event.
And the mainframe is actually gonna insert
that then,
and it's gonna tell the model to delete
the row.
So let's have a look at that.
One thing that I wanna change here
actually is in the
data model if we look at the database it
[UNKNOWN] the data.
When it does get people it actually
returns just the actual array list
of people and other objects that get
that reference could potentially modify
this list.
And I wanna actually prevent it from doing
that by saying collections,
collections.unmodifiablelist like this,
and and put that around there, and at the
import, and that will prevent
other classes from modifying the list file
the reference that they retrieve.
So I'm going to enforce that and as a
save, I'm gonna actually I'll allow
the table to remove roads, by telling the
main frame to remove them, she'll tell the
controller, which will tell the data, so
I'm
just enforcing a really clear flow of data
in my application, rather than having all
different
components do what they want with the
data.
And another thing I'm gonna change here
is I'm actually gonna be deleting person
objects
from this array objects, and I'm gonna
delete
person objects from anywhere in the array
list.
And although this could be a bit pedantic
really, cuz it's such a small application,
a small amount of data, I'm gonna change
this to a linked list because linked
lists, unlike array lists, are optimized
for
adding or removing items in the middle of
the list whereas an array list is only
optimized for adding and removing at the
end
of the list.
In fact, let's just change this to use the
list interface.
That's maybe more elegant.
Cuz we only need to actually have
LinkThatIsMentioned, where we
actually create the object that actually
implements the list interface.
Okay now, so the first thing is that I'm
gonna, in my table panel here.
We'll let's actually take a look let's
look at from kinda the top
end, as it were, because the main frame
here creates the table panel.
And I wanna be able to say in the main
frame something
like this, tablePaneladd let's call
it, I don't know, addPersonTableListener
add a new personTableListener.
[SOUND] And I want that to have some
method, such as a public void.
Row deleted, maybe.
Which will accept a row, like that.
And that will then tell the controller to
do something but
for the moment it can just do, just have
sysout row.
So I've not implemented any of this stuff
here.
None of that actually exists or works.
And I'm gonna implement that now.
And the first thing I'm gonna
do is I'm gonna create this
personTableListenerIInterface.
So, and you see this this, is exactly
like adding, a, action listener to a
button really.
In fact I'm gonna make this, set person
Table Listener because
that button actually maintains like a, a
list of listeners on
it, but here I'm gonna only allow the
Table Panel to
have one listener at a time, just cuz it's
easier to implement.
So this set person table listener method
doesn't of
course exist in tablePanel, I put that
implements it.
And we'll start with this interface, so
I'm gonna right click on the Gooey here
and go to New Interface, and call it
person Table Listener and Finish.
And, I want to ad, I want the interface,
to specify this method here.
Public void road deleted, so let's add
that to the interface like that.
And, now, I need to implement this, set,
person Table Listener method, in the Table
Panel.
So let's go to Table Panel, and let's
maximize that
and let's go down here and say I'll paste
that in.
And that's gonna be public void set person
Table Listener, and that accepts
a person table listener, which I'll call
Listener.
And what it's gonna do with it, is, it's
gonna have to say something like, this.,
set, actually, sorry, no.
thi.personTableListener equals Listener.
And now, I need to create this reference,
this private reference to the listener.
So this just stores a reference to the
listener.
Basically up here where I have, I'm gonna
have private, private,
PersonTableListener.
This is the interface that I've just
created here.
And it's gonna be a variable of that type.
And now what's gonna happen is that if
someone selects, someone right clicks on
the table and selects
Remove Item it's now gonna tell any
listening class about it.
So say if personTableListener is not equal
to null.
In other words if it's been set to
something, which I just did in my
main frame, then I am going to
say, PersonTableListener, and that's only
got one method.
It could PersonTableListener.
Just got this row deleted.
Row deleted and passed in a row there that
got, indeed, last tutorial.
So, and this is the third time we've been
to this kind
of list now, idea, I think now, or at
least the second time.
And, if I save my main frame now the error
will go away.
And it's just gonna print out the row for,
for the, for the moment.
So if I run that and let's import some
data.
And if I select Remove on one of these
rows,
you can see it's gonna get printed out
down here.
And the thing that's doing the printing is
this in the mainframe.
So the mainframe is now being informed,
when we select remove
row and the mainframe knows what row we
want to remove.
Now to actually remove the row, I wanna
say something like controller.removeperson
and parse in the index of the row to see
the index of the person in the array list.
So let's go to Controller and implement
that.
So in Controller, I've already got an
[UNKNOWN] person and I'm gonna add a
public void remove person int index let's
call it.
And that's gonna say to the db,
the database, something like
db.removeperson, at index.
And, if I go to the database class now,
so, in the model
database.java in here, I can say public,
public void,
removePerson int index, and all that has
to do is say people, that's the array list
up here, dot remove,
and pass any index there.
So, I just remove it from the array list.
Now, if I actually run this now, in put
some
data, and try to remove stuff, it doesn't
actually work.
And, the reason for that is I need to tell
the table, the table view that the table
model has changed.
And the way I'm gonna do that is, I could
actually call tablePanel.refresh here.
And that might not be an altogether bad
idea.
But I can possibly do it more efficiently
because the
tablePanel itself knows when someone's
selected to remove a row.
So right here, where I have the action is
still
on the menu, I could say table.fire, and
rather than
fire, actually not table but table
model.fire.
And rather than fire a method that just
says the data has changed as a whole, to
be more efficient I could fire table rows,
delete it, and pass in the actual rows
that hopefully will be deleted after doing
the deletion here.
So if I run that and fingers crossed, that
might actually work.
Delete row.
And I'm deleting rows from my table, like
that.
But of course, I'm not saving anything at
the moment.
So, let me get my rows back [UNKNOWN].
I do an import.
Okay, so, that's it for this tutorial and,
so we we see now how to import data into
tables and implement table models
and add and remove rows from tables, and
in the next tutorial we're gonna
look at the Jdialog class, so join me
again then.
Until next time, happy coding.
[SOUND]