Hello this is John from
caveofprogramming.com, and this
is a tutorial on dialogues in Java Swing.
So, I'm gonna take this application and
I'm
gonna add a preferences item to the window
menu.
And that's gonna bring up a dialogue that
allows me to set some preferences for my
application.
So I'm gonna start by creating a new class
in this GUI package here.
So say new class and we're going to call
that PrefsDialogue.
An, and that's going to extend JDialogue.
And I'll have the end quote there and, and
I'm gonna basically do the same
thing with this class that I've been doing
with panels and with my main frame.
I'm gonna give it a constructor, public
prefs, prefs dialog,
and, and in the constructor I'm gonna add
some widgets to this and to this dialog.
So for the moment, back in main frame
here.
I'm gonna give mainframe a instance
variable of the off type, prefs dialogue.
And i'll call that pref's dialogue.
And down here lets that equal to mu and
set
press dialogue equal to mu prefs dialog
capital P there.
Now to to show this dialog all I need to
do is call set visible true.
Actually, before I do that let's let's
change a few things here because one thing
I wanna call the
super constructor, and I'm gonna use
a version of the constructor that takes
three parameters.
It takes the a reference to the owner of
the dialog, the parent window
and the title and a true or false that
says whether it's modal or not.
Modal dialogs are ones that don't allow
you do anything else while their actually
open.
Which is usually the case of the J option
pane dialogs and non modal dialogs.
Allow you to carry on working, while
they're open, so let's
here, I'm gonna make this take a reference
to a J frame,
let's say frame, and let's just pass that
in the, it's called
a, maybe I'll that parent, because it's
actually the parent of this dialogue.
The window that the dialogue is kinda
attached to, if you like.
Let's have a title here.
So I'll make the title preferences,
preferences and let's say false for
modal, and later I'm gonna change that to
true just so you can see the difference.
[SOUND] Now in main frame here, I'm
passing this, so let's see parent here.
Let's snap the input here for jframe, and
I'll also get this dialog size.
I'll say setSize and let's just make that,
I don't know, 400 and by 300 let's say.
Just so we can see it.
And, and that's enough of that.
And I'm not gonna call setPhysical here
because
setPhysical is gonna be called by my
mainframe.
Okay, so now I've got the preferences
dialog setup and
ready to use, so it's got no controls in
it.
And I'm gonna go down to the window menu
now.
The window menu at the moment just has a
sub menu called Show.
I'm gonna add a new jmenu item call preps
item, set that equal to new jMenuItem.
And that's gonna say preferences, and by
convention if
you have a, menu item that brings up a
dialogue.
[UNKNOWN] an ellipses, like this, after
the text.
[UNKNOWN] and so let's add that here, so
windowmenu.add
prefsitem, and let's add an action list
next to the prefsitem.
So prefsitem.listItem.add actionListener,
new actionListener, and you
know the drill for this by now.
And let's add the unimplemented method
there, the actionPerform method.
And put semicolon in, and here, all I'm
gonna do is say prefs
prefs dialogue dot set visible true, like
that.
And that's gonna show my dialogue, and to
hide the dialogue again, I'm gonna call
false,
but that's gonna happen, that invisible
false is
gonna happen within my dialogue itself, so
that's.
Just take a look at this and now if I
go to window preferences, and it brings up
my preferences dialog.
Now in the next tutorial, we're gonna look
at adding some controls to this dialog,
and we're gonna look at a, adding a j
spinner control.
Among other things.
So join me again then.
And until next time, happy coding.
[SOUND]