Hello, this is John from
caveofprogramming.com.
Welcome back again, and in this tutorial,
we're gonna look at Spinner Controls.
And Spinner Controls are little
specialized
controls for entering numbers in Java.
So I've got my application set up at the
moment to produce
this blank dialogue, and I'm gonna add
some controls to this dialogue.
And in this particular tutorial, I'm just
gonna write
the minimum controls that we need to
demonstrate with JSpinner.
So, here in my dialog class, I'm gonna
start by creating a, I'm gonna add a
JButton okbutton = new JButton.
actually, let's I've, I'll actually create
a new the new
objects and shape of an object down here
in constructor.
Although I could equally create it here
when
I declare a variable that would still be
okay.
And, and let's have a private J button,
cancel button.
And I'm going to add a J spinner here.
So, J spinner, and I'm going to call it
port
spinner, because this dialog is actually
gonna store database connection details.
And in a future tutorial we will look, we
will have kind of a whistle-stop
tour of JDBC and we'll look at connecting
this application to a database.
And there's another thing that I need
here.
I also need a private spinnerNumberModel
and this is the data model behind the
spinner.
And that will allow me to set minimum
maximum values to my spinner and also the
increment.
When you click the little up down button
at the side of the spinner.
So let's go ahead and create these
controls but actually
there's one thing that I want to quickly
fix before I
do that because at the moment, even though
I specify the
parent from my dialog, for reasons that I
don't fully understand.
It still, still appears in the corner of
the window there.
So I'm just gonna quickly here, say, set
location relative to.
And I'm just gonna pass in, the parent the
J frame parent.
Because, otherwise that's gonna drive me
crazy.
So now if I do window preferences it comes
up in a nice location.
Okay, that's much better.
now, yeah, I don't know what that was
about.
Okay, so, let's now create these controls.
So I'll say okButton = new JButton("OK").
And we'll have cancelButton = new
JButton("Cancel").
So you should always have okay and cancel
buttons on your dialogue or
at least you stores allow the user
to cancel the dialogue without changing
anything.
And I'll say spinnerModel,
equals new J, equals new Spinning of the
model.
Actually that doesn't really have to be a,
private instanced
variable, because that isn't gonna need it
again, but that's okay.
And now, to the constructor's spinning
number model, firstly, just to control
space there, I'm going to use this
constructor, he's gonna store integers.
And firstly I'll pass it the value that I
want to set when it, when the spinner
appears.
And as far as I can remember, the MySQL
server runs
by default on port 3306, or set up for the
default.
And let's set the minimum at 0, and the
maximum at
12349, so 9999 and the step size is gonna
be one.
And then when I create my j spinner I can
say quote spinner
equals new j spinner and I can pass in the
spinner model in constructor
and now I can set the layout and add these
controls so I can say set layout set
layouts.
If I can get the right keys set layout,
new grid bag.
It's our old friend here grid bag layout.
And I'm gonna also create a
GridBagConstraints.
So GridBagConstraints
gc equals new GridBagConstraints.
And I'm gonna add controls here in rows.
So, the first row will be GC.gridy
equals zero and then set GC.gridx equals
zero and then I'll also set up some
defaults here.
I'll say GC.weightx for the moment, I'll
set equal to one, GC.weighty equals one.
And if you don't set this stuff at the
start then you can run into some problems
later on.
And gc.fill, I can set it equal to
horizontal, vertical, both,
or none, and I'm going to set it equal to
grid
back constraints.none, because I want my
controls
to be their preferred size, rather than to
be, rather than to fill the whole cell.
so, now, let's go ahead and say let's add.
I'll add a new j label for start and I'll
set, I'll set that equal to, I'll set the
text on it to port colon, space, comma
GC and then, next to that on the right, I
will say
pc.gridx equals let's just do plus plus
actually.
And then I'll say add, and I'll add my
spinner here, support spinner comma gc.
So that's one rows, sort it out.
And then let's go to the next row.
So let's have a, comment here.
Next row, and I'll do gc.grid y plus
plus and go back to gc.grid x, equals
zero.
Here I'm gonna up my, cancel button.
If you bring up the dialogue for example,
let's see, custom inspected, you
can see the cancel button's usually on
the, right so it stays here.
So let's add the okay button here.
So I'll say add okay button comma gc and
then gc.gridx plus plus and add
cancel button comma gc.
Now with a bit of luck, or lots of luck
this will appear reasonably presentable.
So there we are.
We need to address the spacing issues
here.
But we've got a spinner.
And you can see, it's even got a comma in
it, so it's nicely formatted there.
And I can increase or decrease the spinner
like this.
And it's got a minimum and maximum value.
I can type in one there, but it won't go
below
zero no matter what I do and the maximum
is 9999.
So let's try, let's try that.
I can't increase beyond that and so there
we go.
and, if I try typing in, I can type in
greater values, but
and if I do that, I just, it won't let me
change it anymore.
It's gone funny.
So, anyway, let's now get the value from
that
spinner [UNKNOWN] so, I wanna add an
action list now, to the OK button.
OK button to add action list, I mean
there's a, you know
the routine now, by now with this so add
action, action
listener, and so I'll say, you know, say
new action listener
and then open the [UNKNOWN] brackets here
at the unimplemented methods.
You can port action this in the first, add
an implementing method, and let's maximize
the editor, get rid of some space that I
don't want, add the
semicolon in here, and now at this point,
I can get the value from
the spinner control, and it's just a
little complication here because the
spinner actually returns.
If I say, if I say at this point, spinner
what do I call that actually, I called it
port spinner.
So port spinner.get, there's a get value
if you look
at it actually returns a object, but now I
know
that I'm storing integers in this spinner,
so I can
cuss this to a integer, cuz it's gotta be
a integer.
And I can say integer value
equals, and then cuss the return type of
ports.getValue to that value.
And finish off this tutorial, I'm just
gonna output the value here in the
console.
So if I run this and get to preferences
dialogue, and
maybe change that a little bit, and click
okay, I'm gonna get the value 3301.
Yeah.
And actually, one, thing that I could also
do is,
I can also make the dialogue go away when
you click "OK" or "Cancel" so I can
say set, setVisible here, false.
And I can also add a, if I just copy
that and add a listener to the cancel
button, the only
difference between the cancel button and
the OK button is
that the OK button, gets values and does
stuff with them.
Before setting visible defaults, and,
apart from that, the seminar.
So now hopefully, if I go into preferences
here
[NOISE] console will just get rid of my
dialogue.
And okay will get rid of my dialogue.
But first it will retrieve the value from
that spinner.
So, let's just see that one more time.
So set 3311, click okay, and we get 3311
down there in the console.
Okay, so that's it for this tutorial.
In the next tutorial we're gonna look at
password controls because
we're gonna store a user name and password
in this dialogue.
And we're gonna create one of those
password
controls that, where you just see, like
asterisks
in stead of she's seeing what you're
typing,
to hide what you're typing from other
people.
Okay, so join me again then, and until
then, happy coding.