Hello, this is John from
caveofprogramming.com.
And this is a tutorial on password fields
in Java Swing.
So I'm gonna add a password field and a
username to my dialog here.
Because this is gonna be the connection
details
for a database connection to a MySQL
database.
So, I'm gonna here's the preference dialog
class I created in a previous tutorial.
And, password fields work pretty much like
j, text
fields except that they don't show what
you're typing.
So here let's create a, I'm going
jTextField for the user name.
I'll call it userField.
And I'm going to create a jPasswordField,
passField for the password.
And set the input.
And down here I can say userField equals
new jTextField.
And let's give that a length of ten.
And I say passField equals new
jPasswordField.
And I'll give that a length of ten as
well.
And now, let's add these to the grid back
layout.
So I'll start with gridy equal to 0 here,
and I'm gonna add them right at the top
here.
So the stuff that I want to add looks
pretty much like this.
So let's have a comment here.
So this is gonna be first row.
And then after that I'll just say, next
row, next row.
So I'm gonna paste some stuff in here, and
for the
next row, I'm gonna need to increment
gc.grid y, plus plus.
And this is all stuff that we did, in in
designing
the the form panel that goes on the left
in this application.
And I'm gonna change this to user, and
I'll change this to
userField, and, let's take a look and see
if that looks okay.
And it does, apart from being, a mess at
the moment.
And I'm gonna add the same thing again.
So let's delete some of this.
And, I'll copy this and under the
userField I'm going to add in the
password.
So, I'll say passField and make this say
And, I'll try looking [INAUDIBLE] and that
looks like a user password port.
So it's a bit of a mess at the moment, but
we're gonna fix that, in the future.
And we're just gonna spend one tutorial on
making this look a bit nicer.
But, for the moment, so, userField, of
course it's just
a text field so I can type my name in
there.
And, in here, when you type stuff it
doesn't actually show what you're typing.
And you can, you can actually configure
what character
it shows if you want to, when you type
stuff.
By saying, take a password field and call
these setEchoChar method.
And pass in, pass in a character there to
that and is
the one that will be displayed instead of
the text that you're typing.
So let's have a look at that.
And if I run that.
So we can see now we've got asterisks
instead of sorta circles.
When you want a text from a pass, password
field.
So down here the action is from my OK
button, and I'm,
I'm getting the value from the port
spinner control at the moment.
And of course to get the text from
the user field, I'd say equals
userField.get text.
To get the password from the password
field, I need to say
passField.getPass, at least I thought it
was getPass.
Let's take a look.
password.
Let's take a look at the API document
here.
It's [INAUDIBLE].
Yeah, get password so I don't know what
the problem was there.
Autocomplete running out on me, there we
go.
And that actually returns and array of
chars.
So if I unfortunately I have this little
problem if the
right square bracket is set to a some
sorta shortcut in Eclipse.
So I can't type that very easily, but
let's try typing one left square bracket.
And with a bit of luck Eclipse will to
complete, so except
this, so this is an array of chars instead
of a string.
And I'm gonna set that equal to the
password field and get password.
So there we go, we got there in the end,
and if
I output that just to show you, in fact,
let's output the user.
And then, the password and so there we go.
Actually I'm not sure if I can yeah, well
let's try this and see how it looks.
If I run this and then go to Window >
Preferences and type user John and
password and click OK.
You get and this is a representation
unfortunately of the array of characters
and you've got like an array bracket there
to show that, that it's an array.
And this tells you it's an array of
characters I believe and that's the hash
code.
So that's no use, but what I can do is, I
can wrap this into, a string let's say.
So, new stringPassword.
And then, if I run that, let's
go, and then, I'll type some stuff in here
and click OK.
Now, I've got the password out of this
text.
So just by wrapping the array of chars in
a string, you can then output it.
So that's it for this tutorial.
And in the next tutorial, we're going to
look at making this dialog,
this dialog that we've been working on,
save a default value so that.
When you type stuff and quit the
application and then start
it again, it will remember the values that
you entered last time.
Cuz you want it to store these connection
values between, between runs.
And to do that we're gonna use,
properties, which are great for
storing all kinds of things about your
application that you want to persist.
Such as you know the window size and the
location, and that kinda thing.
OK, so that's for next time, and until
then, happy coding.
[BLANK_AUDIO]