Hello, this is John from
caveofprogramming.com, and in this
tutorial, we gonna look at saving data
with your application using preferences.
actually, at, at the end of the last
tutorial, I said properties.
And properties were kind of the old way of
doing this in Java.
And the new way, the preferred way is to
use preferences.
Now preferences aren't suitable for
storing large amounts of
data, like for example, the stuff in our
database here.
But they are suitable for storing things
like the
little bits of data that you'd have in
this.
Dialogue or, for example the size and
location
of a window and that kind of thing.
Now before I can save preferences in this
dialogue, I'm gonna add a
event that will allow me to get the
information from the dialogue.
Back to my main frame.
And in the main frame I'm actually gonna
save the preferences.
So let's go to the let's go to the prefs
dialogue here.
And I'm gonna have a, some kind of
thing that can listen to that, and get
information.
From it.
Let's say let's create a new interface
here.
And I'll call it prefs listener.
And, I'll give prefs listener one method,
public void.
prefs, let's call it preferences set.
And that's gonna accept a
string user, string password.
And, a int, fault, number.
So now, in my main frame, I
can say well, what, with a bit more work,
I'll be able to say
prefs dialog.set.
Prefs listener and in
here, I will be able to say new prefs
listener and
just create an anonymous class using that
interface that I just defined by this.
So I can add the I need to create this,
method.
Set prefs listener my pref [UNKNOWN]
dialogue [UNKNOWN] for me.
There we go.
and, I need to add the anonymous method
here in,
it's very deep and that's the method here
in the mainframe.
So this is just stuff that I've done.
Several times before already in this
tutorial.
Just adding listeners and using them to
pass information to the main frame here.
And in my prefs dialogue here, so I'm
gonna save that, and I'm gonna have a
let's have a instant variable private
prefs listener.
So at the type of the interface I've just
defined prefs listener I'll call it.
And in the set method down here, I will
say,
so this this dot prefs listener, equals
prefs listener.
And now finally, the last step before I
actually deal with the properties
is that, when the OK button is clicked
here, I can
say, if prefs listener, is not equal
to null, in other words, has been set to
something, so there is actually
something listening I can say
prefslistener
dot, and call this preferences set.
And now I can parse in the user.
The password, which I'm gonna wrap in a
string.
So I'll say new string, password.
Because remember, password is an array of
chars, primitive chars.
And the port number let's call this port.
And, I can pass that in there.
Okay, so now, when I click OK in my dialog
it's gonna receive.
This preferences set thing and I'm gonna
get this user and password
import if, if any values have been typed
for them of course.
So let's just output here the user, and
the password and check that this works.
So if I run this now, and go to the
preferences dialog, and type something
for user and something for password and
click Okay, it comes out in my main frame.
It's coming out twice, because I've also
get [UNKNOWN]
out here in my prefs dialog so I remove
that.
And now the bit that you've been waiting
for, which is I'm gonna store def, the
kind of values that are typed into this
dialog between runs of this application.
So, first I'm gonna give this a public
void set defaults method and the
set defaults is gonna have String, String
user
and it's gonna have String password and
int port and what it's gonna do with
those.
Is, it's gonna say user field, dot set
text user,
and pass field dot set text, and
pass, so password actually.
So even though their password field
returns.
It let's you set it, set the password with
text.
And the port spinner here dot set five
and that's we're gonna pass in the portva
and you'll notice port is a.
Primitive integer.
But and set that to an actual object but
what would happen is, or I think it does.
What would happen is that Java will auto
box out
with an integer type and it will pass the
problem.
So, in my mainframe I can now set.
Defaults, if there are any defaults to be
set.
And to do that in my mainframe here.
I'm gonna give it a, private
object to type preferences.
Preferences.
Which I call prefs.
And down here, I'm gonna set prefs,
equal to Preferences dot user Root.
And I need to create a Preferences node,
which is,
is basically just a kind of key that you
use to store your preferences objects.
I'll say node.
And often people use they say,
getClass.getName in there, so their, the
name,
it would be the name of the class, the
main frame in this case.
But here I think I'm just gonna do I'm
just gonna call it DB.
So it does, it doesn't really matter too
much what.
To what you're typing there.
Just It should probably be some kind of
string with no spaces.
Okay, and now that I've got my preferences
object, when the user
sets preferences here, I can say, prefs
dot part, and I can put.
Things with keys and values.
I'll say user and we'll call it well, well
add in there the user
name and prefs.put and let's add in,
password and source the password in there
and.
The port, let's say perhaps stop put,
port, and port.
So I'm just saving the values in a moment
later on, I'm gonna
actually I'm gonna actually do stuff with
them like set database can.
Details, actually, port this a prim, port
in a primitive integer, I'm gonna have to
wrap it, with a, non primitive integer,
port, and do to string on it.
So I'll actually be able to set it.
And now
I can, when, I run my main frame.
I can actually set set default values for
this dialog.
So, I can say here in the constructor main
frame still, press dialog.setdefaults.
Set defaults, there we go.
And that's the method that I added that
lets
me just set the values, in my preferences
dialog.
Which okay, it's invisible, but it's still
there in
the background, so we can set defaults on
it.
And I can say yes.
So string user equals, and prefs dot get,
and
I just need to say user, just need to use
the same keys.
And I'll supply default, which would've
just been nothing here.
And since it's the default value, for if
there is no values
stored in your preferences there and
string password
equals prefs.get password and
I'll make the default again and then an
empty string and integer
port equals prefs.get well
actually at this point I'm probably gonna
have
to do a little bit more work so integers.
To sort of get suppressed will get caught.
And let's make the default three three,
zero six.
Which is the default MySQL port.
Now, for the port, press dot get, is gonna
return a string.
But actually what I could do here.
Which would be simp, simpler, actually,
now [LAUGH] that I
think of it, is, I could use prefs put in
there.
Instead of converting this to a string.
I can just, put [INAUDIBLE] directly.
And then I can use here, the get in method
and the default can be three three zero
six there.
That's a much better idea.
Okay, so press has this put for strings.
And there's also.
Put in four integers and get into four
integers and I think that will do the
trick.
So, let's, let's test this and see if it
works.
If I run that and, and go to preferences
here.
Let's type user.
John password hello.
And let's set the port here to three three
zero seven, click OK.
And now of course it's still gonna
have those values while the application's
running
because the dialog doesn't actually, it's
not
actually destroyed just cuz if I click OK.
But if I clear the application, and run it
again, with a
bit of luck, it will load, my default
preferences and there we go.
So using preferences it's pretty simple.
And it's a lot like putting keys to a map.
If you've just got put and get and it
stores it somewhere in your operating
system and the actual.
Plus a file and the location of the file,
is gonna depend on your operating system.
It doesn't really matter, but the bottom
line is
that you can create these nodes and store
sets of
preferences, onto these nodes between runs
of your application which
is suitable for little bits of data like
this stuff.
Okay, so that's it for this tutorial.
And in the next tutorial we're just gonna
look at.
Making your dialogues, a little bit
prettier using panels because, this
dialogue looks like a whole [UNKNOWN] and
what I want to do, is I wanna align the
bottom [UNKNOWN] to the right and have
like a nice panel with a border
that sort of thing, so we gonna look at
that in the next tutorial.
So join me again then, and until next
time, happy coding.
[SOUND]