Hello, this is John from
caveofprogramming.com,
and this is a tutorial on
basically make, making dialogs look
prettier and this also applies to forms.
So, we've got this preferences dialog at
the moment i'm gonna top this up a bit.
By, using a couple of panels, within this,
dialogue and giving, giving one of them, a
border.
And we're also gonna, we're also gonna use
like, two, or
three different layouts within the same,
dialogue to make it look good.
So if you're using a visual designer like
NetBeans
or even better, the free Windows, free
Eclipse plugin Window
Builder Pro, and you, you might want to
skip this tutorial.
But actually it will give you some
information, because even if you're using
these, facial
designers, you can still, make use of the
techniques in this tutorial, to design
your dialogues.
So the first thing I'm gonna do is assign
an accelerator to this dialogue because as
a general principle.
it's, it's not good to try to develop
an application where you have to run the
application,
and then perform some other slightly
laborious action, just
to see the results of what you're working
on.
So, I wanna fix it, so that when the
application
runs, all I have to do is press Ctrl P to
bring up this preferences dialogue and
that will save me some
time, 'cuz I won't have to keep going to
the menu.
So let's go to the, [UNKNOWN] package
here,
and go to the, Mainframe which is here.
And search for the accelerators codes I've
already
added a couple of accelerators to menu
items.
And I'm just gonna copy these and I'll
change this to preferences, I preface item
that one.
And I'm gonna set the key to be P here, so
if I run this now.
And do Ctrl P, that brings up my dialog,
just to speed things up a bit.
So let's go the dialog and work on that,
I'll go to the preferences dialog here,
maximize my [INAUDIBLE].
And it's here, maximize the wrong window,
here we go, Ctrl-M
and now I wanna create a couple of panels
which
I'm gonna use, we're gonna have one panel
that's gonna control my, it's gonna
contain my, labels text password field and
spinner.
And the other part is gonna contain my
buttons so the first thing I'm gonna do
actually, is, take all this kind of layout
specific code and so.
Down to here, and I'm going to do Ctr-lX
to cut it,
and I'm gonna replace all that with a
function which I'll call,
lay out controls, I think that will do the
trick.
And, I'll implement that function down
here so, I'll have, put private void
lay out controls, and, let's just paste
the original letters.
[INAUDIBLE] code in there.
So that should work exactly the same as
before, and it does.
Now, in layout controls here, I'm gonna
just do Ctrl-Shift F to format that.
I'm gonna start by creating a couple of
panels, so I'll have a J panel
controls panel equals new J Panel, and
I'll have a J paneled buttons panel equals
new J panel.
Now, so that I can better keep track of,
which panels
were, I'm gonna start by setting very
simple borders on each one.
So I'll say, controlspanel.setborder set
border there.
And let's just use border factory.create,
oh yeah, I've got
to have the right spelling for start that
will help Ctrl-shift-O to add the import.
And then the auto complete, let's have
create
line border, and I'll give that color of
black.
Color, at the input for color, and then we
can do, color.black, just
so that we can see what's going on, and
I'll copy that line.
And, okay page
down or up by mistake there escape that
copy that line and then, paste
that in then, I can use, I can set a
border on my buttons panel as well.
Now I'm gonna be adding these panels to
the dialog as a whole,
and the first thing I'm gonna do here is
instead of setting grid by layout on the
actual panel, I'm gonna set it on the
controls panel and I'm gonna add stuff
to my controls panel instead of adding it
to this main direct to the dialog.
So I'll do, set that on the controls panel
and then I'm gonna look down here, and
I've got
six different controls that I want to add
to the
controls panel instead of adding them to
the main panel.
And they are the three labels, and three
import
controls so got the user field and its
label.
And you've got the password and it's
And we've also got the port, spinner and
its label.
And for the buttons panel here, the
buttons panel, and,
so let's go down to where you are at the
buttons now, so that's right at
the bottom here, and let's delete, let's
change this comment here
to buttons Panel, and on the buttons
panel, I'm gonna set the layout, and I'm
gonna set that to new
flow layout.
cuz I want my buttons to be next to each
other actually I want them to align, to
the right
hand side with in my panel.so I'm gonna
say here,
in a constructor of flow layout, I'm gonna
pass flow layout.right.
To say that I want my buttons right
aligned, and then I can add
the buttons to the button panels, let's
get rid of actually first I'll paste in
the add, and then I'm not gonna use the GC
anymore because the flow out, flow layout
uses that controls and there's no extra
perimeter to add character this.
And now the final thing that I mustn't
forget, of course, is, add sub tunnels to
dialogue.
And on the dialogue itself, I'm actually
just gonna use a nice
and simple, border layout, which we've
seen before, cuz we used it there
in the main frame, so I'm gonna say new
border layout, and, I'm gonna add the,
these [INAUDIBLE] in now, so I'm gonna say
add, [INAUDIBLE]
controls panel, and I'm gonna add order
layouts.center.
And then I'm gonna add the buttons panel
add border, border layout.south,
there we go, and let's take a look and see
how How that looks.
So,Ctrl P and, there we go.
So, it's pretty much the same as before
but now I've got two panels.
This Is panel at the top, which is my
controls panel
and a panel at the bottom, which, which
is, bottom, which
is my buttons panel um,and see that I've
got the [INAUDIBLE]
console buttons there, now and they're
right aligned using their flow layout.
One thing that I might wanna do is, make
the buttons the same size, which could
look nicer.
So, let's, let's just do that It'll be a
nice little touch there I'm gonna say,
So, we'll go to, up here, before the
button's routed although I don't suppose
it matters.
And then let's say, dimensions
button size let,s It call it btnSize
equals
and I'll do CancelButton, cuz
that's the bigger button.get let's try get
size, and see if that works.
And then I can do on my okay
button, okay button, actually that's not
dimension, it's for dimension and,
Ctrl-shift-0, okay
button.set, preferred size, and
btnSize in there I'm not sure if this will
work, let's just check.
So, in fact my okay button has completely
disappeared, let's try and get preferred
size I think that's probably right and
then click Run and Ctrl-P there we go.
Now we've got the okay button this is same
size, as cancel button.
And, and the reas the reason for that, I
guess is that,
the cancel button after you assign text to
it, which happened when I corrected the
button, had
a preferred size, I wasn't sure if it was
preferred size or, the actual size of it.
And that's the size that it wants to be
and I [UNKNOWN] and then I've just done
set, I've set [INAUDIBLE] size on the okay
bond
to make out the same preferred size, and
it's
actually the flow layout manager that
actually determines the
size of the button but that's obviously
doing get
preferred size to find out what size they
wanna
be it's making buttons that size which is
nice.
So, now let's work there on these controls
here, so the first thing I wanna do is
write a line, these labels so that they're
closer to the form controls that
they represent, and to do that, it's it's
the same as we've seen before, when we
were laying out the person form, that's on
the left hand side of the application
here.
I'm just gonna go to it's gonna to be a
repeat of what we've seen before, so
we're just gonna to the when, where I'm
adding stuff I just label
here, adding stuff using grid background,
using grid by constraints.
That's said GC.anchor, to anchor it to the
to the right-hand side, so that gonna be
grid
back constraints.um.um, the east right?
So let's just check so, everything for the
moment, is gonna be anchored to
the east because I haven't reset it with
the controls so there we go.
And I'm gonna take this and just before we
add the
other two labels I'm gonna set it to that
so here's
one label and the other label is, here.
And just before I add the controls, i'm
gonna,
say that I want to find anchor to west.
So, there's one, and, here's another and
the other control is up here.
So, let's see and do Ctrl-P, and there we
go, so now we've got them aligned.
And actually, before I move on, there's
one
thing I just wanna quickly tell you about
GridBagLayout because I don't know if I'll
get
another chance within this application,
because completed it.
But if you want something to span, like,
two or more,
grid cells either vertically or
horizontally, you can set GC.grid width,
or grid height and the number of cells you
wanna span,
and then you can have control of spans of
multiple cells.
which is Something very handy, but i'm
probably not gonna
use that, in this application I just
wanted to mention it.
And I think the other, or, the kind of
other main aspects,
grip that constraint, constraints, and
grip
back [UNKNOWN] we've pretty much covered.
So, now i'm also gonna add, before I add
the label, I wanna add some space
on the right hand edge of the label there
because they look a bit strange
and being you know, completely next to the
controls.
So to do that, I'm gonna say GC.inserts,
and again
this is something that we seen before,
equals new insets.
And I want, I think, if I do Ctrl-Shift-O,
and look at this, it's top left bottom
right.
So I want the right to be padded a bit, so
I'm gonna say,
top left, bottom and let's make the right
padded by, I don't know, 15 pixels.
And let's just see how that looks, that's
gonna affect
all the controls, at the moment
[INAUDIBLE], there we go.
That's not too bad at all actually, and I
could reuse this,
inset actually in fact I will lets just
cut that and say, right, padding
and up here, I can say, inset, right,
padding.
And then equals new insets, and so that's
my right padding.
And I also want, no padding 'cuz I want, I
don't want the, input
controls to be padded at all so i,m say
insets, no padding, equals new
insets and that's just gonna be [UNKNOWN],
no padding.
And, so, I'm gonna set the insets to right
padding
before I add the labels, and it says one
and this is the one down here new label.
And I'm gonna set it equal to no padding
before I add the control, the actual
fields so this is gonna be no padding, no
padding, and let's
copy that, and look for the places where I
add fields, so, these fields [INAUDIBLE]
pulled spinner, and now if I run that, it,
it looks a lot better.
Now, there's a lot of space between these
two controls, and when I
design a form, the technique that I showed
you is I made
everything, I made the bottom cell much
bigger than the other cells.
And then I made these controls uh,kind of
line up with the top of the cell.
And this as well, and then we had, so we
had space
at the bottom, and they're all kind of
bunched at the top.
So, I mean the bottom cell's the biggest
by far and then made everything bunch up
at the top, that's the [INAUDIBLE] that's
the
technique I used in designing this form
here.
But I'm gonna do something slightly
different here
in this, you know more than one way to
skin an egg, or I should say, you know, I
don't know, you know what I mean.
So, what I'm gonna do here is, I'm gonna
first of all
reduce the size of the dialogue
considerably, so let's go to where I
do set size on the dialogue here and I'm
gonna Make that like
to, I don't know, let's try 200 and 200,
that's probably too small.
And add those, that's too small, and let's
make
the width wider let's try 300 there and
run that.
And that looks quite a lot better and what
I'm also gonna do, is, let's make it,
make it a bit narrower let's try 270, see
how that looks.
And maybe, for the height, let's try 180,
and see how that looks.
So, you can play around with this kind of
thing, I'm quite happy with that.
And, actually, I'm gonna also, I'm gonna
add, a border around the top form here,
and, and I'm gonna make it so that, I
want, I want it so that there's a border
around form itself, but then a space
around
that border, and so actually this is
probably
gonna have to be a bit bigger, so let's
set it for the moment to like 340.
so let,s basically, make this much bigger
for
the moment so, it's gonna look like that.
Now let's put a border around that, around
the top form.
So I've already got a line border, which
is no use
to me, I'm gonna get rid of that in a
minute.
But I'm gonna use two borders here, one
nested in the other, and the first one,
is gonna be a title border so I'll call
it, title border and
I'll set that equal to border
factory.create
title border and I'm gonna pass
in a string here and that's gonna be
database
what should we call it, database
preferences maybe database
preferences, that'll do for the moment
anyway prefer and siz.
And,
so that's going to create a nice, kind of,
border with title
in front, I can show you that if I go to
control border
and we set the title border, and let's get
rid of the
actually I'll need the border on the
bottom border just in a moment.
So if I run that now and do Ctrl-P, we've
got this border around it.
And I'm gonna put another border, which is
just gonna be an
invisible kind of margin, around the title
border to space out that.
So, I'm gonna say here, border,
spaceBorder,
Border equal
borderFactory.createEmptyBorder.
And I'm gonna get that, I'm gonna put some
I'm gonna fill in
these values here to see how much space I
want to create there.
Let's create an entire and say, let's call
it
n space equals, I'm not really sure, let's
try 15.
So let's put in here space, and we'll have
the same space all the way round, like
this.
And to create a border that goes around
the two, I can use borderfactory.create
compound border, so
the border that I'm gonna set in the
controls panel will be a mixture of these
two.
So I'm gonna use border factory.create
compound
border and then I have to parse the
outside border, which is gonna be a space
border and the inner border here, it's
gonna be the title border like this.
Let's see how that looks Ctrl-P I think
that looks quite a lot better, I'll get
rid of the line border around the the
buttons panel.
And if we run this and that doesn't look
too bad I can live with that.
And of course, you could play around with
it more like, I don't
know we could try, there are all kinds of
things that you could do.
I could try making this a bit, maybe, not
quite
so tall maybe it looks a bit better must
be
not quite so wide, either but this is the
sort
of thing that you could spend an awful
long time on.
And if you have a, visual designer, to
hand
of course, it's gonna be quite a lot
quicker.
And so, but, personally, I don't mind
doing this
by hand and because compared to the amount
of time
it takes you to put together the real guts
of
the application often it's, it not really
that much time.
Okay, so, that's it for this tutorial in
the next
Tutorial we're gonna look out setting
Icons on buttons, [INAUDIBLE] not.
Uh,we will look at that in time um,uh,
because
I'm gonna take this, very rough looking
toolbar at the
top and I'm gonna use a proper j toolbar
class
and I'm gonna put Icons on these buttons
and things.
But next time, actually, I'm gonna make
this connect to a
database, so join me again then and until
next time happy coding.