Hello, this is John from Cave of
Programming dot com and
in, this tutorial, we're gonna start a
little detour where we're gonna
look at connecting to a JDBC, we're going
to look at
connecting to a SQL database, I should
say, using a JDBC, so.
This is a part of swing.
And this applies to any kinda job
of programming, including including like
servlet programming.
But the reason I'm including this in this
series of tutorials is because I've found
that a lot of people, who write Swing
applications want to connect to a SQL
database.
So I'm just going to, I'm not going
to dwell on creating databases or anything
like that.
I'm just going to show you the minimum you
need to connect to an
existing database and to save stuff in it
and retrieve stuff from it using JDBC.
So I'm going to start by I've actually
already.
To actually connect in this case, I'm
gonna connect to
MySQL database it's running on my, on this
chain that I'm
working on here to do, to connect to MySQL
database you
need the MySQL Java Connector, Java is
I've got here and.
If you search in Google flat you'll find
it, very quickly and you can download it.
I think from the MySQL website.
Just search, like, MySQL Java Connector
and you'll find this job.
And you need that.
To connect to databases using JDBC.
So, to start with here, I'm going to go to
Eclipse and I'm actually not going to
use my user interface here because, one of
the advantages of keeping your back end
separate and.
Or keeping separated in code terms from
your front
end is that you can test the back end
separately.
I'm gonna do that here.
I'm gonna actually create a new class, and
I'm gonna call that Test.
Let's put Test Database, and let's give it
a main method, and I will type.
In here, just, this out, running database
test.
And I could actually use a j unit test
here as well,
but, I'll just stick with a simple, main
method for this, this tutorial.
Let's right click back and go to [UNKNOWN]
Applications runs down
here and now I'm going to my database
class and am gonna
give that a method called public void
connect, which is gonna connect
to the database and am also gonna give it
a a string.
The closing bracket there, I'm going to
get a public void disconnect and I'm
gonna test those from my test application
here, So I'm gonna say
database DB equals new database and then
I'm
gonna say DB dot connect and DB dot
disconnect, so we're just gonna connect.
And disconnect for the moment, and
yeah, let's see, so that's public void,
connect,
disconnect, and yeah, I've got a, added
the import
there already, added automatically, and
it's saying that the
method, oh yeah, I've just got to save it.
Sometimes Eclipse can be annoying, and if
you don't save stuff, you get an error.
When there isn't any there.
Now in the connect method, I've just gotta
do two pretty simple things.
The first thing is, I need to say class
dot full name.
And here I'm gonna dynamically load the
class that
is actually there, My SQL Java, connect to
driver.
So in here I'm gonna put.
Com dot MySQL dot JDBC dot driver.
And if I, I need to handle the exception
around
that, because it has a, throws a class not
found exception.
And I'm gonna throw that out to my connect
method saying.
Just throw new just make it a new
exception.
Driver not found.
Like that.
And then it says throws, throw you
exception.
And if I save that now I can add a froze
declaration.
Actually after I add the semicolon I can
add a throws declaration to connect.
And now I'm forced to handle that where I
used it to so here, I
can say add [INAUDIBLE] and down here I
can say, yeah let's just
leave it with e dot prints dot trace for
the moment, so I'll see
an error if it can't load that driver and
if I run it now.
Now I'm gonna see that our, cuz the
driver's not found,
and what I need to do is right click my
project here.
Go to build path, and, then in, in like
Net Beans for example, you have
to right click and go to properties, I
think, and you find a similar thing there.
And I need to go to libraries.
I'm gonna go to add external jar, because
the jar is not
actually in my project folder, and if it
was I'd say add.
Jar, and let's go to the location where I
put the jar file that
is, that contains the driver, so go to
tutorial swing scroll down
here, here's the MySQL connector, and now
if I run this,
I don't get the error cuz it's actually
managed to load the class which is good.
Now the.
The second thing I need to do here is
I need to actually get the database
connection.
So, for the moment, I'll just say
Connection com equals Driver Manager.
get.
Let's add the imports there, so I need
java SQL connection and
I need to say driver manager dot get, and
get connection.
And we're going to use the form that has
the username and the password.
Now the first argument here.
Is a kind of connection URL string and it
looks something like this.
So let's say string
connection URL I'll make sure a few rows
quite the right time I think it is
actually but, that's gonna look like this,
JDBC
the name of technology I'm using to
connect.
I'm going to connect to MySQL database and
then
we have, it looks a bit like a, drive
specification.
So, if I remember right, it's colon,
slash, slash and we need local host.
Because I'm connecting on this machine on
this case, and
you might wanna make that configurable on
your application of course.
And it's gonna run on port 3306, and
later on we're gonna get these connection
details
from, from the actual, dialogue, where you
can
specify by Preferences BI log, we specify
these details.
And then finally, I've got a database set
up already called, I think it's called,
SwingTest.
So, this specifies where and how to
connect to a database.
And if you have Oracle, of course, it's
gonna be slightly different.
And that's the first argument here,
connection URL.
In fact, let's just call it URL, so the
name URL, and now I need the username,
which is
going to be root, and in the real world,
you probably don't want to connect using
your root user.
You probably want to set up a user,
especially for your database,
and connect using that with restricted
privileges, and I'm going to use my.
Root password here, which is this
extremely cryptic string.
Oh, I don't know why cuz the port is not
even
open to the outside world, so probably
doesn't matter too much.
And then we gonna, we're gonna paste the
password in
there, and, and then we'll see if we can
connect.
Or not.
So if I think like so,
if this can't connect it's going to throw
a sequel connection
which is its going to throw sorry, SQL
exceptions.
sequence section which will be thrown out
with my connect method here as an
exception.
So because I'm using the base of exception
class here, of course this can, any
exception
can be thrown from there, which is perhaps
not best practice but It'll do for now.
And if I run this now you can see there is
no exceptions.
So we see that we've connected
successfully.
And now I'm gonna take this actual, this
connection object here, and let's say I'm
gonna
just put a few refinements here, and then
we'll leave the rest for the next
tutorial.
I'll say private connection, con there.
So we'll connect there.
And then in disconnect, I'll say, if com
is not equal to null,
then we're gonna call com.close.
And that throws an exception too, and I'm
just gonna throw that with a tri catch.
And I'm just gonna, I'm just gonna put
sysout I think, can't close connection.
I don't care so much about, about that
exception.
And, in my connect method, I'm gonna say
if,
If con is not equal to null and I'm just
going to return and not do anything.
So I want to make it save to call connect
model times
error and for a moment I'm just going to
put this out here.
This is.
connected, connected, and just so you can
see,
I'm just gonna put let's output the
connection object as well.
So, if I run that now you can see it says
connected, and it's just a two string
method on the connection object.
Let's do it, do it that now.
so, that's it for this tutorial.
I'm just gonna leave it with connecting to
the database [SOUND] and
then the next tutorial, we're gonna look
at retrieving data from the database.
In fact, maybe it makes sense to look
first at saving data.
So we can look at saving data and then.
After that we can look at retrieving data.
So join me again next time.
And until next time, happy coding!
[NOISE]