Hello, welcome back.
This is John from caveofprogramming.
And, in this tutorial, we're gonna look at
getting values from databases.
And the reason for that is I actually
wanna show you how
to save the database that we've got here,
into a MySQL database.
But in order to, to do that, we need to
check if the people in question are
already in that database.
And to do that, we need to get accounts
of for a particular person or a particular
ID.
We need to find whether that person's in
the database or not.
And if they are, we can do a update to
update the data.
Pertaining to that person and if they
aren't
in there, we can do an insert later on.
So, I'm gonna split this into a few, a few
tutorials and in this tutorial, we're
purely just gonna look at doing a count on
our people in database.
So, we've got no people in database at the
moment.
That's okay, I've setup a MySQL database,
with one
table it's got a, this database is called
swingest.
And we've already seen how to connect to
that.
And I've got a, people table here.
You can actually look at the model in this
very nice MySQL workbench tool.
And, so we've got all the relevant fields.
And your num fields, I put in as MySQL in
nums.
We'll see how to handle those.
[INAUDIBLE] The strings [INAUDIBLE] and an
integer there.
And we've got [INAUDIBLE] for the strings
there.
So in a moment if I do a select star from
people, there are no people in there.
And, I'm gonna go to Eclipse here, and I'm
gonna
give the database package a save method,
sorry, a database class.
So let's go to model here, and go to
database and I'll
give it a method, maybe down here a little
bit after disconnect.
Let's maximize the editor.
And, I'm gonna call this public void.
Save and this is gonna save the whole
database ultimately, into MySQL
database, so it's gonna save all these
people up here into my database.
So I'm gonna iterate through that list of
people.
And save so here we are.
So I'm gonna go for person, person then
people and I've reached one.
We're gonna check if that person is in the
database,
and let's say that he/she is, we'll
execute a update.
To obtain details.
Otherwise, we'll do a insert.
So, to check if a person's in the
database, I need a SQL statement.
And I'm gonna use a prepared statement,
that I will
then execute for every person in the
database with different parameters.
So, the way that works.
This is our creator-prepared statement
here.
And I'll call this Check ST MT statements,
equals con.prepare, preparestatement.
LIke this.
And that's gonna, I'm gonna pass that some
SQL to run, like this, inside the imports
there.
And don't add con.mysql.jdpc.
By mistake cause I'm only used to some,
errors that
you're sitting there scratching your head
there as I have done.
Add always the Java.SQL stuff here so
let's add that, let's add that import.
And oh, it's a prepare statement, not a
prepared statement, of course.
And I'm gonna throw the any SQL errors,
SQL sections, [SOUND] out
of the save method there, so that we can
check them in whatever calls save.
Now the statement I'm gonna prepare here
is gonna be let's
write some SQL here, I'll say spring
check, the SQL, equals,
and I'm gonna put in there, select count,
star, so I'm
kind of, I'm kind of assuming that you
know SQL already, and
if you don't, this will be kind of being
dropped in the deep
end for you.
But, select count star, ask count from
people where ID equals question mark.
So, that's selecting the count and, of
people who have this particular ID
represented by
the question mark and I'm gonna call the
at value in the results, I'm gonna
give it the name count, [SOUND] and the
reason I put a question mark there and
not a value, is because you should never
use, literal values in your SQL.
Partly because if you have strange
characters in there it could
screw up the SQL, and partly because of
the risk of SQL
injection attacks, where people type bad
SQL into your form, that's
designed to like, drop your database or
something, and the way to.
Protect against that, is to use prepared
statements and wildcards like this.
So every time I get a person here I'm
gonna say string.
Actually it's, I think the idea is an int.
So int ID, equals person.getID, and
then I'm gonna tell this prepared
statement to replace this wildcard.
With with the ID.
Let's just put the statement in here,
sorry the SQL in here, cuz the statement
needs to prepare the SQL and then we say
check statement, to check statement.
Dot set int and we pass in the position of
the wild, of this wildcard the moments all
of the, all other wildcards in the string.
And in this string, there's only one
wildcard, so it's
gonna be wildcard number one, because it's
start numbering at one.
Not zero, you have to watch that as well,
and then, we'll
put ID in here for the value, so this will
say, look for,
look for the first wildcard and replace it
by D in this statement, which is this
thing here then I can, I can execute that
statement.
I can say check statement.
Having prepared it, dot execute right
here.
And in fact, it's gonna be actually not
just execute,
but executequery, because this is a query,
which brings back results.
And it's gonna bring back results in the
form of result set, object
which I'll call [SOUND] check result and
I'll set that equal to that.
Just like there Java dot yeah, looks like
input there, okay.
And after I've prepared the statement and
finished using it.
Most important don't forget to close it,
with close.
Now, with this check result here I wanna
first,
move to the next row in this check result.
This check result has the rows of results
in.
There's only gonna be one.
Row, such as select can't start.
So I'll return me one row and I need to
move to the
first row because this will be positioned
internally to before the first row.
So I need to say check result.next.
Like that and once I've done that because
I'm not gonna check to
see that there actually, the next row
because I expect that there will
be from this statement and I'm gonna say
check result top get.
Ints, get ints.
And the command inde, common indexer is
gonna be one.
And now if I say intcount equals, and
that's gonna sit out there.
[SOUND] Count for person with ID.
I'm just gonna print out some debug
information here, first ID plus his lost
count.
And since I've not inserted any people
into my database,
I expect the results of this query always
to be zero.
So, let's just run that and see what
happens.
Actually, before I run it, I'm gonna have
to call it.
So in my test database code here, I can
say db.save.
I can wrap that with a tri catch.
[SOUND] So now if I run this, it's a Java
application.
It's it's not gonna do anything at the
moment
because, I also have to [INAUDIBLE]
dp.save.
I also have to add some people into the
database, and I almost forgot.
[SOUND] So because we're gonna query and
see if each of
those people is already in the database,
which they won't be.
Well, that's okay.
That said db.addperson.
And this is adding people to this array of
course here.
So I'm gonna say new person in here.
And, let's let's add in, the import and
then I can go, name, let's say like Joe
[SOUND]
that explains the editor occupation,
builder, age category: adult, age
category adult, I don't know what's
gone wrong.
Let's see, age category, oh yeah, the age
category's actually an age
category enum, so I need to say enum
value, age category dot adult.
And employmentcategory.employed.
[SOUND] Tax ID, let's set, [SOUND] 777.
US citizen I'll say true and gender, I'll
say gender.male, that's my enum, another
enum as well.
So gender dot male, Ip import that should
do the trick.
And, let's have one more person in there.
Just for kicks let's call this person Sue.
Let's make Sue an artist, because I wanna
make her self employed, self employed.
Self employed, and I'll make her not a
U.S. citizen, so the tax ID is gonna be
nought, it's a U.S. tax ID [SOUND] make
her female and [SOUND] let's hover.
senior.
Okay now there's, there is also another
small change that I'm gonna make, because
I've
said in my database here, I've actually
set the pan ID column to auto increment.
So yeah I, I ought to increment.
Which I'm not sure if that's really a good
idea or not but you can't actually
add, as far, as far I know, you can't have
zero for an auto increment value in MySQL.
So let's go to person here and let's make
account one
start with, because that's how the ID, is
set person down here.
So that all prevents.
Getting any funny errors, on count of, not
being able to have zero [UNKNOWN] values.
Finally let's run this and it says, count
for person with ID one is not,
count for person with ID two is not, so it
seems to be working just fine.
If I run it again, same.
Again.
Okay, and that's it for this tutorial, And
the next tutorial, we're gonna be
looking at inserting values into the
database.
So we're gonna be doing some insert
statements, well one anyway.
So join me again then.
And until next time, happy coding.