Hello this is John from
caveofprogramming.com and, in this
tutorial, were gonna look at inserting
values into databases.
So, in the last tutorial we did some work
on database.java
here, and I added this save method, and
the save method at
the moment just executes a statement that
counts, how many of each person
indeed array list the people, is in the
database already.
And the purpose of that is so you can
decide, well let's do an insert or an
update.
And so we get the count here and I'm gonna
say here, if count [SOUND]
equals 0 so if that person is not found in
the database, we're
gonna do a insert, otherwise we're gonna
do an update.
So let's get rid of this sisal, and let's
say here, sisal updating, sorry this is
inserting.
Inserting person with ID, and then let's,
let's add an ID, just some typical
[UNKNOWN].
And, if the account is not 0, [UNKNOWN]
we're gonna also have an update.
So, have updating personal ID, ID.
Now to insert a person into the data base
here, and the first
thing I need to do, is get all the bits of
information from the person object and of
course you could use some kind of
persistent strain work, to do this for you
but here I'm gonna craft it all by hand
and create all the SQL by hand.
So I'm gonna start by saying person.
I'm just gonna go through person basically
and get all the different values here.
So let's start with the name of the
person, and I'm gonna
fill in the variables in a minute, but
first I'll fill in
I'll just use the auto-complete to work
through the fields here.
Person.getAgeCategory, person.get
category.
Lets have the semi colon there, person
.uh, we got ID, got name,
occupation, tax ID, person .um, he's a US
citizen, it's not all we need.
So I've got one, two, three, four, five,
six, so you
can say to them, so person.um, get let's
see you've
got tax ID get agenda, [SOUND] and, I
think there's one more.
Let's have a look.
Person.get got and [UNKNOWN] gender ID,
name,
occupation, he's a US citizen we've got.
We've got the tax ID I'm missing one I
don't know, I am, including ID, we've
got one, two, three, four, five, six,
seven, eight, so actually I've got more.
Okay, so now I'm gonna write the SQL, that
will insert this stuff into,
the database actually let's first declass
some variables here.
So string name equals occupation is a, a
string again.
So occupation equals H category is an
enumerated type I've created in previous
tutorial.
So that's called age and employment
category is integrated type.
Tax ID, [SOUND] is actually a string and
US citizen is Boolean.
[SOUND] Gender, is also, an
enumeration, so there we go.
That looks good.
Now, up here, let's create some SQL that
can actually do the insert.
So now I'm gonna say string insert SQL
equals insert into people.
My database is called people.
Sort of my table is called people and, and
then I'd say columns in the people
table and this has to be right so I'm
gonna try this quite carefully.
ID, name, age and employment status.
So, ID, name, age, employ, employment
status, let's maximize the editor for more
space.
Tax ID US citizen, tax ID US Citizen.
I, I really recommend this,uh, MySQL
workbench tool, by the way.
It's, it's really good.
I can't remember if I mentioned it in the
last tutorial, but you can you can design
whole
entity relationship models with it, and
then import them
into your data base with data base forward
engineer.
But that's a distraction so let's keep on
trying here.
And what have we got?
US citizen, and gender and occupation
there.
So, gender and occupation.
And of course, you don't have to insert
values into all the table.
Columns because some of them might be
allowed to
be null and you'd then have to insert
values.
And these don't have to be in the same
order as your columns either.
But it's simpler if they are.
And then you say.
Values and then in round brackets here,
the CSS is just normal SQL.
In values, I'm not gonna call it literal
values.
I'm gonna put question marks, so, 1, 2, 3,
4, 5, 6, 7, 8.
So we've got one, two, three.
I need a comma there, so, one, two, three,
four, five, six, seven, eight.
1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8.
I think that looks okay.
That's format it okay,Ctrl+Shift+F and the
reason for that is, you
should never be tempted to concatenate
values directly into your SQL strings.
Probably because if someone types any like
weird.
Punctuation or whatever into the, it can
just mess up the
query, but someone could also maliciously
type SQL into your form.
It's designed to drop your database so,
you
could end up with a SQL injection attack
problem.
So the things too is the preferred
statements with these question mark
placeholders here.
And now in here if I'm gonna do an insert,
I
need to set the values for the parameters
on the insert statement.
And let's [UNKNOWN] statement.
So I'll say, prepared [SOUND] statement.
InsertStatement equals
com.prepareStatement, insertSql like this.
So, insert equals my strength here, and
now, let's go down
here to where, I'm gonna try to insert and
I'll say, insert statement.
If fact one thing I do, while I remember
it, is.
Right here I will close the statement,
[SOUND] because as soon as you prepare
a statement I recommend closing them,
otherwise
you'll forget like I just almost did.
And, and okay, so we've got we're gonna,
we've got the statement
now, I'll say that statement.set and first
value's an int ID.
So settings, and that's placeholder number
one, so it
starts numbering at 1, not 0, and that's
gonna be ID, and then
insert statement.um, setString to it's
gonna be name.
In fact, to make this a little bit easier,
let's say int col equals 1.
And, here I can have, col.
And, just col actually.
In fact, yeah, no col plus plus that will
do the trick.
And then here lets say col plus plus.
And then lets copy these.
So I want eight of them.
So that's two, three, four, five, six,
seven, eight.
And let's have a look and see what I've
gotta put in there.
So I need ID, ID name [SOUND] age, I'm
gonna get a string.
Age actually a, non-type.
I'm gonna send it into string by doing
name.
And if you do name on a non-type, you
actually get the
like you get this color here as a string.
So I would get child or adult senior in
this case, which is very handy.
So let's, let's do that [INAUDIBLE] again.
And, so I'll do age.name, and employment
status there is gonna be emp [SOUND]
.name, again.
Whoops, done something horrible there,
emp.name.
And the important thing of course is that,
these, these there have got
to match what I put in the SQL statement
up here, very important.
[SOUND] They've got to be in the same
order.
So after employment status, we've got tax
ID.
So tax, it's just a string.
And we've got ISUS, that ISUS, and that's
actually not a string but a Boolean, so
Boolean.
Very nice, and let's get rid of this extra
stuff here, so set Boolean, and then.
Got after, after isUS, I've got gender and
occupation.
So gender.name again, because it's
enumerated and
I want the string using the .name method.
And occupation is a string.
That was painful long-winded, but Here in
the end, and often you'll find,
or at least I find anyway, that you'll
often make mistakes doing this.
It can take a little while to debug.
And, so having done that, we can say
insert statement .uh, execute [INAUDIBLE]
you're gonna need execute update, because
you wanna actually update the database.
So, it's it's an insert, it's a type
of update statement rather than query of
course.
And later on we're closing it, but we're
not closing it until after we've done all
the people cuz we reuse the same
statement,
over and over again once you've prepared
it.
You've prepared it there, you set.
Values for the parameters.
And Bob's your uncle.
I think that should work.
Let's give it a go.
So I got my test database class here.
And I've got a couple of people there and
at the moment the database is, empty.
Here we go.
So let's run this as if it works if I run
it.
It finds that there are no people in
there,
and it inserts people with ID 1 and 2.
So it's running that.
And, I'm not getting any SQL errors.
[UNKNOWN] Cort, this is a good sign, and
that's, here's the revelatory
moment, let's do a select here and we've
got two people in the database.
So, hey, Presto.
And this is, this is null because I didn't
insert a tax ID for suit if you recall.
So suit and it's not US citizen and
[SOUND] that's your tax ID.
Okay, so that's working perfectly as far
as I can see.
And in the next tutorial, we're gonna look
at update statements.
So, now if I execute this again, it's
gonna find out that this
people are already in the data base, in
fact let's check that now.
So I'll click Run, and it says updating
person with ID one and two.
So the count has come non 0, you can't
[UNKNOWN] in the last tutorial.
And its found that its time to update them
not insert them, so in
the next tutorial, we're gonna look at
creating object statements with JDBC.
So join me again then.
And until next time, happy coding.
[SOUND]