Hello, this is John from
caveofprogramming.com, welcome back.
And in this tutorial we're gonna look at
updating database rows and now we're gonna
be basically.
We're just drawing on the stuff that we
done already and
except I'm gonna use SQL update statements
instead of insert statements.
So, if you're pretty comfortable with the
stuff we've
done so far and you know SQL pretty well.
Well then you could certainly consider
skipping this tutorial, but for
the sake of completeness we're going to go
over it here.
So at the moment, just to remind you, now
I've got
this test program in here which just
inserts a couple of people.
Because those people are in there now, so
If I go
select them in my database, we've got
those two people there.
If I now run this program, it's going to
attempt to
update these people rather than insert
them.
And now I need to write that will
take code, so It's gonna be hopefully
pretty straightforward.
At the moment, I've got up here, some SQL
for inserting people and
I'm I'm going to change this into some SQL
for updating people.
So I'll just copy that as a starting
point.
And I'm gonna call this, updateSQL, so
updateSQL.
And, it's gonna look like update people
set and
then I'm gonna have set, main equals
question mark.
So, I'm using question marks again, which
is very important.
Age equals question mark, employment
equals question
mark, tax ID, US citizen, gender,
occupation.
So I'll just update all of the values for
the
sake of simplicity, even though they
haven't necessarily all changed.
And, and need a, a where clause on the end
of that,
so I'm gonna say where ID equals question
mark.
So I think that should do the trick, it
will take people set, name
equals which is a search code of this
bracket here, where ID equals that.
Okay, lets try this, and I need a prepared
statements, so
prepared statements and I'm going to call
this update statement.
Actually I just noticed that I called the
statement stmt, I'll call it statement
and equals com.prepareStatement, and I
need to pass in updates SQL there.
So I prepared the statement, and now I can
set the relevant values here.
So It's going to be a little bit different
to this, but most of it's going to be
similar.
So, let's just copy that and paste it in
here.
And, I have to remember to close the
statement, so I have to say here update
statement.close.
And let's see, so here, and the ID is not
in the first column anymore,
in fact name is, so I'm gonna just remove
that from there and paste it down there.
Because ID is the last place holder column
now, if you look at this, and
we've got ID last instead of first, as it
was previously.
So, I need to change this of course, to
update statement.
So update statement.
Here we go.
I'll copy that, and it'll lead to change,
and hopefully this should be all that I
need to do.
So let's try, let's try running this now.
If I run this, it's gonna say I'll select
test database here, and run that.
And if I run this it says, it says it's
updating.
Let's just see if it really is, so if
I change Joe, from a builder to a lion
tamer.
And I change Sue from a from a senior to
an adult, let's say.
And so at the moment we've got we've got
those values in there.
Joe is Joe is a builder, and Sue is a
senior.
Then, if I run this with a bit of luck it
will update.
So let's go to here.
And we've got Sue is now a adult and Joe
is a lion tamer, so it seems to have
worked.
Now if, if I was actually, this is a
really
serious data base application, I'd
probably write some JUnit tests here.
And that systematically tests and updating
every single value in there.
And I could even also think of selectively
updating cells depending on which cells
I've actually changed.
But this isn't really a JTCP tutorial,
it's, I'm just
kind of putting this in for the sake of
completing this.
So, and hopefully this will give you
enough to implement your own
simple database code or get you started
with JTCP if you want to.
So I just leave that with that, and in the
next tutorial we're going to put the,
what should be the final part of this JTCP
code into place and we're going to look at
retrieving multiple pull constants from
the database.
So, join me again next time and until
then, happy coding.