Hello again, this is John from
caveofprogramming.com.
And in this tutorial we're gonna look at
loading
the existing people in the database into
our database class.
So, we're gonna retrieve the existing data
in the database and
pull it, create it, create person objects
to represent that data, basically.
So I've already got a save method here,
and in my database class.
And I'm gonna create a public void load
method.
And the first thing I'm gonna do in load
is clear.
The existing people I've got stored in my
list
of people up here in my data base class.
So I'll clear that cuz I want to load new
ones in.
And, I'm gonna create a statement here,
and
it's not going to be a preferred
statement.
Because I don't need to use, place all
this in my select statement.
So it's just gonna be a plain statement.
And I'll call that select.
Let's call it selectStatement, and I'll
set
that equal to com.createStatement, like
this.
And the next thing is to, let's have the
import there, java.sql.statement.
And, and ah,this throws a SQL exception,
so that's likely throws an exception as
well.
And then I can say select
statement.execute.query,
and I can parse some SQL in there to
execute.
And let's create the SQL string up here
actually.
So SQL equals, and then later on I'll
parse that in down here.
Now the SQL I want to execute.
Queue is just gonna be a select star from
people basically.
But
I I'm gonna repeat the column names in my
select star just because
it'll help me remember what's actually in
the person database.
And so let's say select,
paste that lot in from
from people.
And I'll say order by ID.
And or maybe we should sort it by name,
actually.
There's an idea.
Let's do that.
Multiply a name.
And I can of course test that query before
I run it, which will be handy.
So let's try running that, and it seems to
work.
Which is good, I've just got two people in
my database.
So after I've created this statement, I
mustn't
forget to destroy it, so I'll say select
statement.close.
And now I can get a result set from
executing
that statement, and oh, actually that's
that's this bit here.
So when I execute query some move up here.
So of course, we need to close it after
executing it.
Then that's going to return a thing of
tight result sets.
So result set, results equals.
And after you finish with result set, you
also close that, so close, like this.
And now I'm going to say, while results
start next.
And each time I call next, it's going to
move us on to the next row.
And the result set begins initialized to a
point before the first row.
So I need to call results.next, before I
can retrieve any data at all.
And once I've done that, I can use
results.get.
The results.get methods.
So, like, get, int for our first column.
And I've actually parse, column names in
here strings.
Which is a bit clearer than using common
texts I think.
And I'm not going to worry too much about
errors here.
if, if there's a mismatch between what
what common
names in the database, and what it
actually retrieve.
It will I think, will throw a c code
exception, which will be caught here.
So, that's enough error handling here, I
feel for this application.
And let's restart to test the principle.
So I can say int id equals and then let's
print out id.
And it's always good to test your codes
with just like a
really minimal skeleton type thing rather
than before make it more complex.
And I'll go to my test code here.
So add it people, updated people.
And let, let's say here db.load.
Call the load method.
There we go.
So, and I need to catch the SQL exception
of course surrounded to try and catch.
And I'll run this and it'll start updating
people and I've got two ids coming out
here.
So it seems to be working now let, lets go
through now and get all the other stuff
from the database.
So string name equals resorts.getInt name
and this is going to
be a little bit tedious with get string of
course get string.
This is gonna be a little bit tedious.
But I'll speed it up slightly by pasting
some of this in.
So let's have 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8.
And we've got name, age.
And let's call it, for employment, tax.
Is US, and gender, and occupation.
Let's call it occ.
Now name is string.
Age is a string.
Emp is a string.
Text is Boolean oops, I'm actually pasting
the wrong things in here.
I've got name, age, employment status,
let's
worry about these field names for start.
Because these have to be right.
So an U.S. citizen.
gender, gender goes here.
And occupation.
So of course, these all have to match
the common names that's the whole point to
them.
[UNKNOWN] So I think this is all, I think
this is all correct.
And, and now I have too much to word types
here.
Cuz I can't always use GetString.
So most of them are actually, strings.
I think, let's see, I think, so, tax id is
even a string.
U.S. citizen is a Boolean, it's a
getBoolean, maybe it's not.
Oh, yeah, well that's gotta be also
Boolean.
Let's have a look.
That seems to be okay.
Gender and occupation.
Let's just print out another one.
I've made an, any mistakes here.
So I run this code and it seems to be,
okay.
So, now, I can create the, person, object
here.
And I can say person, in fact I could just
create that on a the fly so to speak.
Statement say people, that's my array list
in database class.odds.
And then I can say, here, new person, so,
new, person.
And, I new to supply, to supply a load of
stuff to the constructor.
And, and I also need here to supply an id,
and I
haven't actually given the person object
yet, a constructor that can take an id.
So I'm going to go to person here, and
I'm gonna create a, an overloaded
constructor here, so let's copy this.
And I'll say this is int id.
And then, in here, I can say, this.id
equals id.
now, I don't want to set the id in this
constructor.
So, I could get rid of that.
and, should we increment the count, there
is
no harm in it actually so increment count.
And, but now, it would make sense really
if one constructor would
call the other so I could, I could, in
this constructor here.
I could call the other constructor.
But actually, I'll leave that for a
moment, cuz it's just gonna complicate
things.
So the main thing here is I just need
another constructor that
accepts an id, and sets the id rather than
setting it using count.
So, I'll leave it as it is for the moment.
But you could make one called.
Call the other.
That would be, that would get rid of
this kinda redundant, redundant code here,
kinda extra code.
In fact now that I look at it, I'm
starting
to feel like I really can't, I really
can't leave it.
Let's do that.
It's a little bit boring, but let's say,
in here.
This parse this all in, so name,
occupation, age, category.
Age, category and [UNKNOWN] tax ID.
And Eclipse is very helpful here in,
in helping me to fill in the values, and
telling me what I have to fill in.
So this is just calling the other
constructor.
and, and then then you have, the trouble
is you have to construct actually in
increments.
Actually sets the id.
But let's just override it here so we can
say this.id equals id.
So here in my new constructer.
Call the other constructor thus
eliminating this redundant code.
And, I, this constructor sets the id to
count and increments count.
Then, after I've done that, I'm then
setting
this id actually to the id that's passed
in.
So I think that should work.
And let's take a look here.
So now I need to fill in these values, so
I need
to say id, and name, and the the age here,
is actually an object type age category.
So it's an anon, and I need to convert my
anon from data.
It's two and age category and now that's
two I'm going to use age category m value
off and pass in the age string, like that
and attach.
And that should, that should work, I'm not
sure why it doesn't like it.
Let's take a look.
So maybe I pasted the wrong, wrong one in
there.
Age category.
Yes, so we've got id.
We've got name.
Yeah, we've got occupation first.
Occupation.
And then age category.
And let's maximize the [UNKNOWN] there.
It's more [UNKNOWN].
Employment categories.
So, saying again, top value of end, and if
ever your
autocomplete stops working when you press
Ctrl + Space.
It's a sign that you got the, you got the
arguments wrong.
So, and then we need tax id, U.S. citizen
so
this is U.S. and gender which is again a
numeration.
So gender value of, you're passing the
gender string now.
And of course, if you added another
numeration value to your database
you will probably often not succeed and
you'll throw an exception.
So if I yeah occupation I got I actually
called it occ so lets check that.
And see what we get.
Let's save it and I've got tax id.
I'll call it tax.
Let's rename it to tax id.
That's simpler.
And, and there we go.
So I'm not gonna worry about trapping
exceptions from
the enums and trying to convert values
that are wrong.
And I'll leave that as [UNKNOWN].
And we can try what happens if you put,
the wrong kinda argument there that
[UNKNOWN] can't convert.
But that should do the trick.
So, I've added a new person to my
database.
And, and actually, I think what I will do
is partly because this
is quite a long line and partly because I
want to debug it.
I'll just take that out here, type in
person
and I'll say person, person equals new
person there.
And I'm just gonna say here [UNKNOWN]
person to see how that looks.
Now, if I run this.
It's I forgot that I didn't give person
two strings, actually.
I could do.
So let's go to here and I'll give
it really quickly just a really simple two
string.
I'll say public string to string, and I'll
say, I'll just return I won't even use
string builder here.
I'll just use id plus plus name.
On the person, and then if I run that,
these are the people that it's retrieving
from the database.
So, once again, if this was a real
application.
And you didn't want to use some kinda
assistance framework to handle sorta this
business for you.
Then,
then you probably would want to test this
quite a lot more using probably j unit.
Here I'm not going to worry about it.
I'm just going to leave at that it
basically works.
And in the next tutorial, and while we're
finished with JJBC now, and in
the next tutorial we're gonna look at
wiring this code into our application.
Because remember I've just been using it
to test class here and to test data base.
And in the next tutorial we're gonna look
at, I'm
gonna have a button that saves data on the
table.
And, and we're gonna have a refresh button
that loads it in.
And we're just gonna look at where you can
terminate
your database connection and where you can
do the connect.
So that's for the next tutorial, and join
me again then.
And until next time, happy coding.