Hello, this is John from
caveofprogramming.com.
And this is a tutorial on just, wiring the
database code that
we've been creating in this series of
tutorials into the swing application.
So there, there isn't gonna be any new
really new stuff here.
It's just I'm gonna take stuff that I've
been showing you and bring it all
together.
So I'm gonna change this application so
that this is gonna be a save button.
So you can save the stuff the people
you've got
here in this pane and, and the table into
the database.
And this is gonna be a refresh button.
So that if you click refresh it's
basically gonna reload the
contents of the data base into the, into
the table pane here.
So, to start with, I'm gonna go to my
Mainframe.
And let's search for hello because I want
to change the names of these buttons.
And let's have a look.
So, in fact the buttons are named in this
Toolbar.java.
And later on we're gonna look how to use a
JToolbarController.
But for moment I'll stick with this.
So, this is gonna be called save.
And this is gonna be called Refresh.
Now I wanna make it so that when you click
save it takes everything in the
in that table.
As I save, it saves it to the database.
So I wanna make a make this raise in
event,
that tells the mainframe that save has
been clipped.
And at the moment all it's doing is
what it's doing is, this is text listener,
thing.
To the toolbar, you can set textListener
on the toolbar, and that
has a textEmitted method, which the
toolbar calls for when you click a button.
And this, this is kind of wildly an
appropriate name for I really want to do
here.
So the first thing I'm gonna do is go to
this textListener and change it to some
other kind of listener.
So I'm actually you know, wondering why,
why the hell I
called it textListener if I want you do in
the first place.
Let's go to the declaration of this.
Oh yes it's a stringListener.
And it's declared in this interface here.
So now let's, I'm gonna right click on
that and get to Source.
Actually it is Refractor my new entry and
clips,
I'm gonna rename this stringListener to
something more appropriate.
Let's just call that, let's call it
ToolbarListener which would make a lot
more sense.
So, and I click Finish there.
And instead of textEmitted, let's refactor
that, rename it to
let's see.
Well this is gonna be an event
that's raised if something happens in the
toolbar.
So, let's call this well this can be call,
called
saveEventOccurred really,
and this method could be called if you
click the Save button in the toolbar.
I'm seeing if that's really a good name
for it.
Yeah, let's, let's go with that.
Doesn't matter too much.
And let's also give it a public void
refreshEventOccurred.
And we don't need really to have any
string text in there either.
So these are just gonna be two methods
that call
in response to the Save and Refresh
buttons being clicked.
So I think that'll do the trick.
And now let's have a look in the toolbar
here and see if we've gotten any problems
in there.
So, later on, we call saveEventOccurred,
if this Hello button is clicked,
so, I'm, I'm gonna change that, let's give
it a text hello and goodbye.
And if you click the Goodbye button, okay
now, have a refresh again.
I'm gonna rename these these buttons.
So instead of helloButton, I'm gonna go
with Refactor > Rename.
I'm gonna call it, saveButton.
And Continue.
And let's rename the Goodbye Button.
Let's call that Refresh Button.
So it really saves a lot of time using
these refactor kinda shortcuts in Eclipse.
Because they will find all the places
where
you will, you can get's changed for you.
So that's the toolbar, toolbar delegate,
if I run, if i run this application now.
Actually I can't because I've got an error
in my mainframe.
Because this now leads to declare.
And what we got is message method, message
about serial version ID which we don't
really need.
But I'll get it one of those to shut It
up.
And then we should have another error in
there,
because down here, and the toolbar is now
has the same
event, that doesn't that doesn't accept
any text.
And let's go ahead and get rid of this,
reference to the text panel.
And the the Toolbar Listener has to have a
method called
public void and Refresh Occurred, so let's
add that there.
So we're getting there.
And also I've got this toolbar that the
message is set in the listening toolbar.
A moment it's called setStringListener,
which can as well be appropriately sets
right-click on that, go to Refactor >
Rename, I'll call it setTool.
ToolbarListener.
Okay, so that's just is a lot of stuff,
but just dealing with the tool bar.
And now, if someone clicks that's actually
how this works, so we've always got
practice.
So if they click Save button, I wanna emit
saved in console down there.
And if I click Refresh, let's have it say
Refresh.
So, Save and Refresh.
That looks good.
Okay, and so if someone clicked Save.
And by the way sometimes when this
application's quit, especially if you
click cross bar, sometimes there's that
InterruptedException down here,
and that's actually a little book in swing
as far as
I know, and there is some stuff on google
about it.
And I found what seems to be a fix for it
and I'm gonna show you later, but it
doesn't really affect anything.
And strangely, if you quit by using the
menu item here, you don't seem to get it.
So it's quite odd but we will be fixing
that later on, not that it matters.
And so here if say, it was clicked.
I wanna basically invoke the save method
in the database here, but before that
we gotta connect to the database, and the
way I wrote the database code
you'll recall is that you can click
connect multiple times, and if it's
already
connected, and in fact if it is not null,
it just won't do anything.
And now the first thing I wanna do is cuz
I've
decided not to have my GUI call my model
code directly.
It's gonna go through Controller.
I need some wrapper methods in my
Controller.
And, in my Controller, I need to have a
save method from my database.
So public void save.
And let's just say db.save.
And that's gonna have to throw an
exception.
And then we'll have public void close,
which close the database.
Closes the database connection, db.close.
I'm gonna look at where to put that in the
next tutorial so
actually I maybe call it disconnect.
Let's see, disconnect, yeah.
And yeah, disconnect actually doesn't
throw an exception, so that's fine.
now, I yeah, I've got, I've already got my
save method there.
So that's good.
So now in the toolbar here in the yeah, in
the mainframe we're actually works when it
listens to the toolbar.
When the event is occurs, which
corresponds to
the save button being clicked in the
toolbar.
Then I wanna say controller.connect.
So, controller.connect.
Where are we?
Controler, oh not connect, but yeah, I
didn't like the connect method yeah,
actually.
I want the public void connect in fact
let's call this closed, let's call it
disconnect.
That's maybe, makes more sense.
And that's gonna fire, that's gonna call
db.connect.
And that throws an exception.
So I've got connect and the disconnect
method, I've got my save
method, and actually I also need to put
public void load method.
All of these are purely rapid methods in
the controller.
And, and you might decide that, to just
kind of,
call the database code directly from the
review if you code.
But it's really up to you.
okay, so
that looks good.
And now in the main frame, let's
say controller.connect if you click that
button.
And then I'm gonna say, controller.save.
So controller, controller.save.
Now the connect button shows an exception,
so
I'm gonna handle that surrounded try and
catch.
And if, we can't connect to the database,
I'm gonna say J
options paid dot and it's just
JoptionPaid.yes dot.
And, and let's how I show
show com, show confirm dialog.
Actually just show info dialog would do
the trick.
And showMessageDialog, there we go, that's
what mean, showMessageDialog.
And I wanna use the constructor here, that
this constructor and let's select that.
And maximize the editor.
And in here, so for this I need to pass
the MainFrame.this.
I can't just use this by itself because,
this enormous class here has it's own
bliz.
And the message there is gonna be cannot
connect to database.
And the title is gonna be Database, I
don't know, Database Connection Problem.
And let's have JOptionPane.warning
error_message.
That's the one.
So that should look good, I think.
And then, if everything goes well, we'll
do control adopt saver.
And that also throws the sequel exception.
So I'm not really sure why it's not giving
me the option to to handle it here.
Although yet, the mainframe is showing an
error.
Well let's, let's deal with that.
So and it's such in its throne from
the controller there, is it's actually SQL
exception.
So I feel like Eclipse is being a little
bit, temperamental here.
But, it's probably something that, wrong
or something, I'm not sure.
So that throws a sequence conception.
And controller.connect can actually throws
an exception.
Okay.
I can't remember why, but that's good.
Okay, and now, here now It's letting me
add controller.save.
So let's add a try-catch around that.
That throws the SQL exception.
And we'll have a message box that pops up
there saying something very similar to the
first message box.
And, let's say, Unable to save to
database.
We don't know why.
But we'll pop up a suitable message if
that happens.
So now we want the, in, in this refresh
method
that's triggered, if you click a Refresh
button on the toolbar.
I want to say controller dot dot load.
And that throws an exception, so let's
handle that.
I'm gonna use this kind of message box.
And it's gonna say Unable to load from
database.
And we're also gonna have a similar thing
here.
I'm gonna have this, like if you can't
connect
to the database, I need to pop up this
message.
But rather than repeat the code, let's
maybe just have a message called
connect the, sorry method called connect,
you can call it a message.
Method call, connects the call to connect
method.
And let's just implement that method here.
Private void connect, and in connect I'm
just gonna put the code for
connecting to the database and popping up
the error message if that doesn't work.
Now, I think that should do the trick.
So, I'm gonna run this.
And in my database I've got a couple of
files in there John, Sue.
So let's click Refresh and see what
happens.
Oh yeah, there's something that I actually
forgot, which is that when the refresh
event occurs, I've got to call
tablePanel.refresh
otherwise it's not going to display
anything.
So let's run that and click Refresh, and
there we go.
Look our values.
And if I put another one in here, I'll
call myself John, cuz that's
my name software 1865 and self employed,
thank you very much.
[INAUDIBLE] Click OK.
And then just click Save.
And,
now, we can see in the database hopefully,
if I do a refresh, there I am, John.
Of course there's, there's lots of ways
you
could refine this, but I'm not gonna worry
too much about it in this tutorial,
because
the tutorial is just gonna get
ridiculously long unnecessarily.
But you could, you know you could have a
message saying no data saved or something
popping up
at the bottom or who knows or even a pop
up box, well that could be quite annoying.
Or you could, I don't know you could make
the button go grey to click save and then
you could make it unable to get someone
added to the table or something like that.
But I'll leave that for the moment.
So, that's that.
I hope that was useful, just wiring
in existing stuff, just wiring is all
together.
And, in the next tutorial, we're gonna
look
at something that I've left out of this
tutorial.
Which is like, okay, we've connected to
the
database, but where do you disconnect from
the database.
And to disconnect from the database, we're
gonna intercept the window closing event,
and even though we're gonna disconnect
from the database before the window
closes.
And I'm also gonna fix, fix this bug that
I mentioned earlier.
Which is, is sometimes you see like a
thread interrupted exception.
When you, when you quit the the, the swing
program by clicking on this thing here,
without [INAUDIBLE] swing.
And I don't think there's actually wrong
with this code.
Okay, so join me again next time and until
then, happy coding
[BLANK_AUDIO]