Hello there, this is John from
caveofprogramming.com.
And in this tutorial we're gonna look at
intercepting the window closing event.
And one reason to do that, is so that you
can clear up clean up resources in
there, and in this case, we're gonna use
it to disconnect from a database.
So actually, one thing to do, is to make
sure that
you can disconnect from your database,
even if you haven't connected.
So let's go to the Connect method in the
database here.
And you can see that I've checked, but the
connection's not null.
Because that can lead to a a very
nasty error, if you try to disconnect from
something.
And it's, it's null where you get that no
point reception.
Okay, so let's go in to the mainframe code
here.
And at the moment, I've, I've got this
exit on close thing happening, so I've,
I've caught Set Default close operation
for the
JFrame, and I've said JFrame exit on
close.
And I'm gonna change that, that means that
when
you close the JFrame, it's gonna quit the
application.
I'm gonna change that to do nothing on
close for the moment,
and now, I'm gonna add a Window Listener
to my JFrame.
So I'm gonna say Add Window Listener, and
I'll say New, and I'm not
gonna use the Window Listener itself,
because
Window Listener has like 5 million
different methods.
I'm gonna use a window adapter, which is a
class that implements all the
methods of Window Listener, and let's me
override just the ones that I need.
And it's been sent to a mouse adapter if
you know how that kinda code works.
But don't worry if you don't.
So I'm gonna do go and I'm gonna say
import Window Adapter there.
And then let's right click in there,
and go to Source, overwrite and implement
message.
And I'm gonna override the window closing,
because
I wanna get the window as it's closing.
And in here, let's close this out just for
the moment
and say, window closing, cuz we wanna see
when it actually arises.
And now, I I mentioned earlier, well I
mentioned
in the last tutorial that sometimes, if
you quit
the application here, really clicking the
cross in the
corner, you see like stack trays here,
about interrupting threads.
And if you search on Google, that seems to
be, be
a, a bookend swing, and it may be related
to JFile chosers.
but, I, I've, I've found, and this seems
to help.
But if you do system, system.gc.
So you run the Garbage Collector, like
this, before quitting the application.
That seems to help.
And I'm also here, because, I'm gonna
enter Set Window Closing, print out this
message,
and then I'm gonna call the JFrame dispose
method, which is gonna dispose of my
window.
And when you've disposed of your windows
in Swing, then it, it quits automatically.
I'm just gonna run the garbage collector
at the
last possible moment before the thing
finally bows out.
So let's just see how, how that looks if I
run that as a Java application,
I need to select main class and click the
Run button.
When I click the cross in the corner and
we've got the window closing
event, and there's no trace about, which
is nice although it was intermittent as
before.
But it looks good as far as I can see.
I'm pretty happy with that.
But now, you can still quit the
application by going CTRL+X or
going to the window of the file menu and
go into File Exit.
So, and that doesn't produce a window
closing event.
So I wanna make that work, and
I've actually called system.exit somewhere
in here.
So I've set system.exit here, and that's
the, this
is the Action Listener on the Exit Menu
item.
And actually one alternative to calling
systems that
I've set there, to simply log with
Cleaner.
I used to call it dispose method cuz if
you dispose your
windows, then your frame, your swing
application will exit automatically and if
you
actually just want to do a manage to be,
your windows to become
invisible, but for the application not to
quit then you would just call.
That physical fonts on them.
So, here on this point, I want to create a
window closing event,
because I've added a window adapter that
listens for the window closing event.
And what I could do there is my main frame
actually has a method called Get.
Window listeners not window status
cause that's something different, but
getWindowListeners.
And that returns an array of Window
Listeners.
So Window Listener, and that is an array.
So having trouble here because
unfortunately, the
right bracket on my system conflicts with
another shortcut.
I've got like a Hungarian keyboard here.
I'm trying desperately to type that
[INAUDIBLE] and that have ellipse put in.
There we go.
So WindowListener, Listeners.
And one of the listeners is the, the
listener that I just started, the window
adapter.
That's probably the only one.
So I'm gonna say let's get rid of this
extra text, and say WindowListener array.
Listeners equals getWindowListeners at the
import
and then, I can say let's see why it
doesn't load that?
Cannot be resolved to a type.
Window [UNKNOWN].
WindowListener.
Not WindowsListener.
There we go.
Then I can say 4, or at least this is
one way of doing this, but there are other
ways, certainly.
For WindowListener, Listener, and
Listeners.
I can just say listener.,
and it's not gotten many methods, I don't
wanna call
the window closing method here, and that
accepts the window
event, so you say new window event, the
source I could make
mainframe.this, let's say, and does it
have another argument?
Yeah, so let's just press in 0 for that
second [INAUDIBLE] argument, which is just
an ID interface
integrating inside of your [INAUDIBLE] but
it doesn't, it
doesn't matter, it's not gonna make any
difference here.
As long as this does the trick, because
all this has to do here is basically make
sure that the the window adapter, which is
listening,
.task, this code's gonna be a bit long
actually.
It just, we just need to call that
window closing method, and that's what
we've done here.
That's exactly what I've done.
So let's go back there.
So, Control > Home > Window > Closing.
And now, if I run this, and if I, if I
invoke this File Exit menu item, you still
get Window Closing when you print it out,
so whichever way we're quitting the
application
now, through the File menu or through
the cross in the corner, we get this
window closing, which is rather nice.
So, all I need to do now hopefully, is
just call
controller.disconnect and if if I haven't
connected, cuz I haven't
clicked Save or Refresh then it's fine,
we've accounted for that possibility.
And if I have clicked.
It's okay to click Save actually.
If I, if I hit Refresh I'd quit,
then it's gonna disconnect from my
database, hopefully.
Okay, so that's it for this tutorial.
In the next tutorial, we're gonna get away
from this
database related stuff and, we're gonna
look at setting icon, icons
on buttons, and that'll be a step towards
using a JToolbar
component, yeah, so we'll turn this into a
fully fledged toolbar.
So join me again then, and until next
time, happy coding.
[BLANK_AUDIO]