Hello this is John from
caveofprogramming.com
and this is a tutorial on adding
icons to your buttons using images that
you can create yourself or download.
Now, probably the first thing to say is
that if you
go to Google and search for, something
like Java graphics repository.
You can get this you can get this JAR here
from sun, that
contains various icons for most purposes
in the so called Java look and feel.
Because [INAUDIBLE] applications can be
set to use different look and feels.
And this is designed for the Java one.
But you can also create your own icons.
And in this tutorial I'll show you how to
drop your own
images into a package, and to use those on
buttons, but
what I'm gonna show you will also apply to
using images
directly from JARs that you've downloaded,
and so we'll basically cover both.
Now, because I wanna show you how to use
the individual images in
case you want to use your own, I've I've
actually downloaded that
JAR, and, and, I've I've unzipped JAR I've
unJARed it.
And, I've I've gone to directory here and
found two good icons that I want to use.
So I got the Refresh 16, or 16 by 16 pixel
gif icon in the same 16
by 16, and I want to use those on my
buttons in this application here.
I'm gonna start by creating a new package
to put the images in, so I've right
clicked
my start folder here and I'm gonna go to
New > Package, and I'm gonna call this,
images.
Click Finish.
And now, I could, browse to that folder,
on my computer, and, but I do proctors
here.
You can find the actual folder, there it
is.
But you can also just drag and drop them
in, so I'll take the last approach.
And I'll go to my icons that I downloaded
here, so
I've got refresh 16, and I also want save
16.
I'm just gonna drag those into the to this
package here.
Now, before I can load the images and the
clips,
I need to make Eclipse copy those to my
build folder.
I'm just going to right click source here,
and go to refresh.
If you ever find if you ever find that
you can't load resources visible in your
package browser here.
Try right-clicking refresh, because that
often helps,
so now I've got my images here.
So I'll go to the toolbar.javaclass and,
and
I'm gonna give this a method for loading
images.
And I could load images very simply with
just one line here add on a button.
But I'm gonna actually create a method,
just because I
want that method to warn me if the image
isn't present.
Because it's easy to have problems with
images not loading.
And I want to avoid that.
And I want a war, a warning if it can't
find the image.
So, I'll create a method here.
Private is gonna return an image icon
object.
I'll call that create icon, and I'll pass
in here a path
which will be the path, packing, kind of,
path of the image to load.
Let's have the [INAUDIBLE] icon.
And now I'm gonna say,
getClass.getresource.
So getClass will get me the class object.
There's actually there's actually a class
called class.
And that will get me the class object
associated with this toolbar.Java.
Which is it doesn't really matter but it's
J panel.
And then I'm gonna use get resource method
of the class, class.
And what that does is it uses a class
loader to actually load your resources.
So ClassLoader's the thing that loads your
Java classes.
And I wanna use that same, piece of
technology to lose, use to load my images
here.
Now I'm in here.
I'm in the GUI package.
This toolbot.java is in the GUI package.
So the kinda URL of the image is gonna
look like, well actually let's leave that
for the moment,
because let's just fill in this general
method, so I'm
gonna load images from a path like this,
and that's.
Is gonna return the, a, a url.
So I'll say url, url equals, and this is
the URL the resource and locator of my
image.
And at the end put there javanet,
java.neturl.
And, and now I can say url.get.
[SOUND] url dot, oh, sorry, don't do that.
Let's say ImageIcon, icon equals new image
icon and, if I remember
correctly, can pass the URL as an argument
in the icon constructor.
And then finally I can return the icon
like
that [SOUND] and its worth mentioning here
that when you
create your image icon, so this is the,
this is
the little class that is going to contain
my image.
As a second argument here you can supply
description and that's for kind
of visually impaired people because I
guess
screen reading technology can read that
description.
I'll leave that as is for the moment.
So I'll return my image icon here, and I
just wanna, my purpose in creating this
method is really so I can just say here,
if URL is equal to
null then that means we couldn't load it,
and I'm just gonna say syserr control
space this is going to add up print ln,
unable to load
resource, say unable to load image
actually, and plus half.
There we go.
Now I can use that.
To set images on my toolbar button, so I'm
gonna get
the save button here, and I'm gonna say,
savebutton.seticon.
And you can use to set, this technique
with labels as well.
Even [UNKNOWN] really big images.
If you want a big image somewhere in your
program you can
just put a label there and load a big
image onto it.
I'm gonna say set icon, and I'm gonna
use the create icon method that I just
created.
And then I'm gonna say in here I'll pass
it a path.
Now the path, I'm in the GUI, I'm in the
GUI package.
If the image's package was within the GUI
package, I could say images
here, stroke, and the name of the image to
load so save.
16.gif, but because I'm actually in the
GUI package already, I
need to go to that kind of, root, of these
packages,
with a slash at the beginning, and then go
up into
the image's package, and then I think I
might find the icon.
The important thing here is, this
directory this package or directory,
depending on how you look at it, shows
exist on the class path somewhere.
So it, it, this doesn't have to be within
your project folder or anything, but it's
gotta be.
On the class path somewhere, so, okay, so
let's see if that works.
Now, if I run that and let's go to App
here and run that.
Now, I've got save icon on my button
there, and I'm gonna do the same with
the refresh button, so I'm just gonna copy
that, and let's make this refresh.
I think it's called refresh 16, there, and
now I
maybe have one, one plant line there, it's
from that.
Okay.
That didn't work.
Why didn't it work?
Because I've got the save buttons that the
refresh buttons.
The refresh button.
That should work.
Okay.
Now that's it for this tutorial.
I must say it's a very powerful technique
and
you can move big images for that on to
labels.
It's great.
But in the next tutorial, I'm gonna make
this
look more like a tool bar by removing the
text on the buttons and I'm gonna use a
Jtool bar class instead of my panel class
here.
So join me again then, and until next
time, happy coding.
[SOUND]