Hello.
This is John from caveofprogramming.com.
And in this tutorial, we're gonna look at
the JToolbar class and
we're gonna make this toolbar up here look
a bit more interesting.
So at the moment I've got text on my
buttons as well as icons.
So often what you what is a tool bar like
this one here, that just has icons on it.
Now if I go to my tool bar class here,
which is actually a kind of J panel,
and I remove the text from the buttons
like this, [SOUND] and run that.
They actually look a bit rubbish cuz
they're
rectangular and it doesn't really look
like a toolbar.
And I'm gonna fix that now.
And one thing I'm gonna do to start
with actually, is I'm gonna add tool tips
there.
So I'm gonna say,
saveButton.setToolTipText save.
[SOUND] And, I'm also gonna say
refreshButton.setToolTipText.
Refresh.
[SOUND] And you can use set tool tip, text
or any kind of buttons anywhere
and you then get these tool tips that come
up, which is rather nice.
Okay, now I'm gonna change this J panel
into a toolbar.
So I'm gonna say, search J panel here.
I'm gonna say extends JToolBar with
capital B and I'll add
the input there and I'll get rid of, the
set layout thing here.
And to add buttons to a tool bar you just
call ads, and a button name.
And sometimes you wanna make a separator,
between two groups of buttons.
And then you could say add separator.
[SOUND] And if I run that now, you can see
that the buttons are square.
And I've got a separator, just a blank
space between them.
I'm gonna get rid of the separator because
it doesn't look
that good in this application because
there are only about two buttons.
and, and now I've [UNKNOWN] like that and
they've got tool tips as well.
And, they should still work.
There
you go.
And, now you can make the toolbar
draggable as well.
If you want.
And one thing that I need to do, is get
rid of this border here.
And if I, if I run that, it's gonna be
with a bit of luck trackable.
So, it, in a moment, I can, you
can actually drag it completely out of the
application.
And you can fix that if you want.
But I'm having trouble here docking it.
And I think that's because, when you add,
toolbar.
If I go to MainFrame here.
You need to add toolbars using where are
we, so we've added it using.
Let's look for the border layout.
Here we go.
I've added it using BorderLayout.North.
But, you, you need to add it using
page_start like that,
and you also wanna be careful about what
other components you're adding.
So here I've got a FormPanel to the West.
And that will stop my toolbar docking to
the west, so to speak.
But, I think I can still dock it here.
There we go.
On the right.
So we're gonna drag and drop the toolbox.
It's quite difficult to get [UNKNOWN].
Here at top sometimes.
And okay, I think that's just about it for
this tutorial.
If you don't want your toolbar to be to be
floatable.
If you don't want it floating.
Then say set floatable, false and then if
I run this.
It's no longer, gonna be actually even
dragable, and
you can also like there's nothing stopping
you setting borders around your toolbar.
But, if you set a too, a border around the
toolbar, it's not gonna be not usually
gonna be draggable so.
And these have it with not bother, it's
draggable.
But actually I'm, I'm not really convinced
in
the value of draggable tool bars on the
whole.
I actually quite like the look of it with
set border.
let's just put a comment here.
Get rid of the border if you want the
toolbar draggable.
[SOUND] Okay, so that's it for this
tutorial.
And in the next tutorial, we're gonna look
at splitter windows,
so join me again then and until next time,
happy coding.
[SOUND]