Hello, this is John from
caveofprogramming.com, and
in this tutorial we're gonna look at
JSplitPane.
And so if I, if I run the program as it is
at the moment now, and at the
moment there's a kind of firm fixed size
between
this table and this form, when you can't
resize it.
Which actually really is probably fine for
this application.
But, in order to demonstrate SplitPanes,
which are often very useful.
I'm gonna change this so that you can
resize
the border between these two these two
forms here.
So I'm gonna go to my main frame here, and
I'm gonna create a private JSplitPane,
which I'll call Split Pane.
And after I've constructed my other
components down here, I'm gonna say,
SplitPane.
That's actually at the import, so the
auto-complete works.
SplitPane, equals new JSplitPane.
And, I'm gonna supply some arguments to
the constructor here.
And the first one is gonna be jsplit,
whoops.
Ctrl+Z.
The first one is gonna be jsplitpane, and
here I wanna set where I,
I need to set whether I want a horizontal
split or a vertical split.
And in this case, I want my components to
be arranged left and right.
So I want the horizontal split and then,
I'm going to pass in the two components.
So I want to split between and you can
change these
components dynamically, if you want to,
but here I won't do that.
I'll just say, on the left, and on the
Form Panel,
and on the right, I want the Table Panel,
like that.
So and now instead of adding the Form
Panel under Table Panel down
here, I'm gonna add the split pane, at
borderly at the center, and
I'm gonna get rid of this separate from
panel ad, and if I
run that now, and I've got the split pane
here, which is, re-sizeable.
[UNKNOWN] There we go.
And now there's a few things you can do
with this.
One thing is I need to fix a little bug
here because the way my application works
at the moment, I
can go to window show an unticked person
form, and the
person form vanishes, and split pane
handles it rather nicely, actually.
If I go show it doesn't reappear.
So I'm gonna finally show Menu Item.
I think it's called Show Item.
Or maybe not.
Show Menu let's have a look.
Show Menu.
So we've got Show Menu.
And we've got Show Format in here.
And I've got an action listener, here we
go.
So, I'm gonna change this, I'm going to
set
the the size of the divider on the
splitter.
I'm gonna set the position of the divider,
sorry, when you show the Form Panel again.
So let's say here, if menu item.is
selected.
So, in other words, if the menu items
ticked which means that the users ticked
it, when it was unticked before, so
they're ticking it to show the Form Panel.
I'm gonna say SplitPane.set, divider
location.
And you'll notice there's two, there's two
varieties of this.
There's one that takes a double and that's
a
proportional location from zero, 0.0 to
one point naught.
And there's one that takes an int, which
is a pixel, location.
From the left, in this case.
I, I want to set, actually, the
location to do something approximately
like the formpanel.,
and let's get the minimum size of the Form
Panel here.
And one thing I really need to mention,
actually, is that you should set minimum
sizes on
your components, so if I go to, let's just
take a quick look in the Form Panel here.
Form Panel, here, I got a preferred size,
I've actually got a minimum size.
And so the minimum size is probably gonna
be set
at the default, when I set the, set the
preferred size.
That's that.
A minimum size here, and so that's, when I
call set preferred size, I'm also gonna
set minimum size.
Mimimum size.
To prevent that form
getting too small.
So, if I run this now it's gonna stop me
scrolling too much to the left and
squashing the form.
So you probably want to set a minimum size
for the components in your splitter.
Okay, that's a bit of a diversion, but
now, we'll still find that if I
hide the form panel, show it again, I
still, I still got problem.
I need to move the splitter over.
So in the showMenuItem, I'm going to say
SplitPanes set
DividerLocationFrontPanel.getMinimum
size .getWidth and now getWidth returns
a double value and that would call the
variety of setDivider, sorry a form of
setDivider location.
That and it take a double from 0.0 to 1.0
and I don't want that.
I want the pixel width variety.
So I'm just going to cast this width to an
int.
So now, if I click Run and I go
to window show person form, Unshow it, and
Show again.
It's gonna set the divider to an
appropriate location.
And notice to make that work, I also set a
minimum width on my form, a minimum size
on my form.
okay, so that's that.
And there's one other thing that is, is a
little bit interesting, which is that
on my SplitPane I can say I can set it to
SplitPane.setOneTouch [UNKNOWN] tree.
If I do that it, puts in these little
icons here and I can just click those to
expand and contract like that and.
Or I could [UNKNOWN] using the splitter,
if I want.
I can have my form as big as I like.
It doesn't look very good big, so, in this
case, I don't know if that was
a really a useful thing to do, but it's
just a demo really of the JSplitPane.
So, in the next tutorial, we're gonna look
at
JTabbedPane, and I'm gonna change this
table here into
a TabbedPane where one tab has a table on
and the other tab has something else on
it.
So join me again then, and until next
time, happy coding.
[SOUND]