Hello, this is John from caveofprogramming
.com, and
in this tutorial, we're gonna look at
tabbed panes.
So I'm actually gonna, change this
application so that instead
of just having a table here, we've got a
tabbed pane.
One tab's gonna have a table in it, and
the other tab's gonna have a very fancy
looking message reader that will well, it
won't actually do anything, but,
will can make it display messages from
retrieve from an imaginary server.
That gives us an opportunity to look at
some more interesting swing components.
So this tutorial we're just gonna do the
top pane bit,
and I'm gonna start by declaring a private
J [UNKNOWN] pane here.
We [UNKNOWN] pane, and right here, before
I create
the split pane, I'm gonna set the type
pane to a
new [UNKNOWN] pane, and I'm gonna add the
tab pane
to the split pane instead of a table
panel.
So here I'll put tab pane instead of the
table panel.
And if I, if I run that in a moment we're
not gonna see anything interesting cuz
there's no tabs in it.
But now I can add tabs to that tab pane.
So, let's go ahead and do that.
The first type I'm gonna add, I'm gonna
say type, tab pane dot add tab.
And, you can give each tab a title, and a
component to display actually in the tab.
You can also, if you want specify an icon
for
the tab as well, but we won't do that
here.
I'll just use this form in the
constructor.
So I'll say here person database a dot
being my first
my first tab, and in there I'll put table
panel.
And then I'll have another tab pane here,
another tab, add tab and,
and I'll call this messages, [SOUND] and
in there I'll just use the
text panel for the moment, I I had an
earlier version of this
application, and [INAUDIBLE] put it in the
right place so we get messages.
And something else that's worth mentioning
here is you can also
set a custom component by saying, see top
pane set tab component.
And you supply an index.
The index is a zero based then you can
set a component that actually appears on
the tab.
Like, for example, you can implement your,
own close button.
But, I'm not gonna do that here.
I'm just gonna have very simple, plain
tabs.
So if I run that now, I've got two tabs.
The one tab has my personal database in
it, and.
And, the other tab I'm gonna turn this
into a sort of message panel.
And so that's it for this tutorial.
And in the next tutorial we are gonna look
at tree
controls, so join me again then and until
next time, happy coding.
[SOUND]