Hello this is John from
caveofprogramming.com.
And in this tutorial we're gonna start
looking
at the very interesting and quite complex
JTree component.
So in a moment, if I run this program,
what it looks like is this.
And I've got this tab pane here.
And I can just paste stuff in this table.
And I'm going to start working now on this
messages tab.
And this is going to have like a tree here
that's going to allow us to select
different message servers.
And then we're going to have a list of
messages for all the servers selected.
And then at the bottom we're going to have
actual message text.
So to start with, I'm going to create a
panel to put my tree in here.
So let's go to GUI, the GUI package, and
say New Class.
And I'll make this a I'll call this
Message Panel, Message
Panel, and this is gonna extend j panel,
like this.
And add the imports there and I'm just
gonna
add, I'm gonna go to my, let's save that.
I'm gonna go to my main frame here and
let's create a private message panel.
Message panel.
Call it lowercase m.
And before I add this before I create the
tree the type pane, and get the types to
work, and up here, I want to create a
message panel, so message panel equals new
message panel.
And I'm just going to add this to the
type instead of this text panel, so
message panel here.
Now in the message panel, I'm gonna start
with, I'm
just gonna create a tree, so you can see
the tree.
So I'll say public message panel, give it
a constructor.
Let's set a layout here.
Let's just use, for the moment, I'm just
gonna
use a new border layout that's gonna
change later on.
And I'm gonna give messagePanel a instance
of JTree.
So private JTree tree.
And let's call that server tree.
Cuz this is going to be like a
tree of different message servers that you
can select.
And then the constructor here, I'll create
a new, I'll say server tree
equals new JTree like this.
And down here, I'll add this tree.
For the moment that's the onle component
in the message panel.
So I'll say add.
Now when you add a tree, to a panel or
whatever you almost
always wanna wrapped it in a JScroll pane,
in fact let's say we always do.
So let's say, yeah, add new JScroll pane.
I'm not sure if it even works properly
without this scroll pane so let's set that
in.
Server tree.
And let's set that up BorderLayout.center.
Add the imports and then let's have a look
at.
Well that's not gonna look like anything
at the
moment, because I've not added any nodes
to the tree.
In fact, well, actually I'm quite
surprised.
I've never tried this before, but
apparently this is the fault j tree.
And that's what it looks.
But we're gonna change that now.
And, so to, to create a tree you need
to create a Basically a tree consists of
leaves and
nodes and all the leaves and all the nodes
are all default mutable tree node, I think
it's called.
So all these, this is a node, this is a
node, this is anode which is a leaf as
well.
And they're all default mutable tree
nodes.
So we need to create the hierarchy.
And I'm gonna create a private method here
that returns a default mutable tree node.
mutableTreeNode.
I hope I've got that name right.
And I'm going to call this createTree.
Like that.
Let's add the brackets on there at the
input.
Is ticket right name so that's good.
And I'm gonna say here tab new JTree.
I'm gonna say in here createTree.
And here I'm gonna create a
DefaultMutableTreeNode which I'll call top
or you could call it Root.
And I'll set that equal to a new
DefaultMutableTreeNode.
And let's give that some text in a
constructor.
Let's say service.
And under here, let's create a hierarchy
which has two branches underneath the top.
So I'll say I'm getting sick of typing
that so I'll copy it.
And say Branch1 equals new
DefaultMutableTreeNode and let's set that
equal to USA.
And this is gonna be service in the USA.
And I'll have the same thing again so
let's just copy that and we'll have this.
We'll make this service for the UK and
I'll call it Branch2.
Now to Branch1, I"m gonna say Branch
one.add.
In fact, I'm going to create some under
here.
Let's create some leaves.
So these are going to be the tips of the
branches, so to speak.
So let's say DefaultMutableTreeNode, leaf
conserver1 equals new
DefaultMutableTreeNode.
And let's call that, let's name that
London.
Oh, it's in the USA so let's call it New
York.
And I'm going to repeat this several
times.
Let's have a couple for the USA, let's
say.
So let's have New York let's have Boston,
and also let's have Los Angeles here.
So, Los Angeles.
And call it server1, server2, server3.
And we'll have the same for the UK.
Servers here.
So, we just have a couple there.
So server, call that four and five, and
let's
make this London and let's make this
Edinburgh.
Okay, so now I'm gonna add, I'm gonna, I'm
gonna
add this service, the USA service to the
to branch1 here.
So I'll say branch1.add and then server1.
And let's repeat that through the service.
So I'm building a hierarchical structure
here.
So two and three.
And then let's go to branch2 here.
That's my UK one.
I'll say branch2.add and server4.
And of course you could build up this
structure
from data retrieved from a data base or
something.
But here I'm just going to do it kind of
by hand.
Make the data by hand and show you how it
works.
So let's say top.add and I'll say branch1.
Yeah branch1.
And top.add.
I probably should have called that
location1, location2.
It doesn't matter.
Branch2.
Okay, and now finally we return the top
mutable tree node from createTree.
So you see the strategy is to build up
default
mutable tree nodes and to add them to each
other,
add them to each other and add in the kind
of structure that you need to build up
your tree.
And the lower ones will be leaves of
course.
So now that I've done that let me just
ponder what I've done with this.
Why am I getting an error?
I've probably got a, oh yeah, I've
actually put this in the wrong place.
This is outside the class.
Let's cut that and put it in the right
place.
Ctrl+Shift+F to format a bit.
That always helps.
And so now, so when I create my tree, I
pass in the route note.
[UNKNOWN] the other notes to the route
note in the right structure.
And I add in my tree t the panel wrapped
in the scroll pane.
I'm just using bod layout, yeah, because
I'm just
starting it, it's the only component for
the moment.
And now if I run that, with a bit of luck,
see we've got this tree with servers.
And we've got USA New York, Boston, Los
Angeles and two UK servers there.
So that's it for this tutorial.
In the next tutorial, we're gonna look
at responding to selection events in the
tree.
So join me again then and until next time,
happy coding.