Hello, this is John from
caveofprogramming.com, and in this
tutorial we're gonna look at responding to
tree selection events.
Now one thing I'm gonna do here is, at the
moment in my tree here.
I can Shift+Click to select, or Ctrl+click
to select more than one tree node, and
responding to tree selection events
only makes sense, if you can only select
one node at a time.
And for that reason I'm gonna select the
selection mode on the tree here.
I'm gonna say server tree is the name of
my JTree component .getTreeSelectionModel.
getTreeSelection, .getSelectionModel,
actually .getSelectionModel, and
setSelectionMode.
I'm gonna ask that static constant from
the class,
TreeSelectionModel there and I'm gonna
set, and that's,
I'm gonna used that constant
SINGLE_TREE_SELECTION.
So once it's doing is it's quite complex.
So I've got the selection model,
and called getSetSelectionMode on the
selection model.
And then pass that tree selection model,
that SINGLE_TREE_SELECTION.
And what that does is now, if I look at
my tree I'm holding down Ctrl here, but I
can only
select one node at a time, and that's what
I
want, because otherwise what I'm about to
do won't make sense.
And later on, we'll look at, a much
more flexible way of dealing with tree
selection.
But for now, I'm gonna to say now, we're
going to ask to serverTree,
I'm gonna to say addSelection, actually I
think it's that
TreeSelectionListener part about it, and
let's add a semicolon in there.
And here I could make
MessagePanel implement
TreeSelectionListener but instead
I'll just use an anonymous parse here I'll
say, new TreeSelectionListener.
Round brackets, Scala parenthesis and
implement the missing methods here.
And, this will be called every time
someone selects a node in the tree.
And, when you do select a node in a tree,
I'll say ServerTree,
that's my JTree,
ServerTree.getLastSelectedPathComponent.
And so I have to select, set this to
single tree selection
cuz otherwise there's not gonna be one
unique get last selected path component.
And that component is gonna be a
DefaultMutableTreeNode, so it's actually
gonna return an object.
Because I've only added
DefaultMutableTreeNode into my tree.
So it's gotta be a DefaultMutableTreeNode.
So set that equal to, see this returns a
object, i'm
gonna cast it to default mutable tree node
here.
Because I know that's what it will
actually be,
cuz that's what my is tree made up of.
And when I've done that I can say
nodes.GetUserObject, user object.
And you might wonder what the user object
is, and the answer is, it's
whatever you passed the constructor of
DefaultMutableTreeNode,
and in this case my user object strings.
So I can say string, userObject equals,
cast it to String, node.getUserObject.
And actually, let's not see it's going to
be a string, let's just say
Objust userObject, this maybe more
eloquent, equals node.getUserObject.
And then, all I'm going to do here is sys
out on the user OBJECT.
So now if I run this, and I go to my tree,
and I select something, select
service, you can see it's, it's got the
text service down here, USA, UK.
And if I expand those I can click on these
individual ones
and now the console is getting the string
associated with the, nodes.
so, Now that's all very well, but it's not
terribly flexible.
And, and for that reason, in the next
tutorial
we're going to look at associating data
with tree nodes.
So we're gonna look more closely at these
user objects.
So join me again then, and until next
time, happy coding.
[BLANK_AUDIO]