Hi there.
This is John from caveofprogramming.com.
Welcome back and in this tutorial we're
gonna
look at associating data with with tree
notes.
So so far in this series of tutorials
we've got this application.
That at the moment it has a tree in it, in
one of the tabs.
And in a moment, if I, if I go to this
tree and click some of the nodes, we can
get the text back that was set for that
particular node.
Now that's not really hugely useful
because you might wanna change the text on
a node but without actually changing the
kind of intrinsic meaning of the node.
So usually, if you have some text on the
node that says, well, in
this case New York, you probably want that
to have an ID that doesn't change.
And then if you feel like changing it
sometime to say, you
know, New York hyphen New York state or
something, I don't know.
Then you, you wouldn't want that to screw
up your application just cuz you'd changed
the text.
So what you usually wanna do is you wanna
have an ID, you
wanna have some user data that's
associated with each leaf in you tree.
And that's what we're gonna look at here.
So, I'm gonna go to my, my tree, panel,
my,
it's actually called message panel here,
and I'm gonna create a
little object here, class that I can use
to store
data that's associated Dated with each,
leaf, or, or each node.
And, so I'll call that class, let's call
it class node info.
In fact let's call it, because these are
supposed to be server's, in my nodes.
So let's call it server, info.
This is gonna be pretty simple.
And i'm gonna give it a private string
name and a private int ID just for the
moment.
And let's give it a constructor that
allows you to set the set the name and the
ID, so server info string name and int id.
And I'll say this start name equals name
and this dot id equals id.
And I'm gonna also go and give it a two
string method.
That's [UNKNOWN] and get method.
Which is I see is public int gets ID, and
that's the scanner, return the ID, and
that's scanner, this is
important, the two stream methods, so I
want to say public streaming to
string, just kinda make that return the
main here.
And this is what's gonna actually display
in my tree.
so, now, when I create the tree, I'm
cre, I'm building our default mutable tree
nodes.
I'm actually building it down here, and
I'm passing to each default mutable tree
node.
A user object, which so far, is just in a
stream.
But what I can do is financial service, I
can pass a
new server info object using the class
that I've just created.
Let's give New York an ID of zero.
And I'll copy this.
Paste in wherever I need it.
So here, here
here, and here.
So notice I'm only setting these object to
be serving for object on the actual
leaves.
Because I I might decide I want some kind
of object associated with the countries.
The branches in this case.
But then again I might not.
In this case I don't.
So I'm just gonna set surfing for objects,
user objects on the actual leaves.
So I've got New York, Boston, I've got Los
Angeles
London, Edinborough, and I need, I need
IDs as well.
So let's make Boston one, Los Angeles two.
And these will probably in the real world,
come from database, of course.
And let's set that equal to.
Four, that looks good.
And now, I think this is going to pretty
much work
as before, because when someone selects a
leaf, it gets the
user object, and then go to [UNKNOWN] out
on it, which
is going to invoke my two string method
and user object.
So if I look at the tree it renders the
same as before.
And if I select something, I get the same
text as before.
But as a matter of fact the, the leaves
are actually user object.
They're actually these server info objects
now and not strings.
So, every note has a user object
associated with it.
You pass that user object in when you call
the constructor.
When you constructor default mutable tree
note by this.
So this is the user object.
Before I used strings, now I'm using these
server info objects.
Objects, just for the leaps, now what I
can do is, when I respond to an,
like, a tree selection event, I could say
if user object
instance of sever info.
Which is the class I just made.
Then I could say server info.
I could cast the user object to a server
info user object.
Like this.
Let's cast it.
And then I can call the method getID.
Like that.
And say int ID equals call the ID method
and I could return
instead of doing sysout on the user object
I could like say sysout.
And got, let's say, got user object with
ID
plus ID.
So, just, just to show you that I'm really
gonna use object for leaves.
So, for the, makes no difference for the
nodes, cuz they're still strings.
They're strings.
But if I look at the leaves, that's
actually
a user object, and I'm getting my IDs back
now.
And this, this, the text up here is under
user.
Is this stuff here.
So I could say, ID plus name like that.
If I return the ID in the two
string method, instead of doing this, for
example.
Let's have a look at this actually and
that will, if I now run this.
So, again, when I select the branches,
then it sends before.
But if I go, and I select the nodes.
Well, selecting them will print them out
using the two string method.
And also, the two string method is also
used
to display the actual leaf, as you can
see.
So I've the ID and the leaf.
But now, for the moment, I'm gonna change
that back to
how it was, cuz I just wanna return the
name there.
And in the next tutorial well, if, in, in
a future tutorial, we're
actually gonna look soon at how using
these eavesdrop checks, so you can store
the state of a leaf and you can have, you
can turn the
leaf into a chat box that you can click on
and off for example.
But in the next tutorial we're gonna look
at using custom renderers for your leaves,
and we're gonna render these leave's in a
different way other than using this
this kind of default icon with a string.
So we're gonna change that and have our
own renderer for the leaf.
So join me again for next time, and until
then, happy coding.