Hello, this is John from
caveofprogramming.com.
And in this tutorial, we're gonna look at
tree icons and changing them.
So I've got this tree here, and there are
actually three kinds of icon, icons on
this tree.
There are the icons that represent open
nodes, like this one.
And the icons that represent closed nodes
like this
one, which are actually the same in this
tree.
And there are the icons that represent
leaves, like these paper icons here.
And I'm gonna change all of those.
So I'm gonna look at, I'm gonna use the
graphics from the Java
look and feel Sun graphics repository jar
that we've used previously for tool bar.
And I've unset that here and I'm gonna use
these three components.
I'm gonna use Server 16 for the leaf,
because my
notes are supposed to set kind of a
message service here.
And I'll use the web component, add 16.gif
with a plus sign on
it for the closed modes and the web
components 16 for the open modes.
So let's select those, and let's drag
them.
Crtl + Select.
Let's drag them into my images package
now.
And now to load these images, I'm gonna
use a
little convenience message, method, that I
created for my toolbar here.
Because the toolbar has got a great image
icon.
And that just, gets results and loads the
image, and return to URL.
And then up at this error message that the
URL is null.
Which is really the main purpose of this,
rather
than doing it all in one line, as I could.
And then it creates an image icon with
that URL which just returns the icon.
And I'm just gonna cut that from there,
from the toolbar class,
and I'm gonna go to my utils class where I
implemented this.
Get file extension.
That's a paste in there.
I'm gonna make it public static, and then
since we can't
do get class, and static method, I'm just
going to do systems.getClass.
That'll do the trick, or it should do
anyway.
System.getClass.
Let's have a look,
that should be fine, let's try
system.getResults.
Actually I don't, I don't know why
system.getClass wouldn't work.
Let's try system.getClass, system.class,
let's try system.class.
Work this out in the end.
All we need is a reference to a class.
that, yeah, there we go.
So, this does the trick,
system.class.getResults.
GetResults is a method of the class,
class, so I just needed a class there.
I suppose I could use image icon.class,
but it
doesn't matter, okay, let's leave that,
that does the trick.
And if I run this.
after, yeah, this change the toolbar now,
to use that method.
So I need to go to, instead of saying just
create icons now utils and create icon,
and utils.create icon.
Lets just run that.
To check that I've haven't got anything
screwed up.
And so I've still got icons on the
toolbar, so that's good.
And now in my message panel, where I
create that tree.
I'm gonna, on the tree, I, I'm gonna
first, create a private,
default tree cell renderer,
DefaultTreeCellRenderer.
And I'll call that treeRenderer, let's
call that.
It's actually treeCellRenderer I suppose
strictly speaking.
And here before I create the
tree, I say treeRenderer equals new
DefaultTreeCellRenderer.
And the advantage of doing that is later
on I can say
serverTree, after I've created the
j-tree.set CellRenderor.
Here we go, and I can set that to my
treeRenderor, and a
tree, the tree cell rederor, actually I
think I will call this treeCellRenderor.
Because it's confusing calling it a tree
renderor when it's really a tree cell
renderor.
The treeCellRenderer, the
DefaultTreeCellRenderer is what
normally renders your tree nodes and
leaves.
So if I run that, it's not gonna be any
different from before, hopefully.
There we go.
But now what I can do is I can say
I can say I can set the icons using my
treeCellRenderer.
So I say treeCellRenderer, and let's do,
for starts, set,
and, whoops, setLeafIcon, and then I can
use my utils.
Get.CreateIcon and pass in the path there.
Which is gonna be /images/ and as long as
these images are somewhere
on the class path and in images sub
folder, is gonna be good.
And I set that to server16.gif, then we'll
run that, we'll take a look at it.
So, now in my tree, I've got this server
icon, which is rather nice.
And I can also say treeCellRenderer.set,
OpenIcon.
And for that I'm gonna use it's gonna look
almost
the same as this actually, let's just copy
that line there.
And I'm going to set that to,
webComponent16.gif,
so, let's make that webComponent16.gif.
And if I run that, let's check that that
works.
So, there we go, that's rather nice.
and, I'm also going to, so this
represents, opened
kinda node and closed nodes is still like
that.
And I'm also gonna set the close nodes, as
well, so now I command those.
Let's say setCloseIcon, setCloseIcon.
There we go, get into that bracket.
And, on this set up to
webComponentadd16.gif,
and if I run that now with a bit of luck,
and go to my tree and there we are.
Can expand these nodes and here are my
servers.
And now in the next tutorial we're gonna
be customizing these leaves completely.
So instead of having like the server icons
there, though they do look rather nice.
We're gonna look at how you can make those
look how you can use your own component.
And and finally this is gonna be step
towards having our own editors in there.
So that we can tick and untick these
components.
So next tutorial we'll change these leaves
to be rendered by a completely custom
component.
So join me again then and until next time,
happy coding.
[SOUND]