Hello, this is John from
caveofprogramming.com.
And in this tutorial we're gonna use at,
we're gonna look at using custom
components as tree
cell leaf renders and in fact we're gonna
use boxes as the leaf renderer in a tree.
So at the moment we've got this tree, and
the
leaves render just using this little icon
and some text.
And I'm gonna change that into a check,
check box with some text.
And now the way trees work and the way
many swing components work, is
that displaying the component is different
to editing it.
So to display the component you use a
renderer and to edit the volume of the
component
you use an editor and in this component,
in
this tutorial we're just gonna look at the
renderer.
So we're gonna look at displaying these
nodes using check boxes but
you won't actually be able to all to the
value of them here.
And in the next tutorial we're going to
look at editors that
actually allow you to edit the values of
these of these leaves.
But for the moment let's imagine that each
of these nodes, each of these servers.
That these icons represent, has a, kind of
on or off status.
So it can be, well, selected or
de-selected.
And we're gonna just work on representing
that using check boxes.
And you'll be able to apply this to you,
you'll see how flexible this is
and although I'm gonna use check boxes
in this tutorial, you really could use
anything.
You could make up your own crazy component
to use as the leaf renderer in a tree.
So let's go to, oh let's see.
Where did I put it?
Message Panel.
And the first thing I'm gonna do is I've
got this server info user object which
stores, it stores the values for the leaf
nodes.
And at the moment it's just storing an ID
and a name.
But I'm gonna make that store a value
which I'm gonna call let's call it,
I don't know whether to call it Selected
or not because, you see,
when you've got tree you can select leaf
nodes here.
And we're gonna have a notional selection
that's slightly different it's gonna
be whether your gonna be able to
[INAUDIBLE] these on or off ultimately.
So maybe let's, let's call this value
checked.
So let's say that a server can be checked
or not checked
and let's here a private Boolean checked,
okay?
And I'm gonna allow, I'm gonna make it
that in
the constructor, it sets up a default
value for chat.
So we're going to have here, Boolean,
Boolean hecked.
And here let's say this.checked equals
checked like this.
And we'll have a get checked method, so
public
Boolean gets checked or could maybe call
it is checked.
And that's just gonna return checked value
there, and
that's supposed to have a set method to
public.
I could use the ID, ID to implement these
methods, but sometimes I feel it's
almost quicker to do it by hand and then
this dot checked equals checked.
Okay, and so that's, that.
And so now this server can store checked
or not checked.
And let's look at where we're, where we
are creating the tree nodes, down here.
So, right here, we're, we're, we're using,
we're
creating these default beautiful tree
nodes and we're passing
server info objects and now that subs some
of
these checked, by default, and some of
them not.
Just clicks, just to see how it looks.
So let's format the codes.
So let's have this, maybe, checked.
And, in the UK, let's have, let's have
London false.
Let's have Edinburgh true.
Okay.
Now at the moment, I'm using a default
tree style renderer there.
And I'm, I'm calling set cell render on my
tree.
And I'm using this default tree cell
renderer.
And what I'm gonna do is I'm gonna create
a new class for rendering tree nodes.
And I coud create a class here.
But I think what I'll do, I think I'll
create a new class here.
So I'll say, new class.
And let's call this
serverTreeCellRenderer.
And let's make that implement
treeCellRenderer.
This is gonna implement the
treeCellRenderer
interface and not treeCellEditor.
Okay.
So just this one.
Not quite sure what's going on here.
There we go.
Okay.
Click Finish.
And now, so the tree surrenderer
component, all
it as to do is basically return, a
component
when when get tree surrender component is
caught by
the tree, this has to return an
appropriate, component.
And whoops, these arguments unfortunately
are not well named.
So let's just go here to let's go to
Google.
And let's look up tree cell renderer.
In fact, I probably could do this in
Eclipse.
And so, if I go here and here and go press
F2 to get the focus on this health thing.
And it's not being very helpful, okay.
I'll try Google, so, treeCellRenderer.
And,
I go to the Java platform six it's close
enough.
And now here we've got the names of the,
the things that are
actually the the actual names of the
arguments, so lets just copy those.
Cuz that will be more informative than
these default values here, let's paste
those in.
There we go, do Ctrl+Shift+F to form that,
and all of
these have pretty intuitive meaning, so
tree is the tree itself.
Object value this is actually the user
object.
So it's gonna be our it's gonna be our
node.
So objects in this case because we've put
note
info's into the default multiple tree
nodes, sorry server info objects
selected tells you whether that the, the
tree node is
selected by the user, expanded where it's
expanded or not.
Leaf, whether it's a leaf or not.
Row, or the different nodes and the leaves
in the table are
actually numbered, with a row number,
we're not going to use that.
And has focus, whether it has focus or
not.
Now the first thing I'm going to do here
is,
I'm gonna give this a private J check box,
check box.
And let's give it constructor as well.
Add the input for the check box there.
And I'll give this a public server tree
cell renderer constructor.
And in the constructor I can say check box
equals new Jcheck box, like that.
And, what I can also do, this check box is
gonna be used for rendering the leaves.
I also need to do something for rendering
the non leaf nodes
I wannna use basically what I'm currently
using to render those nodes.
So the way I am gonna handle that is I'll
click Private.
Default treeCellRenderer here and this is
the class we've already used.
And I'll call this, actually let's call
this LeafRenderer and let's call this
nonLeafRenderer.
And then sillyLeafRenderer I set to a,
I'll set to a chat box here.
We'll use that for rendering leaves.
And for non leaves, I'll say
non relief rendered, equals new default
treeCellRenderer.
And what I can do is I can already set the
icons.
So at the moment I've got code that's
setting the icons for my treeCellRenderer.
And so I can cut those from here now.
And go into my constructor, and just set
these icons here on my non leaf renderer.
So let's paste non leaf renderer there, in
there, like that.
And now I can say right here so if leaf,
so I've got this Boolean leaf parameter.
It's asking whether the tree is calling
this method to render a leaf or not.
And if, if we have got a leaf I can say
return leafRenderer.
And so I'm just returning my chat box as
the component that
I want to use, else if it's not a leaf,
return nonLeafRenderer.
Get and retrieve cell, get tree cell,
render a
component, and that's gonna just take all
the arguments
and that, we've got here, so this is the
default implementation in default trees
for render this method.
And I say if I got a leaf, I'm going to
return my own special component.
And if I don't, I'm going to return
whatever default we saw render here would
return.
Let's save that and see how it looks.
I've got an error there for some reason
cell cannot be resolved.
So yeah, it's these arguments of course
have to match these and that's selected.
And I think the rest are okay.
So now let's use this server
treeCellRenderer that I've written.
So, I'm gonna say treeCellRenderer equals
new server treeCellRender, like this.
I'm using the thing I just created.
And, I need to also change the type the
of the variable from default
treeCellRender.
Okay, and now I can use that as a
CellRender in my in my tree.
And let's, let's just have a look see what
that looks like.
It's not finished yet, but if I go to
Messages
here, and I expand it, I've got check
boxes there and
they've got no text in them and they're
not selected or
de-selected, and the color is all wrong,
but we're getting there.
So, that the next step now is, if I've got
a leaf I can
get my user object and from the default
mutable tree node.
And, actually, I made a little mistake
earlier on.
Cuz I said that this was the user object
value, and it's not.
It's actually the default mutable tree
node, which,
which, has a reference to your user object
values.
So what we actually have to do is, I can
say, if leaf DefaultMutableTreeNode
node equals and I can cast this value to a
defaultMutableTreeNode because I know that
my
tree is made up of defaultMutableTreeNodes
so that is what that is going to be in
every case.
And having done that, I can then say,
well my user objects are these server info
objects.
So I created this server info class back
here
and I can say server info, mode info
let's call that, equals server info and I,
I can say value, so I note.get user
object.
So this is the default multiple tree node,
because that's what my
trees made a path, and I once I cast it to
a default
multiple tree node I can use that to get
the user object
which I passed to the constructors
of the DefaultMutableTreeNodes when I
created them.
So now I can get off like, the text for
example.
So I can say
string.
Let's say string text.
no, let's not do that, it's not necessary.
I can say, check box.
What do I call it?
Call it leaf renderer.
So now I wanna basically set the text and
the selected status of this leaf
renderer, which is actually a chat box,
using the information in my node info
object.
So I can say leafrenderer.settext.
And, I can pass in there nodeinfo.2string,
like that because
that's 40 times the text that I want to
display.
And to display whether it's selected
or not, I can say,
leafrenderer.setslectednodeinfo.
And use my is selected method, is checked
already, mine is checked method that I
implemented earlier.
And we're gonna be getting there now.
So now if I go to my tree, you've got
check boxes in there and they're checked.
According to whether I set the check
status to,
to a fault and load so, and the severing
[INAUDIBLE] object that I've created, and
in the next
tutorial we're gonna [INAUDIBLE] but right
now they're not editable.
Right now they, they do not allow you to
edit them, as you can see.
Now, one thing of note is that they look a
little
bit ugly because the color's all wrong,
and we're gonna fix that.
Now, that's probably gonna be the last
thing that we do in this tutorial.
And I'm gonna get the colors in the
constructor
that I need to color the chatboxes
appropriately, and
I could just send them to white or gray
or whatever I feel like, but I'm going to
say.
UImanager.get
and set the import
for that and
UIManager.getColor.
This is being a little bit temperamental.
UIManager cannot be resolved.
Let's, try, getting little dots.
Let's try, let's try something like that.
And then I have to import, Ctrl+Shift+O.
And did it work?
Okay upper class.
I'm just trying to get it to add that
import and for some reason.
It doesn't want to u, I think it's
possibly done it.
Okay, get's call, yeah, okay, good, gets
color, and
I wanna get the color that the tree
normally uses
for the foreground of a text in its leaf.
And to do that, I can parse in string
here, tree.set.text.foreground.
Think that's right.
That's gonna return a it's gonna return a
colored
object so, up here I can have let's say
let's have some colors.
Yes, I'll say private color send text.
As our text foreground, foreground and I'm
gonna copy that.
I'm gonna have four of these.
And text background, and we're
gonna have selectionForeground.
And we're gonna have selectionBackground
as well.
So, selectionBackground and let's have.
At the import for the color there.
And I'm gonna say text foreground equals
Hueymanagergetcolortree.text foreground,
so Hueymanagers.
Stores all the colors of the different
parts of the user interface.
And you've got to pass in these strings,
they're like keys to the colors that you
need.
And let's say textBackground and we'll
also have
selectionForeground and
selectionBackground and
if I've got this right now, I can just
copy those and paste them in there, and
paste this in here.
And
now, I just need to say end here.
So before we turn in this, this check box,
I need to set the color up there
appropriately.
I need to say, if selected then we wanna
say
leaf renderer.set foreground.
And selection foreground and
leaf render.set background.
Selection background and it's pretty
similar, if it's not selected I'll say
leaf renderer.setfullgroundsetbackground
and I'll have
text foreground and text background.
And now, if if I run my, tree,
from this [UNKNOWN] tree you can see that
when I
select it, it it looks selected.
And when I deselect it, it doesn't.
But we can't edit these yet.
And that's the next tutorial.
And the next tutorial will gonna look at
word mainly these check boxes, editable.
And one, one thing that I probably should
explain at little bit
here in case you get confused, cuz it's
quite confusing, this stuff.
There's there's only ever gonna be one
check box here,
there isn't one check box for every leaf
in a tree.
There's just one check box for all of
them,
and before we return a check box using
this
rederer you have to set it up
appropriately, set
the check box to be selected or not
selected.
Set the text on it and so on.
And that's what makes it work.
So there's only ever one check box and
you're just
customizing it to display different
values, one after the other.
Different leaves.
Okay, so, in the next tutorial, we're
gonna look at making these values
editable.
So join me, join me then, and until next
time, happy coding.
[SOUND]