Hello, this is John from [UNKNOWN]
programming.com, and in this tutorial,
we're going to look at creating editors
for your tree cells.
So, in a moment, we've got this
application,
and checkboxes here in this message's
tree, so.
Whether the node has a selected status or
not.
But you can't actually check or uncheck
the nodes
and we're gonna look at that in this
tutorial.
Now I have to warn you that tree
sort editors are one of the most
complicated things.
That you can do and swing, and even when
you do them the results aren't perfect to
tell you
the truth, because your, your trees may
not be fully
be accessible by keyboard unless you do
even more work.
Nevertheless, we'll, we'll look at them
here.
And if you find this tutorial too complex
my advice
is just pretty much cuts and paste the
code and you
can always do a Google search and find a
similar code
for yourself and you might want to look at
for example.
List box editors or table cell editors,
they're a bit simpler than tree cell
editors.
But anyway, I'll do my best to make this
as simple as possible.
So, in a moment if I go to the message
here,
so I've got a I've got a tree I'm creating
and
I'm sitting a custom render on my checkbox
render on the
tree and I've called that render a server
tree, so I'll render.
[UNKNOWN], because this is supposed to be
a tree with different server locations in
it.
And I'm gonna start here by creating a new
class.
And I'm gonna call this class
ServerTreeCellEditor.
Now ServerTreeCellEditor is gonna
implement, the
It's gonna implement the server, sorry,
the tree cell
editor interface, just like the import
layer, implement.
But this tree ell editor interface has a
lot of methods
in it, and we can actually get default
implementations of them.
From the a cast called abstract cell
editor.
So I'm gonna make it extend abstract cell
editor, like this.
It's not that important.
Now if I over-ride and implement the
methods, now, you've only got two.
And I'm going to also overwrite another
very important method here.
So, I'm going to right click, go to
source, overwrite
implement methods, and I'm gonna overwrite
the is cell editable method.
Now to understand the tree cell editor,
really you've just got to get.
Get your head around these three methods.
And what happens is these are called in
sequence by the tree.
When you click on a node, first is cell
editable will be called, and if that
returns false, then that's the end of a
matter and the other two methods won't be
called.
If it returns true, to say that the cell
is editable.
What happens next is that the tree will
call, get cell editor editor component,
and that's got to return some kind of
component that allows you to edit, like a
check box for example, and get tree cell
editor component then has to fire.
A editing stopped event.
It's got to call the method, called, I
think it's called fire editing stopped.
And that's what triggered the tree to call
get cell editor volume.
And that's called retrieve the user object
value for that tree node.
Which is in this case is going to be a
server info object.
Because that's the user...
The object that we've set in the tree.
And the tree leaves.
So here we, we're creating word child to
default multiple tree nodes.
And the leaves of this server info, user
object word past load constructor.
So let's go ahead and implement that lot.
So the first thing I'm gonna do.
I'm actually gonna create an instance of
my server, tree, cell renderer here.
And the reason I'm gonna do that is
because server trees I render will give me
a
checkbox that's formatted with the right
colors to fit
into the tree, and I don't wanna have to.
Let's use that code again But I don't
wanna use the chat box associated with
server tree [UNKNOWN] either, because I've
found that if you try to use the same chat
box for both the editor and the renderer
function, you tend to get some confusion
going
on and your tree gets a bit mixed up or
you site can't make that work.
So I'm gonna call.
Call that renderer.
And in, I'm gonna give this a constructor
here.
So I'll say public ServerTreeCellEditor
like this, using Ctrl + Space
auto-complete to complete the constructor.
And in an constructor I'm gonna say,
renderer equals new.
Server tree cell renderer our path.
Now when I go into the get tree cell
editor component we'll tackle, I think
we'll tackle this first 'cause it's among,
well
it's simpler than the is cell editable
function.
I can then say here.
I can get the checkbox from the server
tree cell renderer.
So I can say
renderer.getTreeCellRendererComponent.
And if I take the argument's that's
passed.
By the tree into this function when it
calls this function and I pass
them on to keep the tree rendering
component then they will all have
appropriate values.
I'll, I'll set that focus here to true
because get
tree cell added component is not passed,
has a focused argument.
Now that's gonna return some kind of
component
such as it's going to be in this case.
Okay it's a checkbox.
So it's gonna be J CheckBox checkbox
equals and I'm gonna return that check
box.
So I'll say return check.
Box.
Now that's almost all I have to do here.
Let's see if this is selected, this is
selected and that's selected so let's make
these match.
okay, and we've got an error.
Can't convert.
So we need to cast this.
It's a J checkbox.
I know it's going to be a J checkbox
because that's what my renderer returns.
So if I look at the, the renderer that I
implemented in the last tutorial,
get, where are we, get [UNKNOWN] surrender
component,
returns a check box if it's a leaf.
Actually, oh yeah, that reminds me, I'm
only going
to [UNKNOWN] to a checkbox if it is a
leaf.
Because, if it's not a leaf, it's going to
be a string object.
Actually, let's get rid of that.
But, say object, let's call this, I don't
know, com
component equals and here I'll return
component.
So, and...
So you can see that this solitary
surrenderer is returning a check box
if leaf renderer here is a check box and
it's
returning a checkbox if we're dealing with
a leaf and if
we're not returning, if we're not, we're
not dealing with a leaf.
Turns, it calls default tree cell
renderor, that tree cell
renderor component returns thee, default
which is, I suppose a stream.
So I'm gonna get this component from it,
return the component here, and in fact
this returns the component so we can make
this component, there we go that should
work.
And now I'm gonna say if leaf, and I'm
gonna do something special here because.
And so as I say, what's gonna happen is is
that editable
will have to return true, and we'll fix
that in a minute.
And if it returns true the tree will call
getTreeCellEditorComponent.
And then the use will be able to edit the
leaf using the checkbox, cuz this will
return a checkbox.
If we have a leaf.
But, I need to tell the tree when I stop
editing, cuz if I don't do that, it will
never.
And switch parties in a renderer.
Anyone never called is, anyone never
called get celebrity value.
And get celebrity value is what you have
to get the value from when you edit.
So which is the checkbox, and return it as
a user
object which is then set in the node to
the tree.
So this will never be called, unless
I call fire stop editing or territories
here.
So let, let's do that.
Say if leaf.
And now, I, how will I know when to stop
editing?
So basically I need to cast component to a
checkbox with start.
So I say jcheckbox checkbox equals, and if
I'm
dealing with a leaf, it will be a
checkbox, so j, j.
Check box components.
I can then cast the component to checkbox.
And I'm going to say
checkbox.AddItemListener.
Like this.
And I'm going to.
Create an item listener here.
So let's say item listener.
Item listener is an interface, and if I
add an item listener to the check box,
that item listener is gonna be invoked
whenever
I tick or untick the tech, the checkbox.
So let's say item listener.
Item listener equals new item listener so
although it's an interface, if I do new
item listener and then open a parenthesis
like
this, I can implement an anonymous class
here.
So I'll say add an implemented methods and
item list just has this item state
changed.
Which is called whenever you tick or
untick the checkbox.
So if the items state changes on the check
box, after that I can say okay, it's
changed.
That means it's been ticked or unticked.
Now we can go back to using a renderer.
And the tree can get the value from a
checkbox, so here, I call fire, editing
/u, and it's very very important to do
this step, or this stuff just won't work.
And I add the item list to the check box,
and
another thing I'm going to do is I'm
adding an item.
List into a chat box, but I'm only using
one chat box here.
It's the chat box that belongs to this
server tree
cell renderer, 'cause I'm getting the chat
box from that.
So it's just one chat box that I'm using.
I don't wanna keep adding item lists to it
all the time.
So what I'll do is I will.
Remove the item listener and the item
state changed.
So here I'll say check, actually I'll say,
yeah, checkbox.remove, remove item
listener.
And then I can either pass in the item
listener, or I can just pass in this.
They're equivalent.
Cuz this here will refer the anonymous
class.
And because I can't refer to checkbox here
because it's a local variable at the
moment, what
I'll do is I'll make it an instance
variable
so let's copy that and get rid of this.
And up here, I'll say private JCheckBox
[SOUND]
That's the [UNKNOWN] that it's a bit
[UNKNOWN].
But unfortunately, the worst of the
complication here is not yet over.
now, is cell editable is pretty tricky.
And that accepts a, event object, I'll
call event here.
And I'll get rid of the contents over
here.
And now what we need to do [UNKNOWN] in
cell editable, is.
We need to have a look and see what
what actual branch your [UNKNOWN] the tree
or leaf,
the user has clicked on and need to say
yes.
[UNKNOWN] oh no we don't and if you don't.
Do this step property if you wish to
return the trivia.
Then you'll have problems with the
rendering of your tree
because you'll be trying to every
[UNKNOWN] which is [UNKNOWN].
And now, It's anybody seen.
And implementation of this that I consider
completely satisfactory.
And and I'm gonna, do something here,
which seems
to be the, the usual way to do it.
Where I'm going to look at mouse events,
and see what users
click on last, because that's what you
usually do in a chat box.
And, although the tree.
Has a a get less, getLast,
getLastPassComponent method or something
like that.
And that somehow lags and it doesn't give
you the right component that's just been
selected.
And we really need here the component
that's just been selected.
And this is the only way to do it that I
know of that I'm going to show you.
But if you wanted to make your tree
keyboard accessible I think you'd
probably have to do a bit more work here
than we're going to do.
But anyway.
I'll leave that as an exercise for you.
So, the first thing to do there, is I need
to say
if, if event is an instance of
mouse.event, because if someone clicks.
On a, a mode.
Then, we will receive here, an instant of
mass event.
And I wanna say, if it's not, an instance
of mass event, then forget about it,
return false.
If it is an instance of mass event, of
course we
can copy it, and say mass event, so it
[UNKNOWN] it.
Mouse event mouse event equals cast to a
mouse event event.
Now the the next step here.
Is, I need to use a method of the tree
that gets me the path, the component
path which is a sequence of branches that
lead down to this leaf if it is a leaf.
And fall the location of the mouse click.
So I can get the tree.
By saying event dot get source.
Because the source of this event, is, my J
tree.
So you say J, tree.
Tree equals [UNKNOWN]
to a J tree, event dot get source.
And having done that, I can then say.
And tree dot get a path for location and I
can
pass in the coordinates to this location
supplied by a mouse event and that will
get me the path in terms of the sequence
of branches that leads
and there the users actually collect on
basically, so here I'll say mouse...
Events dot get x.
There
we go, and mouse event dot get y.
Like, s was my y.
There we go.
And.
That returns a tree path object.
So TreePath path =, and now I just wanna
check that it's probably worth checking.
I think it could potentially be null, but
I'm not sure, so we want to say.
Say if path equals null then return false
because if it's
null then then we'll just say no you can't
edit it.
And okay.
Now, from the path, we can say
path.getLastPathComponent and
that gets us the last component in the
path which will be our leaf.
I do.
In this case a default mutable tree node
object, and it returns it as an object.
So let's say object, last, component
equals get last path component.
So this is, this is, if you worked on the
branch it's the last path component.
It's the leaf itself.
And I'm going to say if last component
equals null, but I'm not sure
if it can be null, but best safe than
sorry, return false, and if we
have now got a last path component, then
we know since the
tree is built up in this case, our default
mutual tree nodes, so
we can call that tree node, and set that
equal to.
Cast, default mutable tree node, to last
component.
Now, we're almost there now, because now I
can find out if this is a leaf or not.
I can say if tree not.is leaf.
Well let's actually, since I'm returning
faults here, let's say if
not tree is leave or I can say if tree is
leaf equals
false then return false.
And right now, I think why don't we just
return tree is leaf?
So if it's a leaf, we want to say you can
edit it.
And if it isn't, you want to say no you
don't.
And you could, you could here, I could
here use the nested if statement and
a lot of a lot of code that you'll find
floating around the internet does that.
But I quite like the, The method of going
through and
eliminating possibilities and saying okay,
[UNKNOWN] return false, okay return false.
And finally if you get to the end.
If everything matches you return true.
[UNKNOWN] extra nesting in your code which
I personally like.
And that's the implementation of
[UNKNOWN].
So much complicated.
So remember, the tree will ask itself /u
it
self-editable, whether it can edit tree
node or not.
if this returns false, nothing else will
happen, instead, if it returns true,
then, it will then call /u.
A component to get the editor for that
node.
And then you'll use your c component and
he or she will click on it hopefully.
And once it's been clicked on, this will
call fire editing stopped will tell
the tree to stop using to stop using the
editor and start using a renderer again.
And before it does that, it will call get
cell editor values.
Get cell editor value will only be called
if file editing stops.
Is, is run here to tell the tree to stop
using the editor.
So you must call that, it's important.
Now if end gets the value.
Here.
What we wanna do is we re, return a server
info object, and really we need the server
info object that we that is, corresponds
to the node that we are editing here.
So what I'm gonna do is.
I'm gonna create here a private server
info, info
and in here so if I've got a leaf, I'm
gonna
say okay, let's have a look at default
multiple tree node.
Which is this, it's this object here.
So I can say default, mutable tree note,
tree
note equals cast default mutable tree
node.
Sorry, I think I promised you that this,
that message was finished, but I just
remembered.
This extra bit now and I'm going to cast
the value up
because these, these values are actually
the objects of trees made up of.
And we made our tree up of default mutable
tree nodes.
Now, I can say value.
So I can say treenode.getuserobjects, and
that will get us a sev info object because
when we constructed the leaf default
multiple tree
modes we passed in sev info objects we
share it with just this class I defined in
the last tutorial I think or the
tutorial before, so I'm actually I'm gonna
use
my instants method here cause I want to.
So we cache the value of that temporarily.
And I'll say info equals.
And now, yeah, I need to cast that as
well.
So to server info.
Because this returns just an object.
Now, in get [INAUDIBLE]
value which is the third of these
methods to be called I can return info but
before I do that I need to update this
info object with the latest information.
On this checkbox, so to do that I just
need to say info.
And I gave info a, a set check method.
And I'm gonna set it to check and not
checked.
And on the value of this checkbox, so
checkbox.ischecked.
I think it says checked.
Is selected.
There we go.
And finally I think we've got everything
here working.
And, and one important thing that must be
done actually is to make your tree
editable.
You've got to call.
Your J tree, set editable method,
otherwise
is editable won't even be called and none
of these methods will do anything at all.
Now let's try running that and see how it
looks.
So here's my tree and I've got these
values here but that didn't seem to work.
So let's take a look here.
And actually, in fact I forgot the other
absolutely crucial thing that you may have
noticed which is that I didn't actually
create the server tree surrender.
I'm not actually using this code at all.
So I'll say private server tree cell
sorry,
I used the renderer not the editor so.
So the tree cell editor, treeCellEditor.
And here I need to set that to a, need to
say treeCellEditor = new.
Server tri.cell editor.
I need to say here server tri.cell
editor and pass ND tri.cell editor I
think.
We are finally there now.
So if I run this now finally we've got
this
tree and you can click the values on and
off.
You can edit the nodes.
So, you can probably see from all this
that trees are, And they're
very flexible and potentially you can do
all kinds of things with them.
In fact, yeah you see at the moment I can,
I'm selecting different
modes here with up and down, the up and
down key on my keyboard.
But because N is un editable I refer to
mouse
events and I can't actually let it I'm
using the.
Keyboard, and you'd have to do more work
to do that.
And it's a lot of work digging the trees.
But if it's your job, I guess you wouldn't
mind.
But since I suspect this is as much as you
probably want to know, I'm gonna leave it
with that.
So we've got our [INAUDIBLE] tree there.
And in the next tutorial we're gonna look.
Collecting information from this tree.
And we're also going to look at detecting
when
all of these check boxes is clicked on or
off.
So, join me again then.
Until next time.
Happy coding.