Hello this is John from
caveofprogramming.com.
And in this tutorial we're gonna look at a
simple way
to retrieve data from your, from the
editors in your tree leaves.
So in the last tutorial we got this tree
working.
And it's got these editors that you can,
it's got these
check boxes in the leaves that you can
tick on and off.
In this tutorial we're just gonna look at
how you can get the data from these
editors.
And what I'm gonna do is, I've, I've
actually, since the last tutorial.
I've taken server info object and I've put
it into it's own class, because it's
used on the message panel to serve the
tree cell editor, and the tree cell
renderor, so because it's used by three
classes it makes no sense to dump it in
with this message panel class, so I've
moved that and I'm now gonna go.
Get rid of this tree selection listener
because the tree
selection listener will tell you if a node
has been
selected on the tree, but that's selected
in the sense
of basically being clicked on so that it
has the focus.
So that's now selected, and I don, I don't
care whether it's selected
or not, what I care about is whether it's
checked on the roster now.
And I only care about the leaves here,
because I don't have to have a check boxes
in, so I'm going to get rid of that and,
and I'm
actually gonna listen to a to events
on the editor because in servertry editor,
the
class I implemented in the last tutorial,
we when a
check box is being ticked or unticked, we
call fire editing stopped and that's
the event that we're gonna look for now in
message panel, because I'm gonna say.
Treecelleditor.addcelleditorlistener,
this map, and I'll add a new cell editor
listener there.
And put semicolon in here.
And add the unimplemented method there.
I'm not interested in the editing canceled
here so I'll just delete that.
But I am interested in editing stopped
here.
So that's, put a let's put, let's put this
out
in there if I can find it again, here we
go.
So, in here I'm gonna put this out just
for the moment, hello.
Now if I run my tree and nothing happens
when I click on the upper branches here.
And if I click on the check box then it
fires that event.
So it's saying hello there, [SOUND] which
is exactly what I want.
And what I'm gonna do is I'm gonna
actually use the retrieve
cell editor method that I implemented in
the last tutorial, so again
this get cell editor value method, and
that's the one I'm gonna use.
I'm gonna see tree select editor.get cell
editor value.
And, that is a server info object, so I'll
say
server info, info equals cast that to the
server info.
Cuz it returns the object.
And that's how this is word solved here.
And let's say info, which is it gonna call
it two string method.
And let's say let's say, let's have the ID
as well.
So info.getid.
And, let's then have,
an info.isChecked.
And [INAUDIBLE] plus there.
So now if I run this I can click on
messages and click, I untick New York.
It's gonna say New York, zero, which is
the idea of New York.
It's the first one, false.
If it's ticked it's true.
Try Edinburgh, which is four.
[SOUND] false true and see if it works
pretty damn well.
So, in the next tutorial, I'm gonna build
a data structure that's gonna
be, kind of a star simulated message
server, and we're gonna have
something where you can retrieve,
supposedly, messages from a server.
For using the ID's of just those servers
that we have checked in the tree and
ultimately were gonna fix
this application up, so that when you
check, check
,a check box or un-check a check box
you'll see a progress bar you
know say like getting messages or
something
and then we'll have a [INAUDIBLE] down
here,
where you can see the titles of the
messages, and then where you
can read the messages, and you wouldn't
necessarily want to do that in a
real application but I just wanna show you
something useful here with trees and
ultimately with things like threads and
program
bars, so I'm just concocting something
here.
I heard that, that's sort of plausible,
and
we're gonna simulate the actual existence
of the message
server, rather than actually doing any
socket programming
or anything like that, which is a
different topic.
Okay, so join me again next time, and
until next time, happy coding.
[SOUND]