Hello.
This is John from caveofprogramming.com.
And in this tutorial we're gonna create a
kinda, fake message
server just so I can in the next tutorial
show you
some multithreading in Swing and we can go
on to look at progress bars
So we're not gonna look at anything Swing
specific in this tutorial.
And if this doesn't interest you, then
feel free to
skip it and it won't be a problem at all.
But if you wanna kind of bit of a
workout with Java collections and
iterators then stay tuned.
And I might mention that also you can go
to caveofprogramming.com there
you can find lots of free tutorials on the
Java collections framework.
So which we're going to be using sensibly
in this tutorial.
But I won't specifically cover how this
works in depth cuz
it's kind of taken us away from suite
programming a little bit.
So I'm, I'm not gonna have like a data
model for
my message server because it's gonna be a
sort of fake message server.
I'm just gonna implement a controller, and
we're gonna sort
of pretend that this this controller is
getting data from somewhere.
Now the first thing I'm gonna do here is a
I'm gonna go to new class in the model.
And I'm gonna create a, just a very simple
class models the message.
So I'll give that a private string title
and a private string content.
So this like an email message or something
like that.
And let's right click, go to Source >
Generate Constructor using Fields.
And let's also right click > Source >
Generate Getters and Setters.
I'll Generate Getters and Setters for
content and
the title and Ctrl + Shift after format
there.
So that's my message class, install title
and contents of my message.,
and I'm gonna right click my controller
here and create a class which I'll call
Don't really know what to call it, let's
call it MessageServer, maybe.
And, MessageServer is, it's gonna have a
map of messages where the key in the map
is gonna be the server
ID and the value is gonna be a list of
messages, message objects.
So for each server, and each server has a
number, we've got zero through to four.
We're gonna have a list of messages that
we imagine in are on
the server, but in reality, they're gonna
be stored in this state structure here.
So let's call that Messages and I'll give
this a constructor, public MessageServer.
And in MessageServer, let's have imports
there, module.message type import list.
Let's say messages equals new needs a new.
Well, I can use treemap because that'll
keep
this sorted in order of ID server ID
there.
Although I'm not really sure it matters.
It's going to be server map of, well the
type
is going to be exactly the same as this
basically.
So let's copy that and round brackets
there.
So I've got a data struc-,
a data structure now that can store my
messages.
And
let's add a like two or three dummy
messages to that.
And I'm gonna add more, but I'll do that
kind of
off screen because there's no reason to
bore you with that.
So I'm gonna say let's have a list
let's call this let's call.
Well, this'll be list of messages, message
objects, and it's
just a temporary variable really, so I'll
call it list.
And set that equal to new ArrayList of
message objects.
Let's start a couple of messages to this.
So say list.add new message and the title
can be the cat is missing.
Have you seen Felix anywhere?
That should do the trick.
And let's copy that.
And I'll have a new one of those.
Not meant to copy it, let's add the import
actually for ArrayList.
Copy this, and add another one, and let's
say
see you later question mark.
Are we still meeting in the pub?
And let's then, then I can say
messages.port and I'll give it the ID of
the Washing-,
I think New York, maybe the New York
server and
the ID zero because it doesn't matter
which one it is.
I'll say messages.port and then let's add
this list in there.
So two messages for this particular server
with ID zero.
And then, I'm gonna just copy this.
Let's add a couple for server with ID one
maybe.
And let's just say
how about dinner later, and let's say
are you doing anything later, later on?
Okay.
And I'll just have one message there, and
that can be one message for.
And actually, these are ridiculous
messages because this is kind of, the
idea is it's not user specific, but it's
just, add new messages
in this application that retrieve from
somewhere, but you know, this text
doesn't actually matter, it's really just
a demo of swing widgets ultimately.
So I'm just kinda trying to make this
plausible, but it's not necessarily
going to make complete sense in terms of
what the application really does.
So so that fills up our message list.
I'm going to have another private well a
private list.
Which will be a list of messages, and I'm
going to call this Selected.
And Selected is gonna be a
array list of messages and its gonna be an
array
list of the messages on the selected
servers so the tree
is gonna allow us to select servers, or
deselect servers.
And I'm gonna have a meth-,
method here, and let's maximize the
editor, called, it's gonna be public void
set selected servers and that's gonna
accept a set of integers.
And lets save ID's, here.
Well, maybe I'll call it servers.
It's gonna be server ID's.
So you'll pass in a set of server ID's,
and then for each int-,
integer ID in servers.
Let's make that servers.
Then we'll get the list of messages from
the map here.
So I'll say if
messages.contains
key ID, then I'll say
list message Let's call this I don't know.
Server message, messages equals and from
the map,
messages I can say messages.get will get
the messages
for that server and then add them to the
selected list.
So selected.addAll.
And if I can do that in one step, I can
say, messages.getID.
And I can do, so add all, add all the
messages.
So, what I'm doing is, I'm going, for each
integer of
ID in this set, I'm getting all the
messages that are supposedly
on that server and I'm adding them to the
list of selected
messages, and before I do that I'll also
remember to do selected.clear.
So clear out the messages in the selected
list,
because we want to create a new selected
list.
Now, I'm gonna give this a let's see,
what's wrong with this, I forgot a
semi-colon.
Now, I'm gonna give this a message called
public void getMessageCount,
and that's just gonna return, return
selected.size.
So the size, the number of messages
waiting to
be downloaded so to speak, and that's
gonna be
int.
And actually, let's put a comment up here
cuz I don't want anyone running
away with the idea that this is a real
message server, which it clearly isn't.
So this is a sort of simulated message
server.
Okay.
And now I want to make it iterable, cuz I
think that would be nice.
I want to be able to say, back in well,
well, let's deal
with setting the selected messages for
start, because back in message panel
here, what I can do here, is I can
have up here a private SetInteger.
And this gonna be selected servers.
And in the constructor here, let's have
the set import and the
constructor says selected servers equals
new and let's have TreeSet.
TreeSet is sorted in my asset integer.
So that's just a set of integers and I'm
gonna add to that a couple
of server ID, so I've selectedServers.art
let's have zero.
And.
Let's have, let's have also
maybe one and maybe four, and then if I
add the TreeSet import, Ctrl+Shift+O.
Now when I create my tree nodes to
see whether they are initially selected or
not.
I'm gonna say selected sell,
selectedServers.contains and the
ID and that will return true only if ID is
currently in the selected set.
So, and let's add that to these other
servers as well.
So it's going to be one and this is gonna
be two and you can add it here.
It's going to be three.
And finally, you can add it here.
Four, Edinburgh.
And I'm gonna add and remove selected
servers from this
list, depending on whether the tree leaves
are checked or not.
Whether the checkbox is checked or not.
And so, here I'm gonna say, int-,
server ID, equals info.getID.
And this is in the, this is in that cell
editor listener response class.
So this will occur, this code will occur
here.
You might recall from the last tutorial if
someone checks a checkbox or, or if, or
not.
Or only checks it, I can say if
info.isChecked,
then we wanna add the server ID to the
list.
So selected, selectedService.addID.
Server ID.
Otherwise, we want to remove it from the
list.
And of course, since this is a set.
Since selectedService is a set, I think
it's wise.
Won't do any harm at all.
Because set will only store unique values
in any case.
Okay?
So serverID.
I think that should do the trick.
Oh, I spelled this wrong, or something.
whoops.
Didn't mean to do that, copy serverID.
Paste it there, add the semicolon and now,
we can say I can create a message server
object here.
So, here I can say, private message,
messageServer
messageServer.
And down here I can say messageServer
equals new messageServer.
And now let's say here, when someone
checks or unchecks
the tree leaf, message
server.setSelectedServers
and pass in the selected servers ID list.
And then I can say sysout
messageServer Well, I can
say, message is waiting, plus
messageServer.getMessageCam.
Okay.
And let's see if that works or not.
So I'll go to my tree here, and I'll tick
off, untick something.
I got one message waiting, I tick New
York's, and I got three waiting, I tick
Boston.
Go to Los Angeles won't make any
difference because I didn't
add any for Los Angeles, but it seems to
be working.
And now I'd like to be able to say here,
if there are
messages waiting, I'd like to be able to
say,
for message, message in message server.
Then get the message basically.
I can say here, sysout message.getTitle
just for the moment.
But the point in doing this is when I've
implemented this behavior
here, I'm gonna make this very slow, and
in the next tutorial we're
gonna look at adding multithreading to
this so that this can happen in
a separate thread and it doesn't lock up
the rest of the application.
But now for the rest of this tutorial,
which is gonna look at
implementing this behavior, so that you
can
iterate through the message server like
this.
And to do that, I need to say here,
implement iterable like this.
and, I kinda think I mentioned it already,
but there is,
there are free tutorials on
caveofprogramming.com on this kind of
stuff.
So lets do Ctrl+Shift+O and I'm gonna make
it implement
iterable templated, our messages, to our
message.
So it's gonna be something that can
iterate through
different messages, and that's, I think,
unimplemented methods there.
And I need to return a iterator here.
So to do that I'm gonna create a class
that can iterate through
my iterate very slowly through my selected
messages.
So let's let's maybe do that down here.
And, I'm gonna say, class,
message, iterator implement.
iterator, iterator.
And set the import.
And now I can add the missing methods for
that.
And I'm gonna make this, give this
constructor public MessageIterator and
that's gonna accept a list of messages to
iterate through.
So, and we'll call that messages.
And it's going to get an iterator from
this actual list which is basically going
to run.
So we'll have a private iterator,
IteratorMessage.
And I'm going to call it iterator.
And here in the constructor we'll pass it
a list of messages straight through.
And we'll just say iterator.
Iterator equals messages.iterator,
and now has next can simply
return, return iterator
iterator.hasNext.
So we are just wrapping the iterator of
the
list of messages and remove, not that I
need it,
but let's just kind of do iterator.remove.
And next it's going to do, it's going to
return iterator, iterator.next.
Next, there we go.
Next step, I'm going to put a delay in
there, here.
So I'm going to say thread.sleep to
simulate
the slow retrieval of messages from a
server somewhere.
Now let's just wrap that and I need to
catch
an exception there, so I'll just wrap that
in a try-catch.
I think that's everything so now, I can
give when this iterator message here.
Sorry, this iterator method or it is a
message, if you like.
You can say return here.
Return new message iterator and wrap the
selected list of messages.
And now, with a bit of luck my message
panel once
it gets, once you check or uncheck it tree
leaf it will
get the number of messages, and then with
the interface locked up,
which is very unsatisfactory, it's gonna
iterate very slowly through the messages.
Let's see that working.
Let's go to the message window here, and
check New York.
It's got one message from New York
retrieved at a very slow
pace, so I want to untick New York and see
it's like locked.
If I click on tabs, you know, while it's
writing through stuff, then I don't get
a whole lot of response until it finishes,
and you can see the messages appearing
here.
Now what we're gonna do in the next
tutorial is we're gonna look at using
multithreading to
run this stuff in a separate thread so it
doesn't lock up your interface while
you're retrieving it.
And then after that, we're gonna go on to
look at progress
bars, which is my real purpose in in
dealing with this stuff.
So that's it for this tutorial and a bit
of diversion but hopefully useful.
And I just though I'd throw this video in,
in case you want to see, see this stuff.
And join me again next time when
we'll incur multithreading in Swing worker
class.
And until then happy coding.