Hello, this is John from
caveofprogramming.com.
And in this tutorial we're gonna look at
multithreading in Swing.
So in Swing you can use standard Java
multithreading techniques.
And if you go to caveofprogramming.com,
which is all one word.
There you can find basically a complete
course on Java multithreading.
But if you create a separate thread, you
can't update the GUI from that thread.
If you want to update the GUI from
a separate thread, you have to pass a
implementation
of runnable to swingutilities.invoke
later, but unfortunately there's
a class that that side steps all the
complication.
Specialize for swing and we're gonna use
that class here
which is the recommended way to handle
multithreading in Swing.
So at the moment if I run my application
I've got this tree, and if
I took something in the tree, it
locks up my application until message
retrieval finishes.
And of course, retrieving messages is not
necessarily the ideal thing
to do when you click a node in the tree
but here
I'm just trying to put together an
application to demonstrate the
basic principles, and I'll leave you to
decide on aesthetics and usability.
So what I want to do is in, in my message
panel
class here I've got this the problem is
that this stuff
here takes a while to return and that's
what's holding up my application.
So I want to run that in it's own thread.
And later on we'll pop up a progress bar
while the messages are being downloaded.
So what I'm gonna do is I'm gonna call the
methods here, call retrieve messages.
And I'm gonna implement that method here.
So, let's cut this and I'll go
down a bit, and right here I'm going to
have private void retrieve messages.
I'm gonna put that code in here, but then
I'm run it in the same thread and the
way to do that is I'm going to create a
swing worker and this is a template class.
And the first type, argument that I'll
supply
is the list of messages, and the second of
argument is going to be an incher and
we'll
see what the meaning of that is, very
shortly.
So lets just call this worker equals new.
And now I need this stuff all again
basically.
New swing worker, and the the constructor
brackets there.
That's add the import job mutual list.
And string worker is an abstract class.
So if I open a bracket here, and go to
add unimplemented methods, I can override
the doing background method.
And actually there's a couple of other
methods that I'm interested in here as
well.
So I'm gonna go to Source > Override
Implement Methods.
Let's try clicking here.
Hopefully eclipse is not going to be
difficult.
Well let's add the semicolon cuz that,
that might help.
And then right click, go to Source >
Override
Implement Methods and I'm going to
override done and process.
And what these are is firstly during
background is a method where
you put the code that you want to run in a
separate thread.
And swing worker will actually will use
one of a number of available swing
threads.
And it will, if no threads are available,
they're all being
used then it will just queue your code
until one is available.
But here, we're only using one of these
threads.
So there's no problem.
And I'm gonna.
Let's put this messages waiting output at
the top here for the moment.
And so, so doing background runs your code
process and we're going to see shortly,
that's actually for getting feedback from
your, from your swing worker.
And done is called when the thread
finishes.
So here, so here I've got my message
retrieval code.
I guess the first thing I want to do is I
wanna build up a list of messages here.
So, I'll say list message and call it
message maybe I'll call it retrieved.
Retrieve messages.
And let's set that equal to a new array
list, which'll do the trick.
An array list of message objects.
And every time I get a message I'll output
the title for the moment.
And I'm gonna just say
retrieveMessages.addMessage.
And then, after everything's finished I'm
gonna say return retrieveMessages, return
retrieveMessages.
Now you might guess here that the first
argument in this template, these two
template, of these two template parameters
is the return type of doing background.
And the way that works is when your worker
thread is done you can then say get.
And get will return what, whatever type
you specified in the first template
parameter there.
So we say, list message.
Let's call it retrieve messages again.
You can call it anything of course,
because retrieve equals get.
And I need to handle an interrupted
selection there, so let's say surround
the try catch, and I just leave these for
the, for the moment.
And execution exception you can actually
throw
an exception from doing background and
that will
show up as an execution exception, but
we're not gonna go into that too deeply.
So basically after, after your thread is
done, you can
call get and you get whatever return type
you specified here.
If you call get outside somewhere else
other than
done it will just block until this is
finished.
So it's probably best to call it done.
And we're gonna use these retrieve
messages
to update a GUI in a future tutorial.
But, for the moment, I'm just gonna leave
it at that.
Now, the second argument here is an
integer.
And in this case I made it an integer
and I'm gonna say here in to count equals
naught.
And I'm gonna count how many messages are
retrieved.
So here I'm gonna say count plus, plus.
And then I'll say process count.
I'm sorry not process, publish, publish.
And what that does is process will receive
whatever objects you publish but
because you could potentially do you might
put this lots of things very quickly.
Process isn't called every time you call
publish.
Process is actually called, I think on a
main screen dispatch thread.
So a little irregularly, but when it is
called it
will receive a list of whatever type of
thing your publishing.
And that's the type that you specified in
the
second argument here, of your swing worker
template parameter.
So here let's, let's rename this to
something else.
Let's call it, I don't know, counts.
And let's just get the last count there.
So let's say int lastCount.
Or maybe I could call it retrieved.
Retrieved equals count.get counts.size,
cuz I just want the last argument here.
And in counts negative one.
So we just want the very last one because
that was the most recent value that was
published.
And let's, let's output here.
Let's say sysout got, got,
plus retrieved plus messages.
That should do the trick.
So now so I've created my swing worker
class object and it's running my message
retrieval code.
Every time a message is retrieved equals
publish, which then
invokes process and you can use process to
update your your GUI.
So done and process, the idea is you can
update the GUI there.
But you probably shouldn't up the GUI in
doing background.
Now I'm going to run that thread.
So I'll say worker.execute.
At least I think it's execute.
Oh yeah, I'm running this in the wrong
place.
Let's go down a bit here.
So worker.execute.
There we go.
And now, that's just going to run and
hopefully
it will tell me how many messages it's
got.
And let's have a message when it's done,
as well.
So let's say sysout retrieved and plus.
And let's say retrieve messages.size, plus
messages.
And I'll run this.
So let's just run it here.
Click Run.
And now let's move this out of the way a
bit.
And I'll go to the tree and I'll take
something.
And now, we are retrieving.
Got one messages.
Got two messages.
So it's got three messages retrieved,
three messages.
And the thing is that it doesn't lock up
my my program so you can still run it.
And if, if you're happy with that there's,
there's probably really no need for a
progress bar here but I'm gonna put one in
just cuz I want to show you progress bars.
And in the next tutorial, in fact, we're
gonna look at popping up a modal dialogue
in response to ticking one of these
checkboxes,
which is to say probably not the best
practice.
But it'll give me a chance to show you
modal dialogues
and then we're gonna put a progress bar in
that module dialogue.
So join me again next time.
Oh yeah, I probably should mention that in
general you should try to avoid
multithreading in your
swing programs because if you got too much
processing
going on, it can slow down your user
interface.
So if you, if you do need it like try to
swing timers instead if you can.
And we'll cover those in a future
tutorial.
But if you really do need it use
swing worker, cuz that's specialized for
swing programs.
And, so that's all for this tutorial.
And in the next tutorial we'll look at
modal dialogues, and until next time,
happy coding.