Hello this is John from
caveofprograming.com.
And in this tutorial we're gonna look at
model dialogues because
so the moment if I run this application
and I tick and load in this tree
it retrieves messages and that something
separate thread.
So my dialogue is response, is responsive
while that happens.
And usually, actually, if you're doing
something in
the background you want your application
to be responsive.
But sometimes you want to remote a
dialogue like if you absolutely need to
use
to answer input before anything else
happens
or if you're doing some really heavy
processing.
And the application would basically be
unresponsive, anyway,
until the operation completes, or user
clicks cancel.
Then you'd want modal dialog.
And here I'm just gonna pop one up just to
demonstrate them to you.
And we're gonna ultimately put a progress
bar in that modal dialog.
So I'm gonna create a new class here in my
GUI package.
And I say New > Class.
And we'll call that ProgressDialog.
And let's, let's make that derive inherit
from JDialog and click Finish.
And add the import Ctrl+Shift+O.
And here I'll give this a constructor,
public ProgressDialog.
Now JDialog has various possible
constructors you can use.
And I wanna use the one, that let's me
specify the modality, of, dialog.
And I'm also, I'll have a title there as
well.
So let's have the first argument, here, is
gonna be
the parent, so I'm gonna parse in to the
constructor actually.
But, I'll leave that for moment.
And then I'm gonna have a title here, that
says, Message is Downloading.
And finally, let's have the modality,
ModalityType dot.
And I'm gonna make a application modal,
and you can also have document
modal, that would make a modal just for
your particular window.
But I'm just gonna demonstrate application
modal here, just simpler.
So the parent, is gonna be something that
I'm gonna parse in.
So window parent, like that.
And for the moment, let's just set the
size here.
SetSize.
SetSize just to something that's gonna be
visible.
Well, let's make it, I don't know, 400
wide, 200 high just for the moment.
And, now I'm just gonna hired to show that
dialog from my message panel.
Let's click Refresh here.
Refresh.
And so in my message panel I start a at
one
point I retrieve messages, so if you click
something
in a tree and it opens to retrieve
messages thing.
And here I want to popup a dialog.
Now let's add, the, the dialog here as
page private instance variable.
Let's type private ProgressDialog.
And I'll call that progressDialog.
And in the constructor I'll create a new
progress dialog,
so I'll say progressDialog equals new
ProgressDialog.
This is all pretty straightforward.
And, and now is the, is a twist because I
wanna say here progressDialog.show.
ProgressDialog.setVisible actually.
ProgressDialog.setVisible true.
And but now that, the problem with that,
is that if you set a modal dialog visible,
then nothing will happen in your
application, in
your thread until you've, until it's gone
away again.
So, I wanna run it in one of these
separate kinda swing threads.
I wanna, I wanna use SwingUtilities.info
later to run it.
Which will just run it, it will just run
it in
such a way that it's not gonna hold up my
application.
And I say new runnable in there.
And, and let's whoops.
Let's add the semicolon there at the run
method here public void run.
And, if I put it in there, it's not,
it's not gonna hold up my application when
it runs.
It's just gonna be scheduled to run.
At some, at, at this possible moment.
So, now, in, in my done method
in the SwingWorker thread, I can
set the dialog to, to invisible.
So here's my done method.
And, in here, let's just, let's just say
here progressDialog.setVisible, false.
Now, just to show you what I mean about
this a visible holding things up in the
modal dialog, let's put this out here and
let's say, showing modal dialog.
And let's put the sys out after this,
after the show,
sys out and say finished showing modal
dialog.
And now let's run that and see how it
looks.
It's got an error in there somewhere.
Where's my error?
Let's take a look.
So somewhere in here, oh, I just I think I
just didn't save it.
No, I did save it.
Oh, yeah, I didn't parse it in.
The reference the parent.
Now if I parse in this, because I need
here, I need the parent dialog.
This is a panel, so that's not gonna cut
the mustard for a window.
But if I say this dot, well, if
I say getParent and then getParent returns
container.
Well, I can actually cast that into a
window.
Cuz the parent of this panel is a window,
so I think that will work.
And now if I save that and I run it.
Let's see how this looks.
So if I tick this here my dialog appeared
before Eclipse.
Let's see that again.
So I'll quit the application and let's
show the console down here.
Let's run the application and tick
something in the tree.
There's my dialog, and I can't do anything
in
the rest of the application, until it's
finished there.
Let's try it one more time.
So it's modal, it won't go away.
And you can see that it's processing
messages there in the background.
And when it finishes then you press that
until
it finishes, and I'm stuck which is what I
want.
Okay, so now in the next tutorial we'll
gonna
look at showing a progress bar in this
modal dialog.
And, until next time, happy coding.
[NOISE]