Hello, this is John from
caveofprogramming.com, and in
this tutorial we're gonna look up progress
bars.
So, at the moment if I run this
application, we've got,
when I click the tree, so, let's just wait
for it to stop, it's thinking about it.
Don't know why my computer is so slow
today.
If we go to the tree here, click this, we
see this dialog, which pops up, and then
disappears again.
And we're going to put a progress bar in
that dialog, but actually first, I'm going
to fix one little thing because I must
confess that in the
last tutorial, I actually showed you some
code that had a little bug in it, because
if you look at the message panel here when
it creates the dialog.
It does window.getParent, but that
actually returns
null for reasons I don't fully understand.
And we're gonna fix that by putting parent
in here.
And parent, it's gonna be JFrame.
The actual parent window.
And when I create the message panel in the
main frame, I'm gonna pass in this.
And then finally, at the end of the chain
here, in the ProgressDialog.
I'll use that JFrame for the parent.
And I'm also gonna do the same trick which
I showed you before which is
set location relative to here in the
ProgressDialog.
Set location relative to two parent.
Now I'm not convinced that dialogue
positioning actually works properly in
swing.
But this is something of an improvement in
the at least the
dialog seems to come up basically in the
middle of the window which I'll show you.
If I can get this working.
Yeah, message panel, I'm typing input
there
to message panel, save everything, and
hopefully the
errors will go away, I can, there we go,
so now I move this application down
a little bit and bring the dialog so at
least now it's in the middle
of the screen and although whether it
actually
move with his window I'm not entirely
sure.
Anyway, we'll leave that because this is
pretty acceptable I think.
And I'm gonna give this ProgressDialog
here two private variables.
Let's give it a private JButton, cancel
button.
And, and I'll also give it private
Jprogess bar, which I'll call progress
bar.
And in the constructor here after adding
the
input of Ctrl+Shift+O I'm gonna set a
cancel button.
Equal to a new JButton with the text
counselor on it, which is gonna be for
counseling.
Message retrieval in this case.
And the progress bar I'm gonna set equal
to a new JProgress bar, and here in
[INAUDIBLE].
Specify a minimum and maximum value.
But I don't think I need to here, because
I'm going
to set, the default minimum will be zero,
and the maximum
I'm going to set later on, as we go along,
in
fact I'm going to give this a method
looking for exact maximum.
And that's gonna take a int count.
And with that count it's just gonna say
progressbar.set maximum.
Set maximum.
And what that does is it sets the the
numerical value of
the progress bar that corresponds to 100%
complete, so
it could be 100 or 1,000 or ten or
whatever you like.
And although it is an inter.
Mixture actually.
And then I'm also gonna give it a, let's,
let's [UNKNOWN] to here.
A public void setValue very important.
And I'll give that value, don't know why I
called this count, actually.
Up here.
Let's call this value.
As well, and then the value is just going
to, is just gonna do progress bar
dot set value and that's gonna set the
current value of the
progress bar and of course slightly
maximum value.
When this value here reaches this value
here.
Then you'll have 100% progress.
So, there's a few other things to do, I
need to add these two controls to the
dialog.
I'm going to get rid of setSize here and
I'm going to do setLayout.
I'm going to
set the layout to a new flow layout, which
is the layout manager you
might recall that just lets you add
components from right to, from left to
right.
And you can't even do vertical layouts in
flow layout.
It's a purely horizontal thing.
I'm gonna do add, progress
bar, and add Cancel button here.
And I'm also gonna resize the progress
bar.
So that it has the same height as the
button and to do that, I'm going to say
size, actually dimension I'll call this
size.
I'm gonna set that equal to the size
retrieved from the console button, the
preferred size.
This will will say cancel
button.getPreferredSize.
And then, after writing the imports, I'll
do size dot width equals 400, and
I'll do progress bar.setPreferredSize.
So we're got this size from the button so
that we can
get the height of the progress bar the
same as the button.
But, of course, the progress bar.
Fours wider.
And so I've set the size to
wider before doing setPreferredSize on the
progress bar.
And finally after adding these two
controls I'm going to
call puck and puck sort of shrink wraps
your frame
or dialog around the controls so you've
added so it
will make it a minimum size for these two
controls.
Now we can [UNKNOWN] it.
Wire this into our message panel.
I've already got the instance variable
here and the
dialog already appears and disappears at
the right moments.
But I'm going to also set the values.
So let's go through tree messages here.
Let's get rid of this text.sysout stuff.
Because we don't need that.
And in process, which is the method that
the publish
method ultimately invokes as you saw in
the last tutorial.
I'm gonna say ProgressDialog.setValue
retrieved.
And that's gonna set it, set the progress
according
to the messages retrieved, the number of
messages retrieved.
I also need to set the maximum up here,
so, here I'm using message
server.getMessage count, and let's say,
ProgressDialog.set, maximum, so
the maximum value here will be the total
number message, messages that are waiting
to be retrieved and I think that's
just about ready to go now and so let's,
let's try that and and see how it looks.
So,.
If I run this, and it's not yet gonna be
perfect, but
if I run it, then we see that we've got
progress indicators here.
And by the way, if you don't know what the
maximum value is, of your, of the
kind of thing that you're doing in the
background, you can set progress bar set
indeterminate true.
And an indeterminate progress bar
basically
looks like this.
So it shows something's happening.
But, it doesn't give an indication of when
it's gonna finish.
Anyway we will use a, a determinant
version here, which is the default.
Now, there's, there's one thing that I'd
like to do here actually, which is that
I'm calling [UNKNOWN] later to show the
dialog, to make it visible.
Because you might recal from the last
tutorial that if we
don't do that, doing set visible on a
mortal dialog just
causes everything else to be suspended and
nothing else can happen
and cuz this will not return until the
dialog goes away.
But I'm going to take this and copy it and
in my ProgressDialog here.
I'm going to override.
I'm going to go to source, override
implement methods, and
I'm going to override in dialog the I'm
going to override
the show method here I think that's the
one I want, and in.
Here, that will not show actually, sorry
I'm talking rubbish,
I'm gonna over ride, shows actually
uh,duplicated, what I,
what I want it's the set visible which is
the newer way to do show on a dialog.
So I'm gonna find setVisible.
Which I know is in here somewhere.
Yeah, it's in dialog actually.
And where are we, setVisible, setVisible.
Here we go.
Let's override setVisible.
And in there, I can put this sort
of threading code and I can set the
visibility.
Here let's call this visible and let's
baseline here as visible.
And I need to invoke the super.
And the super kind of progress style of
method.
So I, sorry not the soup but the this.
We're in here, we're in a dialogue that
extends JDialogue.
And in my overwritten set visible, I don't
want to invoke set visible itself.
I want invoke a super class setVisible and
to do that I have to say, I think I need
J, Well, actually, I could write, So I
need to name the class, ProgressDialog.
ProgressDialog.
And I don't wanna use this.
What I want to use is super.
So ProgressDialog.super.
And also to access this variable here.
And this, method of a anonymous class.
I'm gonna have to declare the parameter
here final.
And then.
That should all work I think.
So let's, let's take a look at that now.
Actually I've gotta take the [UNKNOWN] and
I can remove this from here.
And I can not worry about that here, cuz
it's
now built into the dialogue which, makes a
lot more sense.
There's one other little thing that I want
to fix here in this tutorial.
So, if you look in this dialogue now.
It looks pretty good, and it works.
but, you often don't quite see it.
See, see it going to 100%.
Although having said that, well, One thing
that we
need to fix actually, is, that's going to
these
applications, is we need to make
sure that when you show the dialogue that
it's initialized to zero progress.
So let's go to the show method in its
ProgressDialog, and let's say progressBar
.set value and let's set that to nought
right here.
And now let's see how this looks and so
I'll tick
something on so it's zero to start with
and then it finishes.
Now one thing that you often find at the
ProgressDialog is that annoying they never
seem to get to a hundred because this,
this second reaches a hundred, and then
disappears.
And to fix that.
Well there's all kinds of ways you could
fix that.
But what I'm going to do is think with
this setVisible
method and I'm going to put in a little
delay before it, before it disappears.
So let's say here if physical actually,
what if we do.
If I put a delay in here.
And if I were to put here a thread.sleep,
that's gonna hold everything up until it
finishes sleeping.
So we wouldn't, we wouldn't see any
progress on the
progress bar because nothing's gonna
happen until this thread.sleep [UNKNOWN]
expire.
But if I put it.
Here in the run method of info later, it's
gonna achieve what we want.
So I will say if visible equals false, so
it's been set to disappear.
Let's have a little delay.
Let's say thread.sleep and let's try 500
milliseconds and see how that looks.
I just handle the interrupted exception
there.
And I'll, I'll leave that as is.
It's not too important cuz it shouldn't
really be happening at the moment.
So, that's from this and click this and
now with a bit of luck, in fact that
perhaps wasn't quite enough.
Let's change it to 1,000.
I think that should work.
This all looks okay.
So sleeping just a little bit before
setting it invisible.
Let's run that and now my flips has got
slightly in my way.
Okay, let's go back to this, quit that.
Let's, made the console visible here.
Run the application and keeping my fingers
crossed here that this should work.
And, in fact, it doesn't.
Because I don't actually know why.
yeah, because, we're calling setVisible
and I've got
this, I've got this set value equal to
null and so it's trying to hide the
progress bar and it's doing this, straight
away.
So I already want to get rid of that right
there.
And I only want to set the progress to
zero if it's being shown on the.
It's being hidden.
Now I think we've nailed this, and I'd
really like to cuz progress bars are so
tricky.
There we go.
That looks much better.
Let's try this.
Okay.
Very nice.
Okay, so that's it for this tutorial.
And in the next.
In this tutorial, we're gonna look at
making this console button operational.
So join me again then and until next time,
happy coding.