Hello, this is John from
caveofprogramming.com.
And in this tutorial, we're look at how
you can distribute your application to
your end user.
So this might seem kind of a strange point
to insert
this tutorial in the series but the fact
is, to tell you
the truth, that I skipped accidentally
from tutorial 57 to tutorial
59 and that's why I've kinda gone back and
inserted 58 here.
And this is of course, something that
everyone needs to know.
So, here is as good a place to put it as
any.
So, to distribute your application, the
first step at least, and possibly
the only step you'll need, is to create a
runable jav file.
That's a jav file, a .jav file, that you
can run just by clicking on.
And your file will run in Windows 7 and, I
presume, although I don't know if
it will also run on the Mac because,
historically MacIntoshes have supported
Java better than Windows.
And presumably, Linux, as well.
So let's see how that works.
And you wanna make sure that you've got, a
fairly recent version of Eclipse.
So, here, I've got, I don't know what it
is.
I think it's 3.7.
But the functionality that we need was
actually added in Eclipse 3.5 so,
update your Eclipse to a recent version if
you have, if you've got an old version.
Now, assuming you've got a recent version
of Eclipse,
right click your project folder and go to
export.
And if your Eclipse is 3.5 or greater, you
will have this option runable JAV file in
here.
And that's what you need.
Let's click next.
And on this screen here, you have to
select.
The run configuration for your
application.
And the run configuration basically just
says which
name to run when the jar's double-clicked.
So, in this case I've got hold massive
bunch of run configurations here,
because you get a run configuration is
created whenever you run an application,
basically.
And you can rename these configurations if
you want, up here in.
This little arrow by the run, green run
menu, if you click on that, run
configurations, you'll be able to edit the
name of
your, the names of your configurations
here, but I wont do that here.
I'll just go to this export, runnable JAR
[NOISE] option, and I can
recognize the rights configuration here
cause it's got the name of my
project in it, swing 58 so we see here the
launch configuration.
This one, here, is doing 58, distributing
your application.
So I know that's the right one.
And if I had renamed it, if I had a green
run button, then that name would appear
here which might be simpler.
Anyway, so you have to select the right.
Launch configuration, and you need to set
your export configuration here.
So, I'm gonna set this to, C, let's see,
C,
tutorial, swing, and I'm gonna export this
as,
I dunno I'll call it
DB, DB, DB at top jaw.
So this is basically your, your runable
program and I'm gonna click save there.
And these options are quite important.
What this means is to, to, to run our app,
we've used
a JDBC, add on library, that's in there.
And the jar file, that added, fire, the
build path of the project, you're wrong.
And if you're using any any extra job
files.
Then they need to think about in here.
And your choices are basically, you could
export your files will contain class
files.
And you can either extract the job files,
get the class files
out and repackage them in to a remote job
which is this option.
And that will usually work, but sometimes
you can have problems with it.
The safest option is package required
libraries into generated jar which will
take any jar files that you've used and
put them in your runnable jar.
A jar file just being basically a bit like
a zip file, really.
And the other option is copy required
liable
into the sub folder next to the generated
job.
And if you choose that option, you're
gonna have to distribute
your job files that you may have used with
your application.
So probably what you want is this middle
option here.
Once you've done that, the last phase is
pretty simple.
Just click finish, and usually you'll get.
Some warnings, but you shouldn't get any
errors.
And these just compile warnings and I've
been ignoring a
lot of compiler warnings because eclipse
will warn you.
It will say that, you, you have not, it
always brings up this.
Warning you have not jar added a, I think
it's
called serial UID or something to your to
your class.
But since we haven't needed to we haven't
needed to
serialize these classes, then we haven't
needed to add that ID.
And if you want these warnings to go away,
you just have
to click on the warning icons, those
little yellow warning icons in
your Java files in Eclipse and get it to
add a Serialization
UID, but the bottom line is you can
usually ignore these warnings.
So click OK, as long as you've not got any
errors.
And now, hopefully I've generated my
runnable job.
And I can got the folder that I put it in.
And here it is dbapp.jar.
And if I double click that it will run my
application.
And if I click connect if everything's
gone right
then it will connect just fine to my
database.
So that's how you can generate a runnable
jar.
And if you use Windows a lot, and you-
You all, so all you have to do is
basically e-mail send somehow
this runable chart to your end user and of
course if you've written
a database application you'll have to make
sure that the URL that connects
to your database, that that's the URL that
can be reached from their computer.
but, if you want, like a dot xr file for
Windows, as you can see, a runnable jar is
fine in Windows 7, but if you particularly
want
a dot xr, then I recommend a tool called
j-smooth.
So just search for Jsmooth.
That's J and then the word smooth, all one
word, in Google and
that's a free tool that you can use to
take your runnable jars
and turn them into .exe files which will
even prompt the user to
download the necessary Java runtime files
if they're missing from the user's
computer.
So it's a nice extra touch, but most of
the time all you really need is this
runnable jar.
Okay, so that's it for this tutorial.
Join me again next time.
And until next time.
Happy coding.
[NOISE]