Hi there.
This is John from CaveOfProgramming.com.
And, before I go on to show you how to
cancel threads I just wanna, put
in a quick tutorial here about adding text
to progress bars because at the moment and
we've got this progress bar here, and
there's no text on it.
And you can actually out text to the bar
area it's self which is quite nice.
So to do that, it's really simple.
Let's go to the progress dialogue here.
And I'm going to say here,
progressBar.setString,
painted; it's kind of a strange name, but
you have to set string
painted true, and that will, put whatever
text you add to
the bar, it will, it will show, or paint,
if you like, that text.
And to actually show some text you
say progressBar.setString and we can set
for example
retrieving mess, retrieve, retrieving
messages, like this.
And if we look at that gonna get,
hopefully from text from up here on
my bar retrieving messages and now often
what you wanna do is, make this
text update when, as the progress bar
progresses, so.
To do that I can say here.
Let's add say int progress equals
value divided by
progressBar.getMaximumValue.
[INAUDIBLE]
maximum.
And also, I'll multiply that by 100.
And let's also say,
just in case, maximum happens to be zero.
Well, actually, just to make sure that
this really can't be zero.
Let's go to start here and set
up here let's set progressBar.setMaximum
to 10 or something.
Although that's sort of theoretical
possibility
because actually you should never use the.
Progress bar as it stands without first
setting the maximum here otherwise the
progress value will be wrong anyways so,
okay, and now I can say
progress bar every time I set the father
view, I can say progressBar.setString.
And what string should we set?
Well I'm going to use, a static method in
the string class.
String.format and this format string
slight print f,
if you know that and the way it
works is you pass them a format string
and specify how the string should look
followed by.
a, a series of parameters that will be
substituted into the format string, and in
this
case I just wanna use one parameter, the
progress value, the percentage progress,
and I want to
put an integer in here and Format code
[INAUDIBLE] % d and then a % sign and
because % signs have a special meeting in
these format strings, I need 2% signs,
which effectively
escapes the % sign.
And if you, if you wanna, want more
information on string.format, just type it
into Google and look for it's API document
or you could look at system.out or
printf because that formats strings using
the same codes here, so let's say
% complete, and let's just
run that and see if that works, so open
progress bar, and
there we go retrieving messages 33
complete, 60%, 100%, wonderful, okay
so that's it for this tutorial just a
brief one and.
In the next tutorial we're going to look
at cancelling
threads, and we're going to make that
cancel button actually work.