[BLANK_AUDIO]
Hello, this is John from
caveofprogramming.com and in
this tutorial we're going to look at
cancelling worker
threats and more importantly, I'm going to
show you
how to Implement this cancel button on
this dialogue.
So, to get the dialogue bit working, the
first
thing I'm going to do is create a new
interface.
And this interface, I'm gonna call
progress, progress, dialogue listener.
And I'm just gonna give that one method,
public void,
cancel, let's call it cancelled, actually.
That'll do the trick.
now, in the, progress dialog, I'll give
that a private,
member variable, of type progress dialog
listener.
So that type is the interface that I've
just implemented.
And I'll give it a method for setting
that.
So, we'll say, public void, set.
Set listener, I'll call.
Call it.
Progress.
Then that's gonna accept progress dialogue
list now.
And it's just gonna say disk top list now.
This top listener.
List and equals, listener.
And, and, and also well.
What I want to do is, ultimately, I want
to have the message panel, listen to the
progress dialog, and if someone clicks
that button, it's gonna invoke
the message panel's can't solve, function.
In fact, maybe I should call it something
else, I'll just call it.
That's click progress dialog council cuz
this
going to be a method in message panel.
I'm just going to have to implement this
interface
so we want to give it a suitable name.
And, and, so I'm gonna add a listener to
the cancel button here.
I'm gonna say add, well cancel button dot
add action
listener, and it's gonna be, that's gonna
be a new action listener.
Let's implement the missing method in our
little anonymous class here.
And if someone clicks a cancel button, it
will invoke this method.
And then I'm gonna say if listener is not
equal
to naught, in other words if something's
listening to this dialog.
Then, I'll call this naught, and it's
only got one method, progress, dialogue,
cancelled.
Okay, so far so good.
And also actually while I'm at it I'm just
gonna fix a
little thing here because this dialogue as
we've written here is pretty generic.
And I wanna make it even more generic by
just making this message customizable.
So I'll cut that.
And I'll put the string title here, and
call this, title.
And now, let's go and do some work on
message panel.
So, in message panel, for a start, I'll
put a title in here.
That's better.
So now, progress, the progress dialog, is,
I think, a fairly generic class.
And, I'm gonna make Message panel
implement that interface that I just
created.
So, I'll say implement progress dialog
listener, like that.
Save that.
Let's go to this and add an implemented
method.
And on the bottom here now we've got our
progress dialog cancelled.
And let's just see that working.
So, I'm gonna put these all in here
because
I like to check things as I'm going along.
And I find that even software developers
like me
with decades of experience, well I've got
more than
a decade, we still make mistakes all the
time,
so it's good to check things as you're
going along.
And so, let's go, let's have a look.
I'll bring up the dialogue and click
cancel, and you should see down here,
cancelled.
But, I'm not, so there must be something
I've forgotten.
And, let's see.
So.
Yeah, I forgot to add the message panel as
a listener.
See, this is exactly what I was talking
about.
Okay, so I've got a say now, and progress
dialogue dot add.
Add progress, add listener, I think I
called that add listener.
And I'm not getting much success with the
auto complete here.
Let me check, progress dialogue.
So, I have given it a message called set
listener, that's what we want.
Let's save that, that might help.
And then auto complete set.
And this and that's the one I want.
And the list is going to be this dialogue.
So this is something I've done several
times before now.
I, I've created an interface prefaced that
of this note with one method.
I gave the progress dialog an instance
variable of that type, and, I provided it
with a set method to set it this there and
then if someone clicks the cancel button.
I, if that listener instance for example
is not
null, I call it's progress style of cancel
method.
And so you see, I'm keeping a clean
separation
here between the progress dialog and the
message dialog.
So the progress dialog doesn't know
anything about a message panel.
And that makes it much more reusable
and your application hopefully easier to
debug.
And I'm not saying the message panel, set
listener this, and then
of course I have to implement progress
dialog listener in the message panel.
Now, let's check that it works.
And this time I'm pretty confident that it
will.
So I'm gonna bring up the dialog up there.
And I'm going to click Cancel.
And we've got Cancel coming up down there.
Now there's one other possibility here,
because someone could
click Cross and in the dialogue to close
it.
So let's say here in the progress dialog.
SetDefaultCloseOperation
jDialog.doNothingOnClose.
Because I don't want it to do anything
when someone clicks our cross.
And then I can say add window listener.
And I'll say in here, new window adapter.
And window adapter is a abstract class
implement,
or the methods of of a window listener.
So now I can click in here
and go to override source, overwrite
document methods.
And I just want the window closing method,
because I want to stay in here.
Let's just check if this works.
In fact, what I'll do is say if this does
not equal to null
again, I'll call the I'll call it, I'll
call it progress dollar council method.
So let's check that that works as well.
Let's go here, bring up the dialog and
click the cross in the corner.
And it also says can't sort, so that's
what I wanted.
Now, let's actually get onto the business
of terminating
the thread, and this is gonna be pretty
simple.
It's just that there's gonna be a few
little tiny complications here.
So, the first thing is that my swing
worker thread, my reference to it is a
local variable and I want to be able
to access it from the Progress Style
Console method.
So let's get rid of the declaration here,
paste it up here.
Private, private SwingWorker worker.
There we go.
And now, in this cancel method, I can say
if
worker is not equal to null, which it
shouldn't be null because.
People shouldn't be seeing the progress
dialog unless unless
they have actually unless the thread has
actually been created.
But just in case they manage to because
we've, I
think we create the, the dialog first and
then the thread.
It's just in case they manage to click
bottom in between that millisecond
interval in between the dialog being set
physical and the worker being created.
Let's just check that it's not equal to
null.
And then let's say worker.cancel.
So, and said equals true.
And I'm calling this swing work a cancel
method and if you, this has this one
argument which I've set to true and the
argument actually says, is called may
interrupt running.
So if this would be false, it would cancel
the thread only and been
executed yet, and I want it to be
cancelled, if it has been executed.
Now, what will actually happen at the
moment, will be that wherever I've
got like a thread.sleep or a wait or
something that could be interrupted in
my processing, if I call cancel on the
thread, then that's gonna, dig
an interrupted exception will be thrown
from
wherever it can within my, processing
code.
And it may be that there's nowhere in your
processing code that you call
try to sleep or wait, and there's no way
that it can be interrupted.
I'll show you what I mean.
If I now cancel this thread I'm gonna get.
Like a horrible looking stat trace down
here.
And let's have a look at where that's
coming from.
So, if we can find any details in here.
It's coming from here.
So this get method, for a start, is I'm,
in
my done, I'm still calling get, even
though it's been cancelled.
Now, we wanna sort that out and fix that,
so I'm gonna say
progress dialogue to set visible, we
false, we always wanna do that in done.
But, then I'm gonna say if is cancelled
and
this will tell me if the thread is being
cancelled.
And if it has, I'm just gonna return
because I don't wanna go any further.
I don't wanna try to get anything here if
it has been cancelled.
And let's run it again, see what it looks
like now.
I think I'm still gonna have some stack
trace, stack traces there, so we'll cancel
it.
And we've still got stack trace.
And let's see where this is coming from.
So now if I look at this, it's coming from
my message server.
And you see in my processing code, I've
got this thread.sleep, which can throw an
interrupted
exception, and if the thread that it's in
is interrupted, it will throw this
interrupted exception.
And by interrupted I mean if you call
cancel on the worker, basically.
And so I'm just gonna get rid of this
message, 'cause if this is interrupted, I
don't care.
I just wanted to shut up basically.
And let's now run it and see if we've got
any more in there.
That might be it.
I'm not sure.
And click Cancel.
And now, it's failing silently, which is
good, except I
want it to actually be cancelled, not to
carry on.
And to fix that, because it's not enough
in general to-
It's not enough to simply call cancel on
the thread 'cause all cancel
does is it sets this flag which can detect
by the isCancelled method.
And your thread.sleep's will detect that
but I need to actually look at where I'm
processing stuff and to stop doing that
processing if the threads cancelled.
So my message panel, I'm retrieving
messages from the message server, and I
actually want to say if is cancelled,
cancel, I just want to stop doing that.
So let's just call it break to break out
of that for loop.
And I think that should do the trick, so
let's
run it and I'll take the cross just for
variety.
And now we've successfully cancelled it.
So, and the basic message is you can't
cancel on your worker thread and use
is cancelled within your processing and
doing background
to check whether the thread has been
canceled.
And if it is, you, it's up to you to then
stop doing processing
because string isn't going to barge in
there and, like physically terminate the
thread.
All it's gonna do is set that flag
basically.
And if you've gotten the thread.sleep or
if you've got a
wait in there then that's going to throw
an interrupted exception
and that's just something to be aware of
because you might
want to have your interrupt exceptions
just handled silently or you.
You might wanna handle 'em somehow by
cancelling further processing.
I don't know.
So, that's it for this tutorial.
Join me again next time.
And until next time, happy coding.
[SOUND]