Hello, this is John from
caveofprogramming.com and in this
tutorial,
we're just gonna look at setting the
cursor in Java.
So, at the moment, I've got this progress
dialog that comes up.
And just as an example of setting the
cursor,
I'm gonna set the cursor to a wait cursor
when
the dialog is showing, and I'm going to
set it
back to the default system cursor when the
dialog's gone.
And it's very important, of course, to
restore the cursor after changing it.
So, in my progress dialog, I've got this
overridden set visible method.
And this is a good place, in this case, to
set the cursor.
So I'll say, if visible, we'll set the
cursor to a, wait cursor.
And if we're setting it to invisible,
we're hiding the dialogue, then I'm going
to set it back to the ordinary, to
ordinary cursor.
So, here all you have to do is say, every
string component has a set cursor method.
And that's the one that we wanna use.
It's pretty simple.
And to set cursor you need to pass a
cursor, so I'm
going to say, cursor.getPredefinedCursor
and
then here I need to pass in a static int,
constant of the cursor class, and there's
a bunch you can use.
I'm going to use, wait cursor down here.
You can see from the auto complete there.
There's, there's quite a variety of
different cursors.
And when the dialog goes away again.
When visible is set to false.
I'm gonna call, set cursor cursor.get,
default cursor there.
And let's just take a look at that.
So now, when my dialog comes up.
I've got a wait cursor over the dialog.
Now, you might wanna set the wait cursor
over the
over your application as a whole.
In which case you need to call set cursor
for this jFrame or for, let's say, this
panel here.
But, for the moment, I content myself with
just having this wait cursor over
the dialogue and, if you wanna set the
cursor elsewhere, it's very easy to do.
Just call set cursor on the appropriate
component or the whole frame if you want.
okay, so that's it for this tutorial.
Next time we're gonna look at nesting
nesting split panes.
So join me again then.
And until then, happy coding.
[SOUND]