Hello, this is John from
kevolveprogramming.com.
And in this tutorial we're gonna look at
nesting, split panes.
So, if I run this application now and what
I
want to do is I wanna have this message
area divided
into 3 sections with a tree on the top and
message headers in the middle and message
text on the bottom.
And to achieve that, I'm going to have one
split pane with the tree on the top
and another split pane in it's lower half
and another split pane will contain
the message headers and the message text
in the bottom layer.
So, I'm just gonna make a couple of little
changes first.
One thing is I'm gonna if I maximize this.
So my gooey, I've got this app.
I'm gonna move that into the default
package by dragging
and dropping because it makes more sense
to have it there.
And now if I run that as an application,
should still work.
This is good.
And I'm also gonna go to main frame here
and.
In main frame I've got a text panel, I'm
gonna delete it from there, and I'm gonna
delete
the line where it's actually created as
well because
I'm not using this anymore on the main
frame.
This is from a previous tutorial, well I'm
gonna
use it in this pane, I'm gonna, in this
tutorial.
I'm gonna start using it in this message
panel.
So, I'm going to give the message panel a
couple of new components.
One's going to be this text panel.
And this is basically just a wrapper for a
JTextArea.
So, if you wanna create a JTextArea
yourself, of course, use a JTextArea.
And we'll look at the added tutorial where
we, we dealt with this.
So, and now we're also gonna create a
private j list, which would, initially
will be empty.
And I'll just call that message, message
list.
So at the input, control shift over, and
I'll scroll, scroll down.
Actually, I won't.
First, allow two j split panes here.
I'll call one upper pane and another one
I'll call.
Call JSplitPane.lowerPane.
Okay set the import and I'll go down here
and before I add components.
Let's say textPanel equals new
J text panel and what's the other
one, message list equals new J list.
And, oh it's not a J text file there is no
such component, it's a text file.
JTextArea is the swing component that this
text one uses.
And now, I'll create my lower pane first,
I'll say LowerPane = new JSplitPane.
JSplitPane, I want the vertical one which
is called, what, vertical, vertical split
because, I want
my components to stack vertically on top
of
each other, that should be j split, pain,
actually.
There we go.
And the components I'm gonna add to that
will be the the
message this that's gonna show the message
headers ultimately on the text panel.
And then I'll copy that and, and, the
upper pane here, upper pane.
Also, gonna be a vertical split because I
have a horizontal frontal within a
vertical pane.
It doesn't matter.
And to the upper pane there typed l again
unnecessarily.
And to the upper pane I'm gonna add, the
top pane
is going to be this tree wrapped in a
scroll pane.
And, so I'm gonna add that in there.
And the lower pane is gonna be the lower
split pane, so and now let's add the
upper pane which contains the lower split
pane to the panel that I'm working in.
Now for ring, that's not going to
look very pretty Let's select the main
application.
Click Run.
And you see the panels are basically
contracted at the bottom here.
And there are several ways that you could
deal with that.
whoops, just maximized the wrong window.
One, one way you could do it would be, you
could say.
J, so the JSplitPane has this method,
SetDividerLocation, SetDividerLocation.
It comes in two varieties, and the one
that you'd like to use here has this
double proportional location, which allows
you to set, like 0.5 would
be, to set the, lo, the divider halfway
down the panel, or across
the panel and 0.33 would be a third of the
way and so on.
But, you can't use that because that only
works when the
panel's already, pane's already in another
panel and it's already sized.
So here because we haven't added it yet
and even if we'd added it we'd have to
let the, the hole GUI be created before
we could use that version at set divisor
location.
We could use set divisor location, it
takes an int,
it specifies the number of pixel for
second divisor location.
That would work, but I'm not gonna use
that here instead
I'm just gonna set a minimum side on the
text panel.
So, I say set minimum size.
And let's set that for new dimension.
And now the horizontal dimension, the
horizontal value that
I passed in, this is in pixels, to
dimension here.
Doesn't matter because the control will
expand to take up
all horizontal space anyway so I'll set
that to ten.
It doesn't matter.
And what matters is the, the vertical
dimension.
I'm gonna set that two, let's try a
hundred and 15, see how that looks.
I'm gonna also set a minimum size on the
message
list, so that, that doesn't get too small
as well.
In fact, maybe let's, let's make it a
hundred or make it.
Quite small I think.
And now if I run that, the the text panels
look better, but if I resize,
this lower panel here which is gonna
contain
a message text, takes up all the extra
space.
Now that might, might be what you want,
and in this application perhaps it is.
But just to show you how to control this
resizing behavior, I'm going to make it so
all these panels expand proportionally and
the way to do that is, let's
take the upperPane as an example.
If I say upperPane.setResizeWeight and if
I set that to
1.0 and this is going to be between naught
and 1.
Then when I resize it, the upper panel
take up all the available space for the
cam.
If I set that equal to naught on the upper
panel here, then the lower part of the
upper panel would take up all the
available space
when you maximize the window when you
resized it.
And, and to get the two parts of the upper
pane to
resize equally, I would set not 0.5, and
now they are sized equally.
But notice that we still don't have equal
resizing
behavior, because this lower pane is still
resizing too much.
What-
I think I just quit Eclipse by mistake.
I must have hit the "X."
Start this again.
And what I'm going to do when eclipse
restarts is I'm going
to set on the lower pane here, I'm going
to set a-
Where were we?
I'm gonna set a value, I'm going to set a
resize weight on the lower pane,
basically, is my guess.
So, let's just go in here and say lower
pane, set resize weight, 0.5.
And I need to, let's go to my project
here.
And expand it and select the app because
that's what I want to run.
Click run.
And take a look at it now.
So now it looks pretty good, I think.
And it resizes quite nicely.
And,
okay, so, that's pretty much it for that
tutorial.
One thing that it's mentioned not in the
main stream documentation for J split pane
in the sort of list server problem
solutions
that you can find on the sun, Oracle
Site, is that if you nest a lot of split
panes the borders can accumulate in
the inner panes and you might wanna set
the borders of the inner panes to null.
We're doing like the split pane.set border
brackets null, but here this doesn't look
like a problem to me because this, the
appearance of this seems quite acceptable.
So, I am going to leave this as it is.
And that's all for me this time.
Until next time, happy coding.