Hello, this is John from
caveofprogramming.com and in this tutorial
we're
gonna look at how you respond to list and
to tab selections.
So, in a moment, if I click this message
tab
here, I have to actually do something in
the tree.
I have to click check box before my
messages are retrieved and I want
to change that so that just selecting the
type in itself will retrieve messages.
And by the way, I've added a bunch of
fake messages to my message controller, my
fake message retriever.
And I decreased the time that it takes
to retrieve each message, a bit more
realistic now.
Okay so this is pretty simple.
I'm going to go to place, main frame,
where I actually create the top
pane and I'm going to add to
the top pane, topPane.aChangeListener, so
add ChangeListener.
Now I could make, make frame implement
changes in
it but I say, I use an anonymous class
here.
I say new ChangeListener.
Like this, open and curly bracket.
And put a semicolon in.
And let's add the unimplemented methods
in.
So, it's just got one method called state
changed
and this will be called whenever a tab is
selected.
And when a tab is selected, I'm gonna say
tabPane.getSelected tab, getSelectedIndex,
sorry.
And I'm gonna say int, tabIndex equals
topPane.getSelectedIndex and
that's just do assist out now to see what
type that is tabIndex.
There we go.
And minimize the editor and let's go.
So now if I click messages, so that's, you
can see down here that's.
That's their tab number one and their
person database is tab zero.
So it's quiet nicely and that's all their,
all you really
need to know to so that thing tabs but I'm
gonna
now make this application actually,
actually retrieve messages in
response to that tab selection and, and
display them in a kind of JList.
That we got as our middle panel in this
message database.
So to do that I'm going to go to the
message panel
and I'm gonna get that message called
refresh, so put public void refresh.
And refresh is gonna go retrieve messages.
And I'm also gonna.
I've actually set the selected service in
response to a tree cell
being edited but I also need to set
selected service value
as well and if, because we want there to
be a
selected selection service even if no
one's clicked anything in the tree yet.
And so, here's my selected service and I'm
just setting that.
Selection on my message server.
This is all stuff I implemented in
previous tutorials.
And now we can just say here, if tabIndex
equals 1
then messagePanel dot, whoops, message,
let's
have a look message pane, messagePanel,
yeah
messagePanel.refresh and that should do
the trick.
And when the message panel is refreshed,
I'm
gonna add the titles of the messages to
the.
JList I got in there and we've covered
JList
before so I'm not gonna show you anything
new here.
And but I'm gonna say, private
DefaultListModel here in the message
panel.
Let's call it messageListModel and down
here let's say
messageListModel equals new default
message, new DefaultListModel.
There we go.
And in the other code where I shall go
over to this, it doesn't matter,
I don't need that, in the bit of code
where I actually retrieved some messages.
So long method or theSwingWorker thread
down here.
I'm gonna say after I get the messages
I'll say,
messageListModel,
messageListModel.removeAllElements
to clear the list and then I'll say for
message, message
in retrieve messages, retrieve messages is
a list.
I can say messageListModel,
messageListModel.addElement.
I can pass in there message.getTitle for
the moment.
And one thing I mustn't forget to do and I
always
do forget to do this, is we've gotta set
the list.
Use this message list model, so just copy
that and go down to where I.
I, I think I copied, Ctrl+C.
And I go down to where I create the JList,
I can just pass in the model right there.
And now if I run this and I think on the
messages tab it outputs the messages here.
And actually one, one refinement that I
just,
like, so need and it should make here is.
So I've got my messages there.
That's write that in a new JScrollPane
because that list of potentially infinite
size.
Let's not write in the scroll pane, it's
not use at all really.
So-
whoops-
let's take a look at this.
Now come up.
There we go.
That's much better.
And in a future tutorial we're gonna take
a look at
making this look a bit nicer by
implementing a list renderer.
But that's off the list tutorial and until
next time, happy coding.