Hello, this is John from
caveofprogramming.com and in this tutorial
we're gonna look at implementing a custom
renderer in a JList.
And I'm gonna show you, a JList that has a
JLabel.
I'm sorry, a JPanel in it and that's
really just to
demonstrate that you can put basically
anything you like in a JList.
You can render it any way you like.
And you might wind up, if you can use
editors in lists.
And the answer is well you could with a
bit of work.
But if you want an editable list where you
can edit the actual entries.
You probably want a j table with one
column.
So let's go on now and look at this
renderers.
So, I'm gonna create a new class here in
this gooey package, file new
class, and I'll call it message title
renderer, or maybe, actually let's call it
message list renderer.
That's a good name.
And I'm gonna make message list renderer.
Implement list cell renderer
and let's implement let's
add import and implement the one method
that has.
And this is pretty simple.
I'm gonna give this a public, constructor
so message list renderer.
And in the constructor, I'm gonna create
some components, Now what I'm gonna
show you is gonna be pretty simple, and
probably using a panel really is overkill.
But I just wanna demonstrate here that we
can bump anything we like into that.
So let's have a private jPanel.
jPanel panel.
And let's put a jLabel on that panel.
Label.
And I guess I won't put anything else on
that panel here, which is why
the panel would be overkill, but you could
put other stuff on that panel, of course.
So, in the constructor, I'm going to say
panel = new JPanel.
And let's say label equals new j-label.
So, we've got a panel and a label and so
in this gat list our render component.
A little problem here is that eclipses
ought
to completed this and it's not done a
very good job because it hasn't get the
arg, hasn't given the arguments here very
good names.
And yet the documentation that come up
when I hover my
mouse over it, in eclipse, has actual good
names for the arguments.
So when I hover my mouse over that, press
F2 and
eclipse to bring focus to this window,
this help window, I'm gonna
copy the argument list from the
documentation here, so let's
copy that, control C, and then let's paste
that in there, there we go.
Control shift F to format there.
Now, I'm gonna say, in here.
Well let's, let's set an icon on the label
for start so I'm gonna go to my
my chart looking for your graphics
repository graphics here.
And what kind of labels might we want to
use, I could use this and, I don't
know information 24 dot GIF, I suppose,
and yeah, that's, let's go with that.
So, and, I'll copy that and, and
go to Eclipse and go to the images package
that I
created, which is down here and I'll
paste.
So, right-click, paste and if I expand
that now.
Hopefully, we have images in there
information24.gif
and let's set and icon on the label.
So I'll say label.seticon and I'll use my
utils class I've created in an earlier
tutorial.
Utils.,
and feel free to use this class in your
own code, if you want.
And, let's set this to the path is gonna
be images/information24.
Information, I had to think for a minute
there.
Information24.gif.
Okay, so we've got an icon on the label.
And let's say panel.set.
Layout new flowlayout.
And panel.uh, label.
Panel to add label.
And as I said, I feel a bit guilty,
because really
you only need to use the label if you just
want to
have a label rendering your missed item,
but
I'm, so I'm going to put a comment here
note,
this demonstrates, demonstrates using
a arbitrary, arbitrary component as a,
listbox renderer.
But, it's, probably,
probably overkill to
use J panel when JLabel
could be used directly.
So it's just
probably overkill in this case.
Okay, bear with me.
In this case.
Okay, I just wanted to put that comment on
there,
because we haven't really got a need for
that panel here.
But anyway, I'll carry on.
So we set an icon on the label and you
wanna do as much setup as possible in the
constructor of your renderer because you
don't wanna keep building
panels and things in this, get this
renderer and component.
Now, this get this cell render a
component, just returns
whatever component you want to render the
items in your list.
And it's basically the same as get three
cell renderor component
and it's said that it's a lot simpler for
lists than it is for trees,
so let's go to let's go to the
message panel here, and I'm gonna look for
the A bit where I actually add stuff to
the list,
instead of, instead of adding message dot
get
title, I'm gonna add, a message directly
itself.
And, now, message is gonna show up.
As this value here some would say message,
message equals
cast and value to a message and then
presto.
I can import bubble.message, and now I can
say let's set a text
on the label.text,
and than say message.get title.
Message.get title.
And, finally I night want to.
I might want to when, when you click on
the item in
the list, you probably wanna show that i,
it's actually been selected.
So this, this is true if the item is
currently selected.
So, I'm gonna say here,
label.setbackground and
for the background here, let's have a
couple of colors here.
I'll say 'private selected color', and
that's going to be a type color.
And private color let's call it
normalColor.
Might be import for color.
Now I can say, selectedColor = new color.
New color.
And let's use the RGB form of the
constructor,
so I've got integers here from nought to
255.
And I'll say maybe, I don't know, to 10?
To 10, and I'll make it blue, so to 55 for
blue there.
And normal color, let's make that
color.white.
Okay, and now I can say here, in get, get
cell render a component,
I can say label the set background and
cell has focus, question mark.
So I'm using the turnery, conditional
operator here,
or you could use the initial statement, of
course.
And let's say if it does have focus.
I'm gonna set it equal to selected color.
And if it doesn't have focus I'm gonna set
it equal to normal
color.
And I need to return that component, so
return label.
No, return panel.
Although returning label would do the
trick.
Let's see how that looks.
And
I'm gonna, in my Message panel I need to
set this message list,
this Jlist to use that, renderer, sorry,
yeah, the renderer.
Okay.
So, here's my message list and let's say
Message
list.setCellRenderer new
messageListRenderer.
There we go, messageListRenderer.
And let's run that and see how it looks.
I'm not sure how this is going to look.
Messages.
So I've got messages there.
Eclipse has hidden it for me.
And at the moment it looks a bit rubbish,
and two reasons.
The alignment is all wrong which I can fix
with the
flow layout, and the other thing is that
on a label.
Labels are transparent, by default.
So they show, the color of whatever's
behind them.
So, to fix that, I could even make the
label not transparent.
Or,
why don't we just set the color on the
panel instead?
That'll also do the trick.
So, in fact just to show you here,
I'll say label.setopaque and set that
equals true.
And in my flow layout when I create a flow
layout, I'm gonna say give it an
ar, an arguments constructor
flowlayout.left float to left align
there, and let's see how that looks,
hopefully better.
And
now, actually it still doesn't look good
because
the label's not taking up all the space.
So, I think what I'll do is instead of
doing that, let's just get rid
of the label.setopaque and let's say
panel.setbackground instead
of label.setbackground, and let's see how
that looks.
So here we go.
That looks a lot better.
That's what I want it to look like,
basically.
And if you click on an item then hit
guess.
Selected.
Okay, that's it for this tutorial.
And until next time.
Happy coding.