Hi, welcome back, in this tutorial we're
gonna look at responding to selections in
JList.
So in the moment if I run this
application, here in this
panel here, I've got a JList list which
I've added objects to.
I have to type message and messages since
it's an object I created myself.
And because you could just add strings to
a JList but either way sometimes you want
actually respond when the user selects a
different item.
So often what you want to do is you want
to have a button like here
and you just get the selection when the
user clicks the button and we've covered
that before.
But what I'm gonna show you in this
tutorial is, how
to actually detect when an item is
selected in a JList.
So, let's go to the message panel and
I'll search for the message list, JList in
here.
And here it is.
And I'm gonna say,
messageList.addListSelectionListener.
And, I'll add a new ListSelectionListener
and I'm going to add do Ctrl+Shift+O to
add the import there.
Doesn't seem to have worked, I've got a
extra bracket there.
Okay, Ctrl+Shift+O, etcetera.
Put the bracket in the right place and I'm
going
to add the unimplemented method it just
the value change method.
And this is called whenever someone clicks
an item on the list.
And all I'm going to do here is I'm going
to get the selection from the list but
I'm going to get the selected object in
the
list, which if you know these strings will
be strings.
Well I've added message objects to
the, o the list, so if I say message,
message equals messageList,
messageList.get, getSelectedValue
rather than getSelected.
So we've seen it get to that index before
and that
get's you the index starting at zero with
the selected item.
If you say getSelectedValue it returns an
object of
whatever kind of thing you added to the
list.
If you added strings, you get strings.
I added these message objects that I
created so I'm gonna get message objects.
So, I'm gonna [UNKNOWN] a message.
Saying string, so I'm typing string.
And now I can say, I can get the text to
that message.
And what I wanna do is
I wanna say, textPane, textPanel.setText
and message.getContents.
Actually the problem with this is I
haven't actually
to define the set text in my message
panel.
So let's go to a text panel, sorry.
So let's go to the text panel here
and give it a public void setText(String
Text).
And this is just gonna wrap the
corresponding method in the underline text
area.
So I could really have just use a text
area directly in this lower panel.
So let's say set text, text.
Here we go, text.
And now when I run this program, I'm going
to get, if I select
an item on the list, the text will appear
in the panel down here.
And I'm going to make one little tweak
here which is I'm
gong to go to the message panel and let's
find the retrieveMessages method.
RetrieveMessages.
So, it sets, retrieve messages sets the
items in the list right here.
And I just want to say, after we
finish adding items, let's say
messageList.setSelectedIndex and let's say
zero.
So hopefully.
Now if we get like a default, we get like
the
first item selected and we like the full
text appearing down here.
Although the selection isn't showing which
may be a little bug in my application.
But that's okay because actually I don't
think it's
the same with Outlook but it wouldn't
surprise me.
So let's, let's also I'm just gonna do one
little thing that's not actually connected
to this at all but I just think might be
text in this text panel down here.
It looks a little bit like it's too close
to the border.
For that, I'm just going to go to my text
panel.
I'm going to say, here, text, text,
area, text area, area.setBorder
and I'm going to set the border to a
BorderFactory.createEmptyBorder.
Let's set the import and create empty
border and
I'll use the right, that type of anti
border
that takes arguments and I'm just gonna
put like
a 5 pixel, anti border around the text
area.
So if we look at that now the text is a
little bit indented, well
it's a little bit not quiet as flush to
the edge as it was before which is good.
So I'll leave it there for this tutorial
and join me again next.
Next time and until then, happy coding.
[BLANK_AUDIO]