Hello, this is John from
caveofprogramming.com.
And in this tutorial, we're gonna look at
setting the font.
So if I run the application here in this
mess, message panel above, you've got a
text window here.
It's, it's actually a J text area, and I'm
gonna show you how to set the font on that
text area, but actually, Swing components
in general, the ones that display text
usually have a set font method, and I'm
going to show you the set font for J text
area that equally well applies to labels
and buttons and all kinds of things.
So my text area is actually within this
text panel class I created.
And I'm going to call here textArea, so
this is the J text area here.
I'm going to call text area.setfont.
And to set font, and this method as I say
is the same for labels and all kinds
of controls, I'm gonna pass a new font
object,
and let's have the input load, Ctrl +
Shift load.
Now this has a constructor that takes
three arguments, and
the first argument specifies what kind of
font you want.
So actually in this tutorial I'm gonna
show you
how to use what's called logical fonts and
Swing.
And the way the logical fonts work is that
you say what kind of
fonts you want and Swing then chooses an
appropriate font from the system for you.
You can also load specific font files, and
we'll look at that in the next tutorial.
So the first argument here is a string.
And the string can be one of serif,
sans-serif monospaced, dialogue or
dialogue input.
So dialogue and dialogue input are kinds
of fonts for dialogue boxes.
And monospaced means a font where each
character takes up
the same amount of space, and that's
useful for displaying data.
For example, if someone sent you a, like a
file that's in CSV format exactly,
that's a bad example; well, a file where
they've protect file, where they've tried
to sort of create a table using text; now,
then you want all the
characters to be the same lengths, so the
different rows of the table line up.
And serif mean a font that has
basically twiddles on it and sans-serif
without twiddles.
Let's take a look at examples rather than
me just talking.
So let's start with serif here and the
second argument is whether
you want it to be plain, bold or italic,
and I'm going to
go for plain here and certainly is
aesthetic variable
of the font class, and the final argument
is the size of the font in points.
I'm going to try setting a 20 point font
here.
So let's take a look at that.
And if I run that and now, we can see that
we've got a serif font here.
And you can tell it's serif because if you
look, for example, at
the bottom of the Y here, it's got a
little bulb on it.
It has various twiddles that you wouldn't
get in a sans-serif.
Let's take a look at some more examples.
If I set here sans-serif, sans-serif and
run that,
sans-serif font doesn't have those
twiddles, so
now you can see there's no bulb at the
bottom of the Y.
The H doesn't have like bulbs on it.
If you look at the serif font, H is like,
at
the ends of the lines, it's got like a
little thing.
And that's missing in the sans-serif.
So sans-serif fonts are just plainer than
serif fonts.
Actually, I don't want to turn this in to
a lesson on types
of fonts, but I'll just show you the three
most useful
types, and the other one, monospaced is
sometimes useful.
So if we look now, kind of looks a
bit like a sort of, sort of teletype type
thing.
And, but I think actually, the one that
looks best for
this message dialogue is the serif, so
let's stick with that.
And as I say, you can make that, bold or
italic, instead of plain.
Okay, so I'm going to leave it there for
this tutorial, and
in the next tutorial, we're gonna look at
how to load font
files so you can set specific font if you
want if you
want to, so join me again then and until
then, happy coding.