Hello, this is John from
caveofprogramming.com and
in this tutorial, we're going to look
at loading particular font files so you
can set the exact font that you want.
Now, let's just run the application and
I'm gonna set
the font this time on the headers of these
messages.
So I'm gonna change the font on, this is
actually a jLabel.
And I'm gonna change the font on that.
So I've downloaded a font file and I have
it in this folder somewhere.
Let's see, somewhere I've got, I found on
the Internet this CrimewaveBB.ttf.
So I'm gonna copy that and that's a font
file of course.
And, in my project I'm gonna make a new
package.
I'm gonna say, new package.
And I'm gonna call that fonts.
And I'm gonna paste my font file into
there.
So now it's there.
And now in my GUIutils.java, in here I've
actually got a message for loading icons.
I'm gonna just copy that message.
So, copy that method.
Sorry, although some people call them
messages.
And I'm gonna change this so it can load
the font file.
So I'll say create font instead of create
icon, and
that's gonna return a font and it's gonna
take a path.
And it's gonna return, it's gonna be a
system.class get resource.
And that returns the URL.
And then if the URL is null, we'll say
unable to load font, and say what the path
was, and then if that goes well, I'm gonna
say font.
Font equals, instead of doing new image
icon here.
I'm gonna say, let's let the font class.
You know?
Let's say font.createfont.
And the first argument here is a static,
integer, variable from the font class.
And it can be either true type font, or
type 1 font.
And since I've got Chrome, [UNKNOWN] .ttf,
in other words,
true type font, I'm gonna set that to true
type font.
And the second argument here is it's gonna
be the actual
font that you wanna that you wanna sorry,
the second argument here, lost my
train of thoughts there for a second, is
gonna be a stream.
On this font file, an input stream that
can stream this font file.
And to get that input stream we just have
to say URL.
Dot let's get focused there.
URL.openstream, so the URL points not to
the internet but to this font file.
Because that's the path that we're gonna
put in, we just need to open
stream to get an input stream from this
URL and that will load the font.
okay, so.
And after that actually, I could say
URL.closestream.
URL dot where are we.
I'm pretty sure there's a closeStream
method.
Okay, maybe I imagined that.
So I won't worry about that.
And let's just return to font then in that
case.
I don't know why I thought there was a
closeStream method.
Okay, so here.
I need to say return font, so I'm gonna
say return font.
Format thing there, somehow I've messed up
these brackets, so let's let's take a
look.
So we load the font with create font and
then I
wanna say return font, and oh yeah, put
semi colon in.
And I think we're now in business.
We've also got to handle the exceptions
that can arise when you call create font.
So we're gonna do surround with tri catch
there, and I'm gonna say here.
So, it will throw a font format exception
if you if you can't
if, if their font file has the wrong
format altogether.
So in that case, let's just say sys, sys
err, font, well, if
that adds the formats in font file,
that'll do, plus path.
And here.
If there's an IO exception, probably it
just can't read
the file because of, I don't know
permissions or something.
And let's say, Unable to read font file,
and plus path.
Okay we're almost there and now, I'm gonna
have to set this to no, because
there's the error here is that it's, this
variable could be uninitialized because,
if you can't, you know, if, if this throws
an exception, the font's not
gonna get set to anything, and you've got
to initialize your variables in Java.
So, so that equal to null.
So, this returns null if it can't load the
font.
And now I'm gonna go to my message panel
now and there is a little complication
still to come.
So let's look for, actually, yeah, it's
the
message, this renderer actually renders
those message titles.
And we've got this label here.
And I need to set the font on that label.
So, I'm gonna say here in the constructor
message this renderer, Label.setFont,
So it has a setFont method just like jText
area, for example.
And then I'm gonna say, util.createFont,
and I'm gonna pass in a path, /fonts/
and my font's called crimewavebb.ttf.
And now that's, that won't work in itself.
Because if I run that it's just gonna look
invisible and
the reason is that the reason is that
where are we, utils.
So when you do create font, this returns a
font
with a size of one point, which is
basically invisible.
And to get, to get this to work, once you
return to font so this returns a
font, I need to then call the dot derive
method of the font class.
And I'm gonna use the method that takes
style and a size.
You'll notice some different methods for
style and size here.
But I've found that if you don't set the
style then it
still seems to be invisible for reasons
that I don't fully understand.
So I'm gonna use this method here that
sets the style and the size.
Now the style is just font dot plain bold
or italic.
Let's try making it bold.
See what that looks like.
Font dot bold.
And I'll do control to go to add the font
class.
And then, I want to, I'm gonna use the
rest of this
method that then just takes the font size
for the next document.
So let's try setting that to, I don't
know, 22.
See how that looks.
And so that should do the trick and I'll
do control > shift > F there to format it.
And let's run that.
So basically you return the font using
your url, input screen.
And you call derive font to create the
derive font, font
from the initial font, which will be the
font you actually use.
So I'll run that.
Now if I look at my message headers,
they're in bold and they're in this
crimewavebb.ttf.
Actually, I'm going to try to plain that,
because I
think it would look better and probably 20
is enough really.
Okay, so that's it for this tutorial.
Join me again next time and until then,
happy coding.
[BLANK_AUDIO]