Now this this isn't really a tutorial.
It's really more just mentioning something
that I
forgot to do earlier, to tell the truth.
Which is that this connection preferences
dialogue
from [UNKNOWN] point view is all fine, but
I forgot to actually make you configure
the
database connection, so it wasn't actually
doing anything.
and, and, so I just implemented that and I
am not going to get through
it in detail, because there is no new
swing concepts and and it would be boring.
But basically I given an database switch
over some private instance variables,
and I've given it a connect method which
also disconnects if it's
already connected and then reconnects and
I've wrapped that in a inject
messaging controller, and then in the main
frame in the GUI package here.
I've basically made it so that the prefs
dialogue let's go down here.
When that's closed, it reconfigures the
connection.
So, that's it for now.
Just something that I've got to do
basically.
Oh yeah, and also when the application
starts up somewhere up here I've
made it so that it loads the, oh yeah,
here, it loads the defaults.
And configures the configures the actual
database
connection was previously just loading the
default
so much, from doing anything with them
apart from pulling them in the dialog.
So that's it for now.
And until next time, happy coding.