Hello.
In this tutorial we're gonna knock, making
your tables editable.
So if you use the default table model that
you can use with the Jtable.
Your table will be editable by default.
In this tutorial we've actually created
our own model.
And it's in this gooey package and its
person table model.
And, if you create your own table model,
which I think is worth doing, cause it
gives you a lot more control, you gotta
do a couple things, make a column editable
[SOUND].
And, in this tutorial, I'm just gonna make
one column editable.
And we will, we'll look at a couple of
other cases in future tutorials.
But I'm gonna make this, name column here,
editable.
So, to do this, it's, it's pretty simple.
The first thing to do is, in your,
Actually,
maybe it's, maybe it's the only thing to
do.
I'm trying to think.
Okay, so let's have a look.
So in your model class, your table model
has to
override well, in this case, it extends
abstract table model.
And you need to return true, if you want a
particular cell to be editable.
And a particular method, which we're going
to hae to override here.
So I'm going to right-click in my
personTableModel class and
I'm going to go to source > override
implement methods.
And down here, we've got this
isCellEditable method.
Then click OK there and to make yeah,
actually, we're gonna have to
override this method and it's gonna be one
other thing to do as well.
So, so you've got a class, it extends
abstract table model and you
override the is cell editable method and
that gets passed in a row index.
It's in a column index which are
zero-based.
In this case I wanna say that, any row in
column one is gonna be editable.
So I need to say, let's do switch.
Switch, call, and then say.
Case one return true.
Let's say the default is default return
false.
So I'm going to return false to say all
the columns are not editable
except for this column one, which is gonna
be, is going to be editable.
Actually, if I already run that you'll
already see that [INAUDIBLE].
And by the way, I've also in the
constructor.
I should have explained that.
So in main frame, we've got codes.
We had code previously that refreshed the.
That reloaded the database, sorry.
So you've got a refresh button, and if
someone clicks refresh we get a refresh
event occurred.
And there was a loaded code in there, but
I moved it to
it's own refresh method in mainframe and
I'm now calling that in constructor.
So let's just a look and that means that
my
data loads automatically if it can when
when the application runs.
So yep, we got a refresh call there.
Anyway, that's nothing to do with this
tutorial.
I just wanted to quickly explain.
So I've overwrite, overwritten my
[UNKNOWN]
editable method in the table model.
And now it already means that I can edit.
If I double-click there I can edit the
name, but as soon as I finish editing if
I hit, hitting return it's not gonna
remember that
value, it's gonna go back to the cell
renderer.
Which is gonna use the value stored by the
data model for this table.
So, the second thing I need to do is I
need to
override a method here, let's go to, let's
right click, and go to
source, override implement methods and
it's a method.
Called set value at.
So I'm gonna click OK there.
And again here, we've got a row index and
column index and we've
got a value that we want to set for that
row and column.
I'm gonna get rid of the [UNKNOWN] here
and I'm just going to say, again.
Switch call, switch call.
And the default is, is going to do
nothing.
It's going to return.
But case 1, so if we've got column 1 here.
I'm going to do something, and then you
mustn't forget the break.
Otherwise, you'll carry on down here.
And I'm going to say.
Here where we want to set the value at
whichever row and column this is in our
database.
And this table model a, is actually
storing
the values in this in this kind of list.
This list of person objects.
And that's that's that's eb that database
list.
Is set down here and called set data.
So let's just actually, let's just check
and say if DB equals null.
And we can't do anything.
Well, not in this, sorry.
In the setValue method.
We want to say, okay, if there's not data
then just return.
Because we're not going to do anything
with it.
If DB equals no return.
Just return.
But now, if the DB is not equal to null.
We can set the value in this list of
person objects.
So I can probably the easiest thing to do
is just to get the reference from the
person, so I can say, like person I
need to get the reference so that person
object.
The specified column or row yeah
[INAUDIBLE] here is getting a bit tricky.
Okay, this, this list has elements in it
and
the elements, yeah, correspond to the rows
in the table.
So element 1 in this list is going to be
row 0 in the table.
In other words, well the first element is
going to be row 0.
So, I want say person,person equals
DV dot get, .get, if that will do the
trick.
So I'm just getting from my list the
person
that I want to change and reference that
person.
And let's put this up here, actually, cuz
I'm gonna need to do this for
any value and then here I can just set the
value and say person dot set.
And in this case, call him on its name,
and I just want
to set him a new name, which will be the
value paste in here.
I just want to cache that to a string,
like that.
So it's pretty simple really, all you have
to do is
you get the value, your given a row and a
column.
And you just set the value in whatever
data model you're using.
Flat row and column, casting this value to
an appropriate, appropriate value.
It's going to be string in this case.
And now, if I run that, hopefully, oh
yeah.
I also want to explain so although we're
doing db dot get, db is a list.
We're doing get from the list.
This reference will simply point at a
value that's actually in the list.
So if we change this, we're changing the
person objects in this list.
And that's why this, this is gonna work.
So if I run this now.
And let's change this to Joe, Joe Smith,
Joe Smith.
And hey, presto, now it's Joe Smith.
Now I'm now gonna save that and load it
again.
And if I run my application again.
i feel flushed with success now and then
it's dismissed in
future we're gonna look at setting a
couple of these other
values and that's going to be a little
more complex well
maybe not so join me again next time and
until next time.
Happy coding.