Hello.
In this tutorial we're gonna have a look
at using check boxes in tables.
And to use a check box in a table is
actually pretty simple
but it's gonna introduce another little
concept that's useful to know about
tables.
At the same time, so at the moment in this
table we've got a U.S. citizen, which is a
column, which is either true or false and
I'm gonna change that to use a check box,
so obviously you can
tick it, if it's true and it's gonna be
not ticked, if it's false.
Now to do that let's go to the table model
and actually it's in GUI.
So we've got this person, table model.
Which is in the GUI package cuz it's a
kind of a
model for GUI component, rather than the
data, proper data model and such.
And we've got, let's maximize the editor
here.
We've got this column at the end,
U.S. citizen and that's, that's column
let's see.
So, looking at previous code we've written
here, that's column number 5.
Now what I need to do is, there's going to
be a couple of things here.
But firstly I need to right click here and
go to Source > Override Implement Methods
and there is this getCommonClass method
here, so I'm gonna override that.
And so we're overriding a method of the
abstract table
model here, and all table models have to
have this method.
And getCommonClass has this funny return
type class brackets question mark.
And that's saying basically we need to
return
a class an object of type class and class
is a template class, it gets awfully
confusing
but this is simpler than it looks once you
see how it actually works and I'm going
to put in here, this is actually, this
argument's
actually column and I'm going to do switch
on column and we're going to have a bunch
of cases here and actually.
This is gonna be pretty similar to this
switch, you can get the value of that.
So I'm just gonna use that, let's copy
that.
And paste it in up here and I can use this
as a guide.
Now, okay so the first column, column
zero.
Well, yes, I'm gonna return to class for
each of these columns and that
is gonna actually cause the is U.S.
citizen to render as a check box.
And if we return boolean for this class,
it's
gonna, it's gonna render this check box in
a table.
And a table renders a bunch of default
types in different ways and
the main ones have string in it,
string numerical values which is aligned
differently.
And then these boolean values have a check
box.
So let's just have a look at how that
works.
So for get idea, I'm gonna return integer.
[SOUND].
And, well that's my window closing.
I thought it was a gun going off for a
minute, but luckily it wasn't.
Okay, and for name I need to return
String.class
and this .class just returns an object of
type class.
Class is confusingly a class in Java and
yeah, get occupation.
I, again, I'm just gonna return string for
moment for most of these.
So a little later I'm going to look at how
you can
put combo boxes in tables and then we'll
return something other than string.
So string there.
And string and taxID.
Let's see taxID.
GetTaxID is returning what?
It's returning, hover my mouse so it
returning strings.
So let's make that a string as well.
So return String.class and here's the
bit that's particularly relevant to this
tutorial.
For each U.S citizen I'm gonna say return
Boolean, capital B .class,
like that and if you return a, yeah I need
target default value there.
Although it shouldn't be anymore cons.
This, this collection never be more than
six but Java's
gonna say you know, what if it is more
than six?
You gotta return to something.
So then I'll just return null.
I think that will work.
Yeah return null.
Now okay, let's run that and now we can
see already that we've got the this
boolean column which we return
Boolean.class is rendering as a checkbox.
But we can't actually tick it or untick
it.
To make it editable, we've got to go to is
setEditable
and say case 5 return true, that's for
column 5 you want it to be editable.
We also need to store the values, so I am
going to say here in setValue at
case 5 person.setUSCitizens
and that's gonna be now boolean value.
So we're gonna cast the value that were
passed in here
to a boolean cuz that's what it's gonna
be, basically boolean.
There we go.
That'll do that trick.
If I run that now, we've got, let's take
Sue and say Sue's your citizen.
And just to prove it works, I just reload
the data.
It didn't seem to work actually.
Let's take that.
Oh yeah, I forgot to save it.
Save the data, then refresh.
And we can see that the check has remained
checked.
And I'll run it again and just-
There you go.
You can see it still ticked there.
So, pretty minimal work to get a check box
in your table.
You just need to return the boolean value
for that column.
Boolean.class must be returned and get
column class.
And you've gotta insert editable.
You need to, is that, sorry,
isCellEditable
you gotta return true for that column.
And finally you probably want to provide a
set value at method.
A set value at code, some code for set
value at for that
column so that you can literally set the
value in your date model [UNKNOWN].
That's all for this tutorial and join me
again next time.
And until then happy coding.