Hello, this is John from
caveofprogramming.com, and in
this tutorial we're gonna look at table
cell renderers.
So there are basically two work, two ways
to set your own completely custom
renderer on a table cell, and one way is
to say
table.get column and then you can get a
column from
the table by supplying a a integer.
So like get column zero, will get me the
first column in the table.
And then you can say set cell renderer.
And that would set a renderer just for
that table column.
But I'm not gonna do that here.
What I'm gonna do here is, I'm going to
set a renderer
for a particular class of object that I've
added to the table.
So I'm going to say table.set
defaultRenderer.
And here I'm going to supply a class.
And I'm going to supply the class of the
employment category.
So I'll say employmentCategory.class.
And employmentCategory is an enumeration,
you may remember from a previous tutorial
that is, it's one of the, data kind of
objects in my table.
And at the moment I'm just displaying it
as a string.
But, here I'm gonna set a new renderer for
it using a combo box.
And now here I can supply a renderer,
which has to implement the table cell
renderer interface.
so, I'm going to say here
EmploymentCategoryRenderer.
In fact, I'm going to say new
And this renderer, I'm going to create
now, so let's just put a
semi colon at the end of that line, and
let's go to new class.
Actually, I'll put this in the GUI
package,
and I'll right click and go to new class.
Employment word category renderer, click
Finish.
And let's just say that, that implements
TableCellRenderer, render, renderer.
At the import there and next let's add
the, the missing fields.
So it just gone one method command here.
And now to actually make the table use
this.
I need to go to my table model which is
here.
And in this get common class method that
we've overwritten.
And previously I returned Boolean which
causes the chat box to display at one
point in the table for the is US citizen
column.
And rest of them are all strings apart
from the first one.
The ID which is an integer it just causes
a different alignment in the table.
But I'm gonna go to I think it's column
four here.
Cuz in column four we are, we actually
got less employment category enumeration
objects in there.
And I want to set a renderer for that
particular class.
So I need to go to get column class.
And instead of returning a string, I want
to say that
what's in that particular column of the
table what's in column
four, actually the fifth column because it
numbers from zero is
going to be employment, is going to be an
EmploymentCategory type.
Thing type object.
And when we're actually returning the
values from
the table, you might remember in, where
are we?
So we've got this, we've got this
somewhere, a method
that returns the value for the for the
column.
And see, so, we've got value out, get row
count, get column count, get column class.
And we've got,
Where, actually, is it?
I think I lost it.
Oh yeah, get value at.
Yes, so get value at, is, you might
recall,
is, is actually returning the values from
my personal objects
from my database and getValueat is
returning an employment category
type object, and that's the senior
[UNKNOWN] I've created here.
And we're gonna set a renderer for this in
employment category type.
Now the first thing to fix, is so I've got
my renderer there.
I'm gonna have to fix this up.
But, actually I probably wanna give these
prettier names
because these are just kind of constant
type values.
Like, I'd like self employed to have a
space in it, and a lowercase e.
But I'm gonna, actually I'll fix that up
in a minute, because let's just do this
first.
And, and we can actually run the
application.
So I've got my table cell renderer, and
I've set, in, of, I've done set, I've done
set before renderer for this particular
class, and in my rendeerr, I'm going to
actually have a public, private, J combo
box, combo.
And, at the import there, and in a
construct
here, I'm going to give it constructor,
employment category, renderer.
And there, I'm just going to add the
values
of, from the employment categories
enumerations to my combo box,
and of course, if you weren't working with
enumeration,
you can add whatever you like to that
combo box.
But, I'm going to say combo equals new J
And the simplest way to get values into a
combo box
is just to supply them to the constructor
as an array.
And to get the possible values here of my,
employment category as an array,
I can say, employmentcategory,Values
there.
And that will return the different
possible
values for employment category as an
array.
And now all those, all I really have to do
is.
I need to return the combo in my sort, get
[UNKNOWN] component.
And let's just hover the mouse over that
press F2 to get focused on this help
window.
And I'm just gonna copy this this list of
parameters from the help Ctrl + C.
Because it looks nicer than this aug zero
aug one.
And so on the eclipse is filled in.
I'm just gonna paste that node Ctrl+V and
do Ctrl+Shift+F to format.
And now, value will be the actually
numeration
value that's in this particular cell of
the table.
So I wanna say combo.set selected item and
supply the
value there to actually set the right
thing in the combo.
And now if I run that hopefully this will
work.
Okay so it does work, but you can see that
the the
combo is very, the height of it is is not
really enough.
So I'm going to go to my table panel where
I create a table.
And I'm going to say table.set row height.
Let's set that.
Let's try 20 for the row height and see
how that looks.
So if I run that and, I think that looks
quite a lot better, may be even 25.
Let's try 25 and run that.
And, so now the final touch I can do here
is to get my
numeration to return, to have a two
string method that supplies nice looking
values here.
And by the way you'll notice that this
combo box doesn't do anything at the
moment.
And that's just cause I'm, I'm sending a
render at the moment.
And then in the next tutorial we'll set
the
editor to make this combo up, combo box
actually function.
But in this tutorial it's just all about
displaying it.
And you can display it any how you
like, of course, by returning some
component that,
you know, you could have your own
component,
draws its own stuff, and looks really
funky.
It wouldn't like it.
But I'm just going to use a combo box for
simplicity.
So in Employment category here, this is an
enumeration and
objects of this enumeration type are
actually in my table.
I'm going to give this to constructor, so
I'll put a semicolon after the
last enumeration value and say private,
because
the constructors of enumerations have to
be private.
And I'll say, I'll get that stringText and
I'll also have a private string text here.
Private instance variable.
And in the constructor I'll say this .text
equals text.
And for the two string method, if I right
click and go to, source over items in that
methods.
Just got a two string here.
And there I'm just gonna return text,
return text.
And the place to supply the text here is,
right here where you create your actual
enumeration constants.
So I'm gonna say here employed and let's
just copy that.
And Ctrl+C and paste it in here, here, and
here.
And so I'm going to have self-employed
with space, unemployed, and other.
And now if I run that, you see the thing
is that in my renderer here, I'm supplying
employment category enumeration constants
to my [UNKNOWN], to my combo box.
And the combo box will call just call
two string on the objects to actually
display them.
And that's why this works.
So if I run this now, I'm going to get
nicely formated values in my combo boxes.
That's it for this tutorial, and in the
next tutorial we're gonna make this, these
cells actually editable, so join me again
then, and until then, happy coding.