Hello, this is John from
caveofprogramming.com and in this tutorial
we're going to look at setting editors on
table cells.
So, I've already implemented a custom
renderer in the last tutorial here.
This employment category table cell.
And the employment category column
actually contains
a norm constants and an enumeration class
I created.
And we're displaying this with this check
box, with this combo box.
But what I want to do now is make this
cell, these cells,
this column actually editable so we can
change the values in this combo
box.
So, the first thing to do is, so I'm gonna
go to my table panel here.
And I'm already setting a default renderer
for the employment category class.
And I'm gonna do a similar thing for the
editor.
I'm gonna say table.setdefault editor.
And I'm gonna sa employmentcategory.class
which is the class of objects that's in
that stable column and then say new
employment category editor.
So, let's change from renderer to edit
all.
And that's what I've gotta implement in
this tutorial.
So, I'm just gonna copy that.
Save it, and I'm gonna now right click my
GUI
package and go to new class, let's paste
in the employment category editor.
And this has to implement, implement,
implements table cell
editor as you expect but since since table
cell editor has quite a lot of methods
table cell editor.
I think that's right.
Let's see, so I'll just click this error
message here and
because my renderer implements table cell
renderer, so the editor is gonna
implement table cell editor here, I don't
know why eclipse is being difficult there.
Okay.
But all's well that ends well.
Now the unimplemented methods, there's
quite a lot of
them as you can see and to get default
implementation.
So most of those I'm just gonna say,
extends AbstractCellEditor.
I've struck cell editor, which will give
me,
which will implement most of these methods
for me.
I'm gonna go to add unimplemented methods.
Well that didn't work, hang on.
Let's add the imput there and then save
that and add unimplemented
methods and then there are just two that I
have to implement now.
And I'm also gonna right click here.
And I'm not sure, actually, if this is
really strictly necessary.
But I'm gonna go to, is cell editable.
And let's return through there.
But this probably isn't necessary because
I'm gonna
fix this in my table model as well.
But, might as well, change this just in
case it makes a difference, I don't know.
And now, I'm going to use a combobox here
and if
you had kind of jazzed up your combobox in
your renderer.
And set the colors on it and things like
that.
You probably wanna have your renderer here
as a private variable, or something like
that.
And get the, get the convo maybe in the
constructor or this class,
from a renderer so you get the same combo
with the same colors.
But, in this case I'm just using a generic
combo with my renderer.
So I'll use a generic.
Editor as well.
Let's add a constructor here.
In constructor, I can say, combo equals
new J combo
box and in this case, since I want to
render an
enumerated type, I am gonna add some
values to my
combo box, just like in a renderer by
saying, implement category.
This is my enumeration type.values.
Which will get my my enumeration
constants.
And, you could add whatever values you
want in there, of course.
As long as they're consistent with what's
actually
in the table, or can be in the table.
So, n gets an editor, editor component,
I'm gonna return that combo.
In Get Cell Editor Value, I'm going to
return combo.getSelected item.
And finally, in getCellEditorComponent I
need to
say combo.setSelectedValue, just like in
the renderer.
setSelectedItem, sorry.
That's going to be set to value which is
this here.
The actual value of the table cell passed
in.
And I also want to add an actionListener
to
my combo like you do with buttons.So new
action.
I'll have an anonymous class here, where I
implement the action performed method.
Let's import action listener, and an
action performed method here.
And in here I just want to call fire
editing stopped.
That's really important, to tell your
table cell to stop using the editor and
go back to using the renderer and to
update the value in the table modeler.
Now we have a little bit of work to do in
the table model now.
I wanna make sure that in get column
class I am returning employment
category.class for the class.
I already implemented this in my renderer
so that's okay.
And I need to implement in
set value at so I need to say case four
'cause we're working on common four here.
Don't forget break.
That's very important, otherwise you'll
get strange errors.
And I'll say person.set untcut and pass in
the value there.
And I'll probably need to cast this
value to the enumeration type, employment
category.
So, I'm providing a set method to actually
set the value of
the data, otherwise my comment would work
but it wouldn't actually set the
value and as soon as you finish clicking
the combobox it would
display whatever value was originally in
the cell if you didn't implement this.
And in getCellEditable I also want to
return
true, to say that that column is editable.
And I think that should do the trick so if
I run this now, I've got this now,
editable comment box.
And if I set this to other, click save and
then click refresh.
Still got a value over there just to prove
that.
Let's quit that.
And let's run it again.
And we've still got other in there, but
I'm gonna set
it back to employed, and maybe I'll set
this to other.
Hit save, just for some variety.
Okay, that's it for this tutorial, join me
again next time.
And until next time, happy programming.