Hello.
This is John from caveofprogramming.com,
and
this is a extra tutorial on setting the
look and feel in Java swing.
So I'm adding this sometime after creating
the original
swing course from cave of programming, and
this is just
because this is actually something which
can at least sometimes
arguably improve the look of your swing
application a lot.
And various people have been asking me
about it so I figured it was time
to include this maybe in in an appendix
or something to the original set of
tutorials.
So I've got this swing application that
we've been
working on in [UNKNOWN] tutorials, and it
looks like this.
But Java actually let's you set the look
and feel of the interface.
And by default you get this kind of swing
default kind of swing interface.
And actually although I'm running on
Windows here.
A, a swing application in my experience
never looks like a native application.
So you'll never get something that looks
completely like a Windows application.
And if you wanted one you would have to
use
not Swing but the somewhat similar and yet
different SWT.
Toolkit which you can download for free.
And that actually uses native components,
rather than drawing things itself, swing
does.
However, you can change the look and feel
of swing, maybe get one you're happy with.
So if you go to Google here, and
search for swing look and feel, you'll get
information.
And go to the docs.oracle.com, site.
And you can, you'll find a whole page
about how to set the look and feel.
And the built in look and feels in Java
used to be all pretty
rank to tell you the truth, pretty bad,
but some of them now are pretty good.
So to set the look and feel you
just call UE manager.setlookandfeel and
then you pass
in the name of a class that you want to
set a look and feel to.
And you can download some professionally
designed looks and fields,
looks and feels in Java files and just put
them in the build path
of your application in the normal way and
the way that you
does any [UNKNOWN] by sort of
right-clicking and going to build path.
Configure build path and add a jar,
external jar.
And and then you can set the, the looks
and feels to those using an appropriate
class name.
But let's look here at just the built in
ones, so I'll try setting this.
And see that this is gonna be, well I
would say pretty bad.
I'm gonna go to the constructor of my main
frame here,
and just paste this in and it throws a
bunch of exceptions.
So I'm gonna surround with try catch, in
fact
I'm just gonna change the first one here
to exception.
And get rid of all the others because I'll
catch all these exceptions just
by trying to catch exception here which is
the parent class of all exceptions.
And let's just put a sys out here and say
can't set look and feel, just in case that
fails.
And I'll run this.
So I'm setting it a metal look and feel
just by specifying this class name that
I've got.
Got from a documentation and if I run
that it doesn't actually look to me any
different.
Maybe the metal look and feel is the
default.
Let's try a different one.
So let's try this moti, motif look and
feel or however you pronounce it.
And this is gonna look rubbish again but
in a moment,
I am gonna show you one that's gonna look
really good.
So, all set, I run now.
And so this looks like something that's
running on motif
I guess but I don't want it to look like
that.
So let's, if, if you look here in the
sidebar,
I think here, there's something about the
members look and feel.
Here we go, members look and feel.
Which is actually pretty nice, if you look
at that, it's really not bad.
so, I'm gonna set that, I'm gonna use this
example code.
Like you see here.
Which actually iterates through the
different installed looks and
feels, so you can print them out if you
want.
And if it finds the Nimbus one, it
sets set, then it just throws an exception
there.
So let's try that.
I'll paste this in here.
And I will just say here again, sys out,
cont, set look and feel.
So what we're doing here is, this is just
using ui manager.
Don't get ensnared, looks and feels, looks
and feels.
Iterating through them and for each look
and feel here, it gets the
name and you could display that if you
want to see what's installed.
And if one of them contains the letters
Nimbus, it does seven can feel, why it
doesn't set the numbers directly just with
the
class name, which you could do, I don't
know.
Maybe the size class differs in different
releases of Java.
I'm not sure.
Anyway, let's try this.
So I'll run that and here we got the
nimbus looking field.
One thing to be aware of is that because
things will now take up slightly different
amounts of space possibly, you may
introduce little
bugs in to your application like this one.
And what's happened here is that this
preferences dialog is
just not wide enough to support the extra
sort of padding.
With the nimbus and nimbus look and feel.
So if I find where I set the size on my
dialog
here, I maybe just need to set it a little
bit wider.
That's 20, 20.
This is my preferences dialog code.
And Window Preferences.
And it's still not good.
Let's try 380.
And if this
doesn't work, actually, I just fix this on
my own time.
But what I wanted to show you-
Yeah, so we're widening this but there's
clearly
something else that I've got to fix here.
In fact I will fix it.
I'll go away, fix it, and come back in
just a second.
Hi there, I'm back again, and in fact what
I had to do was not animate the title of.
A bit wider, but also set the fill, the
grid by constraints fill.
And to horizontal, for just for the text
fields.
So you see that set in the looking field
is not without hazard, but
it probably is really worth it, if you
want your application to look nice.
And who doesn't?
Okay, so that's it for this tutorial, and
If there's anything else
that you want to know feel free to drop me
a line.
Although, I can't absolutely promise to
answer but I'll try.
And check out my other courses on New
Demi.
I've got my other course coming up on
Android very soon and there's
also a course on web programming and Java
and lots of great stuff.
So that's it for now and until next time,
happy coding!